<?xml version="1.0"?>

<advantages>

    <advantage name="Age" type="background">
        <cost points="-2" levels="1" max="14"/>
        <description>
            Starting age is one year older than normal for each level of
            this disadvantage. Standard starting age is 16. Maximum
            starting age is 30. This disadvantage allows more skills and
            other advantages to be purchased. A starting age above 30
            does not grant any further points.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Branded criminal" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <description>
            You have been marked as a criminal. -2 point
            disadvantage for petty theft or something similar,
            -5 for something major (maybe dishonour in a society
            which highly values honour) which will cause major
            social problems. The brand is obvious for all to see.
            Note that such a person is not considered an outlaw,
            and to have repaid their debt to society. However, as
            always, people will be prejudiced against the character.
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Black sheep" type="background">
        <cost points="-3"/>
        <description>
            The character is the black sheep of the family, and can
            expect no support from them in times of need. Indeed, they may
            actively try to cause problems for him, or others who dislike
            the family may seem him as a way of getting even, without
            invoking a blood feud.
        </description>
    </advantage>


    <advantage name="Dark secret" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <description>
            You have a secret in your past which is best left
            hidden. If someone were to find it out, or to make it
            public, your life could become quite complicated. This
            is a -2 disadvantage if the secret would be annoying
            if let out, or -5 if it would be a serious risk to
            your health (you were a member of some particularly
            reviled cult for instance).
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Favours" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <description>
            You owe favours to a person, who will call them in at
            some point. Repaying the favours should not be a great
            hardship, but ignoring them will gain you a bad
            reputation (and possibly an enemy).
        </description>
    </advantage>


    <advantage name="Orphan" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <description>
            The character is an orphan, with no parents or immediate
            family to stand up for you.
        </description>
    </advantage>


    <advantage name="Pawn of darkness" type="background">
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <description>
            Either from birth, or because of some event in your
            youth, your life is plagued by the interventions of dark
            powers, be they demons, fey or gods. Alternatively, it
            may have been prophesied that such will come about later
            in your life.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Outlaw)" type="background">
        <cost points="-6"/>
        <description>
            An outlaw has been cast out of society for some crime. It is
            illegal to knowingly give aid to an outlaw, or to seek revenge
            for their death. This often makes the life of an outlaw hard,
            for they are fair game for anyone with a grudge to settle.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Slave)" type="background">
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <description>
            Slaves have few rights, but they are not just property. Laws
            exist which protect them from the worst of physical abuse,
            and in most cases, it doesn't make economic sense to damage
            a slave, since they can be expensive, and often useful.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Serf)" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <description>
            With more freedom than a slace, serfs consider themselves
            well up the social ladder compared to the former. The reality
            isn't quite as good though. Serfs don't have much economical
            safety, are restricted in their movements by their lord,
            and are often indebted to many weeks of work on their lord's
            land.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Freeeman)" type="background">
        <cost points="+0"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A freeman is the norm for player characters, since they have
                the most freedom of anyone in society. They can come and go
                as they please, and they have few obligations, but also their
                lord has few obligations to them either. Freemen are allowed
                to carry weapons, though often they are restricted from
                using knightly weapons.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                Player characters who have a social class less than this can
                be difficult to play, since they will need permissions from
                their lord or master before doing anything.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Guilded)" type="background">
        <cost points="+1"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A guilded character is a member of a guild, and as such
                is allowed to practise their profession. The types of
                professions which require guild membership will vary
                from campaign to campaign.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                A guild member will have certain benefits beyond simply
                being allowed to practise a specialist craft (and earn
                money from it). They may have access to tools and supplies,
                and be able to lodge at guild houses either for free, or
                at a discount. Such guild members are often respected
                within the community at large as well, and have the full
                force of their guild to back them up if anyone starts
                causing trouble for them.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Priest)" type="background">
        <cost points="+2"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A priest is an official member of an organised religion,
                with knowledge of religious traditions, social standing
                and at least some resources of their church.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Landless noble)" type="background">
        <cost points="+3"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A landless noble, often a knight, has many benefits above
                and beyond the common folk, even freemen. Being a noble,
                especially one without land, is no guarantee of wealth
                however, and many such nobles are poor, living by selling
                their sword.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                A knight may carry knightly weapons, and wear knightly
                armour. Their dependents may also be armed as such, in
                order to help defend their noble lord. A knight may also
                own a warhorse.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                A knight can expect aid from other nobles, and respect
                from his lessers, but is expected to live by a code of
                honour, which at least requires him to protect those of
                lesser station from outlaws and wild beasts.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Landowning noble)" type="background">
        <cost points="+6"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A landowning noble, like their landless brethren, have a
                number of responsibilities and benefits, and can be
                considered to be the same in all regards except that they
                own a manor, and have people in fief to them.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                A manor does not guarantee wealth, for often everything
                that is earnt, is spent on upkeep, taxes and presenting
                a face of respectability to other nobles.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (High noble)" type="background">
        <cost points="+10"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                Similar to a landowning noble, however, several manors
                are owned by one of this social class, and other nobles
                will answer to him. Again, wealth is not guaranteed.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Bard)" type="background">
        <cost points="+2"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A Bard is both entertainer and loremaster, respected for
                their knowledge of lore and law, and their skills at the
                spinning of tales and song. Bards can expect hospitality
                wherever they travel, and though they can legally expect
                less than a travelling knight may get, they are truly
                welcomed, for often they are the only source of news
                beyond the borders of the local village.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Reputation" type="background">
        <cost points="Varies"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The reputation of a character can greatly affect how others
                react to him. They can be both good and bad, with good
                reputations having a positive cost, and bad ones a negative
                cost.
            </para>

            <para>
                A reputation should be specified at a level (minor - famous),
                and a region it covers. A village wizard might be famous
                in their home village, but unheard of in the next country.
                Regions are as per the area lore skill.
            </para>

            <para>
                Each level of reputation has a difficulty associated with
                it, and this is the target number for an area lore roll
                to have heard of the reputation.
            </para>

            <targetlist bold="yes">
                <valueLabel>Reputation</valueLabel>
                <targetLabel>Cost</targetLabel>

                <entry target="0" value="No reputation (30)">
                    Just for completness. The target number given is that
                    needed to know of someone who has no particular
                    reputation. However, despite what this table says,
                    a person will know of everyone in their home village
                    or street.
                </entry>

                <entry target="1" value="Minor (25)">
                    A not particularly well known reputation. Maybe the wife
                    of an innkeeper, or son of a famous swordsman. A good
                    fraction of people will be aware of them, but they will
                    be unheard of outside the area.
                </entry>

                <entry target="2" value="Small (20)">
                    A small reputation. A reputable craftsman. Most people
                    in the area will have heard of the person, but very
                    few outside the area will have.
                </entry>

                <entry target="4" value="Moderate (15)">
                    Moderately famous, probably due to some particular event
                    that the person was at the centre of. Practically
                    everyone will have heard of the person.
                </entry>

                <entry target="6" value="Well known (10)">
                    Very famous. Everyone knows the person and is aware
                    of their exploits, and the news has travelled wide
                    as well, and a good number of people outside the area
                    will be aware of them.
                </entry>

                <entry target="8" value="Famous/Infamous (5)">
                    This person is so well known, that
                </entry>
            </targetlist>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Wealthy (comfortable)" type="background">
        <cost points="+2"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The character is comfortably well off, and has about a
                1 pound to spend each year from various sources. When the
                character begins play, they have a years worth of money
                available for spending.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>


    <advantage name="Wealthy (rich)" type="background">
        <cost points="+5"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The character is quite rich, and has about 5 pounds to spend
                each year from various sources. When the character begins
                play, they have a years worth of money available for spending.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Wealthy (very rich)" type="background">
        <cost points="+10"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The character is very rich, and has about 20 pounds to spend
                each year from various sources. When the character begins
                play, they have a years worth of money available for spending.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

</advantages>
