<?xml version="1.0"?>

<advantages>

    <advantage name="Age" type="background">
        <cost points="-2" levels="1" max="14"/>
        <description>
            Starting age is one year older than normal for each level of
            this disadvantage. Standard starting age is 16. Maximum
            starting age is 30. This disadvantage allows more skills and
            other advantages to be purchased. A starting age above 30
            does not grant any further points.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Branded criminal" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <description>
            You have been marked as a criminal. -2 point
            disadvantage for petty theft or something similar,
            -5 for something major (maybe dishonour in a society
            which highly values honour) which will cause major
            social problems. The brand is obvious for all to see.
            Note that such a person is not considered an outlaw,
            and to have repaid their debt to society. However, as
            always, people will be prejudiced against the character.
        </description>
    </advantage>


    <advantage name="Dark secret" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <description>
            You have a secret in your past which is best left
            hidden. If someone were to find it out, or to make it
            public, your life could become quite complicated. This
            is a -2 disadvantage if the secret would be annoying
            if let out, or -5 if it would be a serious risk to
            your health (you were a member of some particularly
            reviled cult for instance).
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Favours" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <description>
            You owe favours to a person, who will call them in at
            some point. Repaying the favours should not be a great
            hardship, but ignoring them will gain you a bad
            reputation (and possibly an enemy).
        </description>
    </advantage>


    <advantage name="Orphan" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <description>
            The character is an orphan, with no parents or immediate
            family to stand up for you.
        </description>
    </advantage>


    <advantage name="Pawn of darkness" type="background">
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <description>
            Either from birth, or because of some event in your
            youth, your life is plagued by the interventions of dark
            powers, be they demons, fey or gods. Alternatively, it
            may have been prophesied that such will come about later
            in your life.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Outlaw)" type="background">
        <cost points="-6"/>
        <description>
            An outlaw has been cast out of society for some crime. It is
            illegal to knowingly give aid to an outlaw, or to seek revenge
            for their death. This often makes the life of an outlaw hard,
            for they are fair game for anyone with a grudge to settle.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Slave)" type="background">
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <description>
            Slaves have few rights, but they are not just property. Laws
            exist which protect them from the worst of physical abuse,
            and in most cases, it doesn't make economic sense to damage
            a slave, since they can be expensive, and often useful.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Serf)" type="background">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <description>
            With more freedom than a slace, serfs consider themselves
            well up the social ladder compared to the former. The reality
            isn't quite as good though. Serfs don't have much economical
            safety, are restricted in their movements by their lord,
            and are often indebted to many weeks of work on their lord's
            land.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Freeeman)" type="background">
        <cost points="+0"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A freeman is the norm for player characters, since they have
                the most freedom of anyone in society. They can come and go
                as they please, and they have few obligations, but also their
                lord has few obligations to them either. Freemen are allowed
                to carry weapons, though often they are restricted from
                using knightly weapons.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                Player characters who have a social class less than this can
                be difficult to play, since they will need permissions from
                their lord or master before doing anything.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Guilded)" type="background">
        <cost points="+1"/>
        <description>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Priest)" type="background">
        <cost points="+2"/>
        <description>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Landless noble)" type="background">
        <cost points="+3"/>
        <description>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Social class (Landowning noble)" type="background">
        <cost points="+5"/>
        <description>
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Social class (High noble)" type="background">
        <cost points="+10"/>
        <description>
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Social class (Bard)" type="background">
        <cost points="+2"/>
        <description>
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Reputation" type="background">
        <cost points="Varies"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The reputation of a character can greatly affect how others
                react to him. They can be both good and bad.
            </para>

            <targetlist bold="yes">
                <valueLabel>Reputation</valueLabel>
                <targetLabel>Target</targetLabel>
                
                <entry target="30" value="Minor">
                    Cost is 1.
                </entry>

                <entry target="25" value="Small">
                    Cost is 2.
                </entry>
                
                <entry target="20" value="Moderate">
                    Cost is 4.
                </entry>
                
                <entry target="15" value="Well known">
                    Cost is 6.
                </entry>
                
                <entry target="10" value="Famous/Infamous">
                    Cost is 8.
                </entry>
            </targetlist>
        </description>
    </advantage>
</advantages>
