<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
    List of knowledge available to characters.

    Version: $Revision: 1.4 $
    Author: Samuel Penn
-->

<skill-list>
    <!-- Knowledges -->

    <!-- Area lore -->
    <skill name="Area lore" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            <para>
                Knowledge of a given area, including geographical and
                political knowledge. The <e>Area lore</e> skill is used
                when checking to see if a character has heard of a person,
                place or organisation. Area lore is nearly always based on
                intelligence.
            </para>

            <para>
                There is an area lore skill for each area, normally an area
                the size of a country, with the same culture. An area lore
                skill can give knowledge of surrounding areas, though such
                knowledge will be prejudiced by the beliefs of the original
                area the skill is for.
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">
                Knowledge that everyone knows, such as who the ruler is,
                to names of major cities.
            </example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <!-- Chirurgury -->
    <skill name="Chirurgury" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            <para>
                Performing major operations on a wounded person. This
                requires some specialist tools (though rarely more complicated
                than sharp knives and tongs).
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <!-- First aid -->
    <skill name="First aid" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            <para>
                Care and treatment of wounds to the extent of stopping
                bleeding, and preventing infection. General first aid
                checks are made with intelligence, though some tasks,
                such as removing an arrow from a wound, use dexterity.
            </para>

            <para>
                A first aid check may be made after someone has become
                injured, though only one first aid roll is allowed for
                a single set of injuries. A new first aid roll cannot
                be made until the subject has received more injuries.
            </para>

            <para>
                A successful first aid check will stabalise a wound and
                allow it to begin healing naturally. Failure to perform
                first aid on a subject means that nightly healing rolls
                are not possible, and weekly checks are at +10 to the
                target difficulty.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                If the subject is both stunned and wounded, seperate
                first aid rolls are required. If the first aid check is
                10 or more points above the target required, then one
                level of stun or wound is also healed immediately. A
                character may try to first aid themselves, though they
                suffer all the normal penalties for being injured.
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="0">First aid a bruised (1 stun) subject</example>
            <example target="5">First aid a dazed (2 stuns) subject</example>
            <example target="10">First aid a bloodied or battered (3-4 stuns) subject</example>
            <example target="10">First aid a beaten or oblivious (5-6 stuns) subject</example>
            <example target="10">First aid a hurt (1 wound) subject</example>
            <example target="15">First aid light or medium (2-3) wounds</example>
            <example target="20">First aid serious or critical (4-5) wounds</example>
            <example target="25">First aid fatal (6) wounds</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Faerie lore" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            Knowledge of the Other World, of faeries, spirits
            and beasts of supernatural nature. Based on intelligence.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Folk lore" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            Knowledge of stories, myths and legends of a people.
            Generally, everyone has basic folk lore knowledge of
            their own culture.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Genealogy" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            Knowledge of the family history of a given line, normally
            a noble house. Based on intelligence.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Herb lore" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            Knowledge of herbs and their properties. Can be used
            to recognise, collect and prepare herbs and plants for
            use in remedies, poisons and potions. Based on intelligence.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="History" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            Knowledge of the past, especially the last few hundred
            years. Based on intelligence.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Law" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            Knowledge and understanding of the law, and how to apply
            it in a given situation. Based on intelligence.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Religion" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            Knowledge of a religion, including its gods, customs
            and rituals. Based on intelligence.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Speak own" type="knowledge">
        <description>
            The ability to speak your own language. This defaults
            to four. Language skills are very rarely rolled.
        </description>
    </skill>

</skill-list>

