<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
    Combat manouevres.
 -->

<advantages>

    <advantage name="Grapple" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="0"/>
        <skill name="Brawl"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                <e>Grapple</e> is an attempt to restrain someone. A normal
                brawl attack is made, at a -5 penalty. Success means that
                the defender has been grabbed. A second roll is immediately
                made to see if the attacker can keep hold of the defender.
            </para>

            <para>
                Both attacker and defender roll
                <skillequation>
                    <attribute>strength</attribute>
                    <skill>brawl</skill>
                    <die/>
                </skillequation>
                though the defender has the option of using agility instead
                of strength. If the attacker is again successful, then both
                opponents are grappling. Whilst grappling, neither can move,
                and both suffer a -10 penalty per point of reach of any
                weapon that is used. Neither can use a shield.
            </para>

            <para>
                Either opponent can try to break the grapple on an attack
                action, by using opposed agility/brawl as above. The
                person trying to break the grapple always has the option
                of using either strength or agility.
            </para>

            <para>
                A grappled character can only defend against attacks by
                the person who has grappled them. Both can use attack
                actions to attack each other as normal.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Trip" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="0"/>
        <skill name="Brawl"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A brawling attack is made at -10, success means that a
                damage roll is made, plus there is a chance that the
                defender is knocked from their feet. The attacker makes
                a second brawl attack immediately, using strength
                instead of agility. The defender defends with either
                strength or agility, and uses either athletics or brawl
                to try and remain standing.
            </para>

            <para>
                Success on the part of the attacker means that the
                defender is <e>unsteady</e>. A good success means that
                they are <e>prone</e>. The defender gets a bonus of +10
                for each leg beyond two that they have (and -10 if they
                have only one leg). Penalties for being lame also apply.
            </para>

            <para>
                If opponents are grappling each other, a trip attempt
                gets a +5 bonus, but the attacker goes down with the
                defender unless a superb success is achieved.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Throw" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="2"/>
        <skill name="Brawl"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A <e>slow</e> attack at -5, success results in a temporary
                hold, as if the defender has been grappled. Immediately
                after success, both attacker and defender make oppossed
                brawl checks, with the defender able to choose between
                using strength or agility. Success for the attacker
                leaves the defender <e>unsteady</e>, whilst a good
                success will leave them <e>prone</e>, and can optionally
                cause stun damage as well - the attacke makes a damage
                roll as normal.
            </para>

            <para>
                An excellent success enables the attacker to place the
                defender wherever they want, within 2m of the attacker.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Disarm" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="0"/>
        <skill name="Single weapon"/>
        <skill name="Weapon and shield"/>
        <skill name="Two weapons"/>
        <skill name="Great weapon"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                This manouevre allows the attacker to disarm their foe,
                removing the defender's weapon from their hand. An attack
                is made at -10. Success means that the defender cannot
                attack with that weapon that round (if their action has
                already occured this round, then they suffer no penalty).
            </para>

            <para>
                The defender has the choice of oppossed strength or
                dexterity skill checks. If the attack wins, then the
                defender has been disarmed.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Fient" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="0"/>
        <skill name="Single weapon"/>
        <skill name="Weapon and shield"/>
        <skill name="Two weapons"/>
        <skill name="Great weapon"/>
        <skill name="Longshaft weapon"/>
        <skill name="Brawl"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                This manouevre is intended to force the defender off their
                guard, allowing a follow up strike at greater effectiveness.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Shield bash" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="0"/>
        <skill name="Weapon and shield"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                Bash with the shield.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Killing blow" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="6"/>
        <skill name="Single weapon"/>
        <skill name="Weapon and shield"/>
        <skill name="Two weapons"/>
        <skill name="Great weapon"/>
        <skill name="Longshaft weapon"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                Kill someone with a single blow. Slow attack, -15 to hit.
                Size x stamina roll of 15 + 5 x wounds or die.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Aimed blow" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="4"/>
        <skill name="Single weapon"/>
        <skill name="Weapon and shield"/>
        <skill name="Two weapons"/>
        <skill name="Great weapon"/>
        <skill name="Longshaft weapon"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                Halves armour. Slow attack, -10 to hit.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Deadly punch" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="6"/>
        <skill name="Brawl"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                Bare handed attack which does mixed damage, adding brawl
                skill to the damage rolled.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Ambush" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="2"/>
        <skill name="Brawl"/>
        <skill name="Single weapon"/>
        <skill name="Weapon and shield"/>
        <skill name="Great weapon"/>
        <skill name="Two weapons"/>
        <skill name="Longshaft weapon"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                When initiated against someone who is not expecting an
                attack (any attack, so cannot be done against someone
                in combat, even if they are fighting someone else),
                then an <e>ambush</e> ignores all armour. If
                <e>Killing Blow</e> or <e>Deadly punch</e> is known,
                then they may be combined with the <e>ambush</e>.
            </para>

            <para>
                <e>Ambush</e> is a slow attack.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Double attack" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="8"/>
        <skill name="Brawl"/>
        <skill name="Single weapon"/>
        <skill name="Weapon and shield"/>
        <skill name="Great weapon"/>
        <skill name="Two weapons"/>
        <skill name="Longshaft weapon"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The attack can attack twice, each time at a -15
                penalty to skill. The first attack is fast, the
                second attack is slow, but both happen at the same
                initiative.
            </para>

            <para>
                This does not affect defence, but no other manouevre
                can be combined with this.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Triple attack" type="manouevre">
        <cost points="12"/>
        <skill name="Brawl"/>
        <skill name="Single weapon"/>
        <skill name="Weapon and shield"/>
        <skill name="Great weapon"/>
        <skill name="Two weapons"/>
        <skill name="Longshaft weapon"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The attack can attack three times, each time at a -30
                penalty to skill. The first attack is fast, the
                second attack is normal, and the third attack is slow.
            </para>

            <para>
                This does not affect defence, but no other manouevre
                can be combined with this.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

</advantages>
