<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
    Disadvantages which affect a character's personality and have
    very little effect (if any) on game mechanics. They should be
    roleplayed by the player.
 -->

<advantages>

    <advantage name="Odious personal habit" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-1"/>
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <description>
            The character has a disgusting habit which others find
            repulsive. It could be continuous humming (one point),
            continuous swearing or nose picking (two points) or
            habits which should never ever be done in public (four
            points). This disadvantage will give big penalties in
            social situations, especially where good behaviour
            is expected. A temperence roll of difficulty 30 is
            needed to avoid doing it.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Pyromania" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <description>
            The character is a pyromaniac, having an unhealthy love of
            fires. It is difficult to resist the temptation of setting
            a fire if the opportunity arises.
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Sense of duty" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <cost points="-4"/>
        <cost points="-6"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                Someone with a sense of duty feels bound to aid a
                certain type of person, or an organisation. His motivation
                is purely selfless, though may be through a sense of
                guilt or gratitude.
            </para>

            <para>
                A sense of duty towards a small group of people (such as
                close friends or family) is worth two points, towards
                a larger group (tribe, relatives, guild) four points, and
                to an entire nation or religion, is six points.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Law abiding" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-3"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The character does not like to break the law, however stupid
                the law may be, or however inconvenient it is. If persuaded
                to break the law (through action or inaction), then they
                will feel very guilty, and worry about being caught etc for
                a long time.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Sadist" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-3"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The sadist gains pleasure from the physical or metal anguish
                of others. They inflict pain on others simply because it
                makes them feel good. They may even go out of their way to
                hurt someone, and may prefer to leave enemies alive, minus
                a limb or two, rather than kill them.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Overconfidence" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-2"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The character thinks too highly of himself and his friends,
                and tends to over estimate their competence on a regular
                basis.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Compulsive behaviour" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-1"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                The character has a compulsion or habit which she has to
                indulge in on a regular basis. A compulsion might be
                to wash very regularly, argue about anything, gambling
                etc.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Fanatic" type="diasdvantage">
        <cost points="-3"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A fantatic is completely devoted to a cause, and will lay
                down their life for that cause if necessary.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Delusions" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-1"/>
        <cost points="-3"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A delusional character believes strongly in something that
                just isn't true.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>

    <advantage name="Lazy" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-1"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A lazy person will try their best to avoid work whenever
                possible.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Glutton" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-1"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A glutton loves to eat, far more than he actually needs to.
                Unlike <e>vorocious appetite</e>, a glutton won't suffer
                if he goes without an extra large portion of food, though
                he may believe that he will, and everybody else will suffer
                his complaints.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Greedy" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="-1"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A greedy person loves money and wealth.
            </para>
        </description>
    </advantage>
    
    <advantage name="Code of honour" type="disadvantage">
        <cost points="varies"/>
        <description>
            <para>
                A code of honour is a set of guiding principles which the
                character sets his life by.
            </para>
            
            <targetlist sort="true" bold="true">
                <targetLabel>Cost</targetLabel>
                <valueLabel>Code of Honour</valueLabel>
                
                <entry target="-1" value="Gang's code of honour">
                    Always avenge an insult, stand up for your friends.
                </entry>
                
                <entry target="-2" value="Mercanary's code of honour">
                    Don't change sides after accepting payment, don't
                    abandon your lord. Always accept surrender, and
                    give a fair ransom - one day it might be you.
                </entry>
                
                <entry target="-3" value="Chivalric code of honour">
                    Live by the code of chivalry.
                </entry>
            </targetlist>
        </description>
    </advantage>

</advantages>

