<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
    List of core skills. These are generally available in all genres.

    Version: $Revision: 1.14 $
    Author: Samuel Penn
-->

<skill-list>

    <!--
        Social skills.
     -->



    <!--
        Wilderness skills.
    -->
    
    <skill name="Animal care" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            <para>
                Experience with animals, and a practical knowledge of their
                general behaviour. It does not provide recognition of
                animals, nor knowledge of specific animals, but a general
                knowledge of how they will behave, and how to gain their
                trust, calm them or otherwise manipulate them.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                It is similar to <e>charm</e>, but for animals. It is used
                with Charisma.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Boating" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            Being able to use a small oared boat. Based on intelligence
            for judging travel conditions, strength for speed or dexterity
            for fine navigation.
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">
                Row a boat in a straight line in calm conditions.
            </example>
            <example target="15">Row a boat in choppy conditions</example>
            <example target="20">Row a boat in rough conditions (open sea)</example>
            <example target="30">Very rough conditions</example>
            <example target="40">Row in a storm</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Falconry" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The skill of training, caring for and hunting with falcons
            and similar birds of prey.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Hunting" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The skill of training, caring for and hunting with hounds.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Ride" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The ability to ride, normally a horse. A different skill
            is needed for different types of animals (horses and ponies
            would be the same skill, a Griffin another skill). As well as
            enabling you to remain mounted, it grants a bonus to combat
            skills when mounted.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Teamster" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            <para>
                Handling a team of animals, either pack animals or horses or
                oxen pulling wagons. Care, feeding and pacing, as well as
                being able to distribute load across the team to get the
                maximum efficiency.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Survival" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            <para>
                The survival skill has to be specialised in a specific
                terrain type, including desert, plains, arctic, mountains,
                woodlands, jungle, coastal and swamp. One specialisation is
                gained for free when the skill is first bought, the others
                cost 3 points for each extra terrain.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                With it, the character is able to find food
                and shelter, track game, and know how to travel safely
                and quickly through that type of terrain.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Foraging</e>. When foraging for food, it takes four hours
                for each roll. Each five over the difficulty allows enough
                food to be found for another two people. If more food is
                found than is needed, then the forager as the option of
                stopping early as soon as enough food has been found. Assume
                that food is found at a consistent rate through the time
                period.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Hunting</e>. Similar to foraging, it takes four hours
                for each attempt to hunt game.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Tracking</e>. Survival can be used to track others by
                their footprints and other signs. It is possible to
                estimate the type of animal, their number and how long it
                has been since the tracks were made. Of course, it can be
                used to track people as well.
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">Find a suitable shelter</example>
            <example target="15">Forage for food for one person</example>
            <example target="-5">Good conditions</example>
            <example target="+5">Poor conditions</example>
            <example target="+15">Very poor conditions (e.g. winter)</example>
            <example target="+20">Trying to forage in arctic or desert</example>
            <example target="+10">Trying to forage in mountains or swamp</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Swim" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            <para>
                The ability to move in water without drowning or panicking.
                Basically, a waterborne version of the athletics skill.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Seamanship" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            <para>
                Handling a sea going vessel. This is very different from
                boating, which is limited to coastal or river boats.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Scrounging" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            <para>
                Being able to turn useless scrap into something useful. Used
                with intelligence. Covers finding, planning and building,
                though skills such as <e>carpentry</e> or <e>blacksmith</e>
                may be needed as well.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

</skill-list>

