<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
    List of talents available to characters.
    
    Version: $Revision: 1.3 $
    Author: Samuel Penn
-->

<skill-list>
    <skill name="Etiquette" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                Etiquette is a knowledge of good manners and social
                behaviour. It is of much greater use amongst the higher
                classes than amongst the peasantry, where no-one really
                cares which fork they use to eat their meal with, as
                long as a meal is there to be eaten.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                It may be used to know how to address someone of rank,
                how to flirt with a noble Lady without offending her,
                or how to behave at a joust or banquet. It is normally
                based on intelligence, but may use charisma (especially
                for courtly flirting or flattery).
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">How to greet a person correctly</example>
            <example target="10">How to eat without embarassing yourself</example>
            <example target="15">Choosing a suitable gift</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Gambling" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                Knowledge of how to play games of chance. Used with charisma
                for bluffing, intelligence to figure out the odds of
                something, or perception to spot cheating. Does not really
                help if the game is totally chance based.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>
    
    <skill name="Game" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                Knowledge of, and skill at playing a game such as chess
                or Hnefatafl. A skill is required for each game played,
                though similar games may allow half skill. This is based
                on intelligence.
            </para>
        </description>
        
        <examples>
            <example target="10">Knowing the rules to a game</example>
            <example target="20">Playing a game reasonably well</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Lip reading" type="social">
        <description>
            The skill of reading lips. Each 10 rolled gives an
            equivalent point of language skill. There may be penalties
            for distance, or partial visibility.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Bard" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                A skill which covers many forms of social skills,
                including oratory, poetry and singing. It may be used to
                rouse a crowd, invent some poetry on the spot, or remember
                a poem or song well enough to recite or sing it.
            </para>

            <para>
                Bard is always charisma based.
            </para>
        </description>
        
        <examples>
            <example target="10">At least sing in tune</example>
            <example target="15">Give a speech without being too inept</example>
            <example target="20">Invent some poetry fit for the occasion</example>
            <example target="20">Sing reasonably well</example>
            <example target="25">Give a confident speech</example>
            <example target="30">Invent a good poem</example>
            <example target="30">Sing very well</example>
            <example target="35">Give a rousing speech</example>
            <example target="40">Invent some very good poetry</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Musician" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                The skill of playing musical instruments, whether they are
                a drum, a flute or a harp.
            </para>
        </description>
        <examples>
            <example target="15">Play without sending people running for cover</example>
            <example target="20">Play in tune with others</example>
            <example target="30">Play very well</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>


    <skill name="Teach" type="social">
        <description>
            The ability to teach another person, and train them in
            the use of a skill. See the Campaign section for details
            on training.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Trade" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                Covers a multitude of skills involved with trading,
                including bartering, and having some clue as to the
                value of goods.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Seduction" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                The skill of seducing people.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Intrigue" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                Political intrigue.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>
    
    <!-- 
        Wilderness skills.
    -->

    <skill name="Boating" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            Being able to use a small oared boat. Based on intelligence
            for judging travel conditions, strength for speed or dexterity
            for fine navigation.
        </description>
        
        <examples>
            <example target="10">Row a boat in a straight line in calm conditions</example>
            <example target="15">Row a boat in choppy conditions</example>
            <example target="20">Row a boat in rough conditions (open sea)</example>
            <example target="30">Very rough conditions</example>
            <example target="40">Row in a storm</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Falconry" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The skill of training, caring for and hunting with falcons
            and similar birds of prey.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Hunting" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The skill of training, caring for and hunting with hounds.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Ride" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The ability to ride, normally a horse. A different skill
            is needed for different types of animals (horses and ponies
            would be the same skill, a Griffin another skill). As well as
            enabling you to remain mounted, it grants a bonus to combat
            skills when mounted.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Survival" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            <para>
                The survival skill has to be specialised in a specific
                terrain type, including desert, plains, arctic, mountains,
                woodlands, jungle, coastal and swamp.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                With it, the character is able to find food
                and shelter, track game, and know how to travel safely
                and quickly through that type of terrain.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Foraging</e>. When foraging for food, it takes four hours
                for each roll. Each five over the difficulty allows enough
                food to be found for another two people. If more food is
                found than is needed, then the forager as the option of
                stopping early as soon as enough food has been found.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Hunting</e>. Similar to foraging, it takes four hours
                for each attempt to hunt game.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Tracking</e>.
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">Find a suitable shelter</example>
            <example target="15">Forage for food for one person</example>
            <example target="-5">Good conditions</example>
            <example target="+5">Poor conditions</example>
            <example target="+15">Very poor conditions (e.g. winter)</example>
            <example target="+20">Trying to forage in arctic or desert</example>
            <example target="+10">Trying to forage in mountains or swamp</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Swim" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The ability to move in water without drowning or panicking.
            Basically, a waterborne version of the athletics skill.
        </description>
    </skill>

</skill-list>

