<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
    List of core skills. These are generally available in all genres.

    Version: $Revision: 1.7 $
    Author: Samuel Penn
-->

<skill-list>
    <skill name="Etiquette" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                Etiquette is a knowledge of good manners and social
                behaviour. It is of much greater use amongst the higher
                classes than amongst the peasantry, where no-one really
                cares which fork they use to eat their meal with, as
                long as a meal is there to be eaten.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                It may be used to know how to address someone of rank,
                how to flirt with a noble Lady without offending her,
                or how to behave at a joust or banquet. It is normally
                based on intelligence, but may use charisma (especially
                for courtly flirting or flattery).
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">How to greet a person correctly</example>
            <example target="10">How to eat without embarassing yourself</example>
            <example target="15">Choosing a suitable gift</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Gambling" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                Knowledge of how to play games of chance. Used with charisma
                for bluffing, intelligence to figure out the odds of
                something, or perception to spot cheating. Does not really
                help if the game is totally chance based.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Game" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                Knowledge of, and skill at playing a game such as chess
                or Hnefatafl. A skill is required for each game played,
                though similar games may allow half skill. This is based
                on intelligence.
            </para>

            <para>
                The simplist way to find the winner for a game, is for
                both opponents to roll their skill, and the highest roll
                wins. If it is desired to play out the game in more
                detail, then proceed as follows.
            </para>

            <para>
                Each opponent makes a skill check each turn of the game.
                If one exceeds the other by five or more, then they gain
                an advantage. Each advantage gained gives +3 to the skill
                check next turn. On gaining the fourth advantage, the
                player is considered the winner. If the player with the
                advantage looses a turn, then they loose a level of
                advantage.
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">Knowing the rules to a game</example>
            <example target="20">Playing a game reasonably well</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Lip reading" type="social">
        <description>
            The skill of reading lips. Each 10 rolled gives an
            equivalent point of language skill. There may be penalties
            for distance, or partial visibility.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Performance" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                A skill which covers many forms of social skills,
                including oratory, poetry and singing. It may be used to
                rouse a crowd, invent some poetry on the spot, or remember
                a poem or song well enough to recite or sing it.
            </para>

            <para>
                The mood of the audience can be affected with either song,
                poetry or oratory. The performer matches their skill roll
                against the will of the audience. If the audience can be
                treated as a <e>crowd</e>, take the average will and roll
                once for the whole audience (a vocal few will tend to
                lead the silent majority). Success by the performer will
                mean the crowd listens to what the performer says, and
                will think about it, though their opinion isn't shifted
                greatly. For each full 10 the performer beats the will
                of the crowd, the crowd's mood is shifted one category.
            </para>

            <para>
                When singing or reciting poetry, the mood of the audience
                can be shifted, sometimes considerably. This can be done
                subtly, though it takes an evening of performance to carry
                it out.
            </para>

            <para>
                A more direct way to sway an audience is through oratory.
                This is quicker and more direct then by choice of song,
                but is also pretty blatent.
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">
                Sing without inflicting pain on listeners. Less than this
                may get the character forcibly removed from the stage.
            </example>

            <example target="20">
                Sing well enough to impress the audience, though not in a
                way that will be particularly remembered.
            </example>

            <example target="30">
                Sing very well. The singer will be well received, and
                probably kept around for more of the same. The mood of
                the audience can be shifted subtly.
            </example>

            <example target="40">
                The singer will be spoken of for months to come, and people
                will be most eager to please. The mood of the audience can
                be shifted noticeably.
            </example>

            <example target="50">
                All others will be compared (probably unfavourably) to the
                singer, who will be heralded as a master of their art. The
                singer pretty much has control over the mood of the audience.
            </example>

            <example target="10">At least sing in tune</example>
            <example target="15">Give a speech without being too inept</example>
            <example target="20">Invent some poetry fit for the occasion</example>
            <example target="20">Sing reasonably well</example>
            <example target="25">Give a confident speech</example>
            <example target="30">Invent a good poem</example>
            <example target="30">Sing very well</example>
            <example target="35">Give a rousing speech</example>
            <example target="40">Invent some very good poetry</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Musician" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                The skill of playing musical instruments, whether they are
                a drum, a flute or a harp.
            </para>
        </description>
        <examples>
            <example target="15">Play without sending people running for cover</example>
            <example target="20">Play in tune with others</example>
            <example target="30">Play very well</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>


    <skill name="Teach" type="social">
        <description>
            The ability to teach another person, and train them in
            the use of a skill. See the Campaign section for details
            on training.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Trade" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                Covers a multitude of skills involved with trading,
                including bartering, and having some clue as to the
                value of goods.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Seduction" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                The skill of seducing people. This gives knowledge
                of how to dress, how to behave and what to say when
                trying to arose sexual desire in someone. It also
                gives skill in bed.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Charm</e> can be used in its place, though use of
                charm often takes much longer to take effect.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Intrigue" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                The skill of dealing with the intrigues of a political
                court. With it, it is possible to find out relationships
                within the court, and to obtain information from people, or
                even to spread information without it being obvious that
                the plotter is trying to spread information.
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">Detect broad allegiences in a group</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>
    
    <skill name="Streetwise" type="social">
        <description>
            <para>
                <e>Streetwise</e> is similar to <e>intrigue</e>, though is
                more suited to life amongst the criminal classes. With it,
                comes knowledge of how to survive on the street, how to
                gain the trust of those who live on the wrong side of the
                law, as well as how to find them in the first place.
            </para>
        </description>
    </skill>

    <!--
        Wilderness skills.
    -->

    <skill name="Boating" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            Being able to use a small oared boat. Based on intelligence
            for judging travel conditions, strength for speed or dexterity
            for fine navigation.
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">Row a boat in a straight line in calm conditions</example>
            <example target="15">Row a boat in choppy conditions</example>
            <example target="20">Row a boat in rough conditions (open sea)</example>
            <example target="30">Very rough conditions</example>
            <example target="40">Row in a storm</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Falconry" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The skill of training, caring for and hunting with falcons
            and similar birds of prey.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Hunting" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The skill of training, caring for and hunting with hounds.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Ride" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The ability to ride, normally a horse. A different skill
            is needed for different types of animals (horses and ponies
            would be the same skill, a Griffin another skill). As well as
            enabling you to remain mounted, it grants a bonus to combat
            skills when mounted.
        </description>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Survival" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            <para>
                The survival skill has to be specialised in a specific
                terrain type, including desert, plains, arctic, mountains,
                woodlands, jungle, coastal and swamp.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                With it, the character is able to find food
                and shelter, track game, and know how to travel safely
                and quickly through that type of terrain.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Foraging</e>. When foraging for food, it takes four hours
                for each roll. Each five over the difficulty allows enough
                food to be found for another two people. If more food is
                found than is needed, then the forager as the option of
                stopping early as soon as enough food has been found. Assume
                that food is found at a consistent rate through the time
                period.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Hunting</e>. Similar to foraging, it takes four hours
                for each attempt to hunt game.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <e>Tracking</e>.
            </para>
        </description>

        <examples>
            <example target="10">Find a suitable shelter</example>
            <example target="15">Forage for food for one person</example>
            <example target="-5">Good conditions</example>
            <example target="+5">Poor conditions</example>
            <example target="+15">Very poor conditions (e.g. winter)</example>
            <example target="+20">Trying to forage in arctic or desert</example>
            <example target="+10">Trying to forage in mountains or swamp</example>
        </examples>
    </skill>

    <skill name="Swim" type="wilderness">
        <description>
            The ability to move in water without drowning or panicking.
            Basically, a waterborne version of the athletics skill.
        </description>
    </skill>

</skill-list>

