<?xml version="1.0"?>

<invocations>
Banner of Mendiz I
Time: 1 round        Range: Short (50m)
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/2
Duration: Combat    Resist: Bravery
Causes an immediate morale check for everyone except the priest within range, though Laranian's get a +10 bonus. Failure causes people to hesitate and regroup. Failure by more than 10 causes route.
Courage of Mendiz I
Time: 1 round        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low
Duration: Combat
Gives the subject a bonus to will rolls of two fifths the invocation roll until sleep.
Curse of the Reluctant Warrior I
Time: 1 round        Range: Near (15m)
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Low/1
Duration: Combat
One chosen subject in range suffers a penalty to all combat skills for the duration of the combat equal to two fifths the invocation roll.
Fast of the Tirannon I
Time: 1 minute        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Moderate
Duration: Day / 5 rolled
Subject does not need to eat or drink for one day per five rolled with the invocation. All attributes however are at -1. If the subject does eat or drink, the invocation is ended.
Larani's Shield I
Time: Instant        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/1
Subject's defence is increased by one fifth the invocation roll as long as they are using a shield. This is doubled if they are protecting defenceless women nearby.
Light of Dolithor I
Time: 1 round        Range: Self
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low
Increases or decreases light in a spherical zone around the priest, up to a number of metres equal to one half the invocation roll.
Passage to Tirithor I
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/1
An invocation to cure infection. An infection of severity 1 per five rolled is immediately cured.
Valamin's Insight I
Time: 1 minute        Range: Self
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/immediate/2
Offers insight when the priest is unsure about what to do. This only applies to moral quandaries.
Bandage of St. Perelyne II
Time: 1 round        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/1
Stops bloodloss and heals one wound level on the person touched. Alternatively, it can cure all stuns the person suffers from.
Blessing of the Winged Lion II
Time: 1 round        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/1
Duration: 1 hour
The person touched receives a soak bonus against ethereal fire equal to twice the invocation roll.
Endurance of St. Amrathas II
Time: 1 round        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Low/1
Duration: Sleep
The person has their stamina increased by one for every twenty points of invocation rolled.
Herald of the End of Life II
Time: 1 hour        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 20        Cost: High/immediate/3
Duration: Week
Blesses a sword with some of the attributes of Avarkiel, Larani's holy sword. While the invocation lasts, the sword has a damage bonus of one fifth the invocation roll. This cannot be combined with other bonuses.
Shield of Hyvrik II
Time: 1 round        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Moderate/1
Duration: Combat
When layed upon a checkered shield, the defence of the shield is increased by one fifth the invocation roll.
Knight's Peace II
Time: 1 round        Range: Short (50m)
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Low
Duration: Scene
Creates a spherical zone centered on the priest within which all Laranian followers are disinclined to fight. If they wish to fight, or continue fighting, they must make a will check against the invocation roll. If they are attacked while within the zone, they will try to surrender, or if that fails, fight.
Oathbinder II
Time: 1 day        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 30        Cost: V. high/immediate/5
Duration: Year
A blessing is laid upon the sword, and it becomes like Avarkiel for a year. If the bearer of the sword is Laranian, then the sword gains a bonus to initiative, attack and damage equal to one fifth the invocation roll. A non-Laranian will find the sword to have a penalty equal to twice this.
Orthas' Faith II
Time: 1 round        Range: Near
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Moderate/2
Duration: Combat
All Laranians within range gain a bonus of one fifth the invocation roll to attack and initiative rolls for the duration of the combat.
Protection of Angcaradina II

Red Robes Flowing II

Valamin's Sleep II

Larani's Charge III

</invocations>
