<?xml version="1.0"?>
<invocations>

<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="1">
<name>Speak with Dead I</name>
<time>15 minutes</time>
<range>Self</range>
<difficulty>10</difficulty>
<cost>None</cost>
<description>
Allows conversation with a captured soul. The soul may initiate
mental conflict. A soul may be captured during a ceremony in
which the body is sacrified to Morgath. Alternatively, any
gulmorvrus can be questioned in this way.
</description>
</invocation>

<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="1">
<name>Heart of Darkness I</name>
<time>15 minutes</name>
<range>Touch</range>
<difficulty>10</difficulty>
<cost>Low</cost>
<description>
The cleric channels a small portion of the Shadow of Bukrai into
a person. It is treated as a will attack as per entering the
Shadow of Bukrai. If this ritual is performed on a dead corpse,
it immediately bcomes a gulmorvrus, with a will of one. The
Difficulty is 10 if the corpse has been dead less than a day,
20 if less than a week, 30 if less than a month, 40 if less than
a year, and 50 if year+.
</description>
</invocation>

<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="1">
<name>Necrosy I</name>
<time>15 minutes</time>
<range>Touch</range>
<difficulty>10</difficulty>
<cost>Low</cost>
<description>
Preserves a corpse at its current state of decay for a number of
days equal to one fifth the invocation roll.
</description>
</invocation>

<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="2">
<name>Cloak of Klyss II</name>
<time>1 round</time>
<range>Touch</range>
<difficulty>10</difficulty>
<cost>Low/immediate</cost>
<description>
Allows the priest, or the subject touch, to find and enter a
Shadow of Bukrai safely. While within the Shadow, the subject
will appear slightly translucent # bones and internal organs
will be visible if not covered by clothing. This invocation is
used to allow living followers attending ceremonies with Amorvrin.
</description>
</invocation>


<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="2">
<name>Eyes of Klyss II</name>
<time>1 round</time>
<range>Touch</range>
<difficulty>10</difficulty>
<cost>Low</cost>
<description>
The priest summons a black orb about thirty centimetres in
diameter. The orb contains a pair of glowing red eyes through
which the priest can see. The globe can be commanded to move to
any place within a range of half the invocation roll in metres,
though cannot move through solid objects. It can see perfectly
in darkness, badly in torch light and is blind in daylight. A
physical attack against it will cancel the invocation.
</description>
</invocation>

<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="2">
<name>Klyss' Command II</name>
<time>1 round</time>
<range>Medium</range>
<difficulty>10</difficulty>
<cost>Low</cost>
<description>
This invocation allows the priest to command one or more gulmorvrus
within range.  One gulmorvrus per five rolled can be commanded.
The basic invocation requires verbal commands to be given, though
a roll of 20+ allows telepathy to be used.
</description>
</invocation>

<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="2">
<name>Throat of Klyss II</name>
<time>1 round</time>
<range>Near</range>
<difficulty>20</difficulty>
<cost>Medium</cost>
<description>
Any within range of this invocation are psychologically assualted
by the sounds of souls loosing themselves to Morgath. Save for
the priest, any within range must make an opposed will roll or
flee in terror for a number of minutes equal to one fifth the
invocation roll. Failure by ten or more causes the subject to
faint, for an equal number of hours. Failure by twenty causes
permanent insanity.
</description>
</invocation>

<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="2">
<name>Myvria's Kiss II</name>
<time>5 minutes</time>
<range>Touch</range>
<difficulty>10</difficulty>
<cost>Moderate/immediate</cost>
<description>
This is Myvria's offer to become an Amorvrin. It is only taught to
those who reach the rank of Khidarmur.
</description>
</invocation>

<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="2">
<name>Resting Place II</name>
<time>15 minutes</time>
<range>Reach</range>
<difficulty>25</difficulty>
<cost>High/immediate</cost>
<description>
Consecrates a new resting place for a morvrus. The morvrus must be
present when this invocation is made.
</description>
</invocation>

<invocation religion="Morgath" rank="3">
<name>Sacrifice III</name>
<time>15 minutes</name>
<range>Touch</range>
<difficulty>20</difficulty>
<cost>Very high/immediate</cost>
<description>
This invocation sacrifices a subject in order to get the attention
of Klyss. If the petitioner is an amorvrus, their will is increased
to one tenth the invocation roll. A living priest instead has their
luck increased to a similar value.
</description>
</invocation>
</invocations>
