<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<invocations>
Counsel of Sweldre I
Time: 1 minute        Range: Self
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/immediate
Gives the priest insight into the proper course of action in a moral quandary.
The Twilight Scribe's Question I
Time: 1 round        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/immediate/1
All plants, animals, and spirits have a unique true name and knowing it is very useful. Priest learns the true name of any entity touched.
Curse of Sloth I
Time: 1 round        Range: Near
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Low/2
Duration: Sleep
The priest can specify a number of people within range not exceeding their invocation skill. For each twenty points rolled on invocation, the target's agility is reduced by one. The reduction is automatic.
Ilsiri Dance I
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Horizon
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Moderate/immediate
Calls an Ilsiri within range. The animal may resist with a will check, unless its true name is used in the invocation. Ilsiri are sometimes mischievious, sometimes helpful.
Nature's Aid II
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Horizon
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Moderate/immediate
Calls a friendly animal within range. The animal may resist with a will check, unless their true name is used.
Sereniel's Stone II
Time: 1 minute        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/immediate
Priest learns the type of rock or mineral touched and its purity.
Siem's Blessing II
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Mod./immediate/1
Gives a bonus of +1 per 20 rolled on the invocation to either strength or perception until sleep. Multiple bonuses can be split between different attributes.
Water of the Azure Bowl II
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/immediate
Purifies up to 1 litre of water per point of invocation rolled. The water must be in a single container.
Yael's Calm II
Time: 1 round        Range: Near
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Low
Ends fighting within range. Combatants must make a will roll to continue fighting.
Truthsight II
Time: 1 minute        Range: Near
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Moderate/immediate
Allows the priest to see magically hidden objects, and to perceive the aura of a living being or ethereal within range.
Way from Taur-Im-Aina II
Time: 1 hour        Range: 1 km/10 rolled
Difficulty: 30        Cost: High/immediate
The priest can physically merge his body into that of a tree or large bush (larger than the priest), and emerge from another of te same species within range. The unique true names of both plants must be known. The priest may remain in one tree indefinitely, but is not immune to hunger or thirst.
On a failure, the priest is stuck in the original tree.
Elmithri's Shower III
Time: 15 minutes        Range:  1km/5 rolled
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Moderate/immediate
Creates a gentle shower over an radius equal to one fifth the invocation roll. If the radius is halved, the shower can become snow, hail or heavy rain.
Sweldre's Cloak III
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 30        Cost: High/immediate
The subject takes on the form of a chosen animal. They have the physical attributes of that animal, but the intelligence and will of the subject. It lasts until the subject or the priest wishes it to end.
    30    Subject is changed into an animal. No clothees or equipment survive the change. The animal must be land based, and no more than 50% smaller, or 100% larger than the subject.
    40    Subject can become a fish. Target shape can be as small as a cat.
    50    Clothes and equipment change, as long as the target form could physically carry them.
    60    Clothes and equipment change, regardless of size.

</invocations>
