<?xml version="1.0"?>

<grimoire convocation="Common">


    <spell name="Focus" level="0" convocation="common">
        <time>1 day</time>
        <range>Touch</range>
        <duration>Special</duration>
        <description>
            <para>
                This spell prepares an item for enchantment as a minor
                artifact. The item should be a suitable foci of the given
                convocation, and this spell enhances link the item has
                with its convocation. The rank of the focus determines
                how many spells can be placed in the minor artifact.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Summon Elemental" level="0" convocation="common">
        <time>1 minute</time>
        <range>Short (50m)</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+25 Range is medium (100m)</boost>
        <boost>+50 Range is far (200m)</boost>
        <boost>+100 Range is extreme (500m)</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                This spell summons a Pvaric elemental out of some mundane
                quantity of that element. Neutral and Savoryan elementals
                can be summoned anywhere. The size of the elemental varies
                according to the rank of the spell.
            </para>

            <para>
                The elemental must remain within the range of the spell at
                all times. If the Shek-Pvar forces the elemental out of
                range, or circumstances allow this to occur, then she
                looses control of the elemental. Regardless of the spell
                range, the elemental will initially appear within Near
                of the caster.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The caster must make an oppossed will roll to control the
                elemental when it is first summoned. The elemental can be
                communicated with using a suitable Pvaric language.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Ward Against Elementals" level="0" convocation="common">
        <time>1 round</time>
        <range>Reach</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+25 Range is near</boost>
        <boost>+50 Range is short</boost>
        <boost>+100 Range is medium</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                Prevents elementals of the same convocation from entering
                the area protected. Elementals of equal to or lower rank
                than the rank of this spell are affected.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>


    <spell name="Speak with Elemental" level="10" convocation="common">
        <range>Touch</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <description>
            <para>
                Enables the target to speak the language of elementals of the
                spell's convocation.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>


    <spell name="Block" level="0" convocation="common">
        <range>Self</range>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <description>
            <para>
                This spell blocks spell of the same convocation from affecting
                the caster assuming that they are of equal or lower rank. The
                caster is also prevented from casting such spells himself,
                regardless of the target of such spells.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

</grimoire>
