<grimoire convocation="Fyvria">
<preface>
Fyvrianism is the magic of the earth, of green and growing, of pale and dying 
things, of the cycles of growth and decay that underlie the natural world. 
The base of Fyvria is fertile earth, where life swarms in its endless 
struggle to survive and prosper.
</preface>

<spell name="Verdant Hand" level="10" convocation="fyvria">
<level complex="I">5 + 10 effect</level>
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Day</duration>
<boost>+10 Years worth of growth</boost>
<boost>+20 All plants in near</boost>
<boost>+40 All plants in short</boost>
<description>
Greatly accelerates the normal growth of a living plant, causing it to 
undergo a month of growth over the course of the day. Food and water 
requirement for the plant are increased by a similar amount. 
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Putrid Hand" level="10" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Affects up to size 10</boost>
<boost>+20 Range near</boost>
<boost>+40 1000 x decay speed</boost>
<description>
Causes dead organic matter up to size five to begin rotting at a greatly 
accelerated rate. While the spell is in effect, the material will decay at 
100 times normal speed. Undead corpses get a will roll to resist the spell, 
but are otherwise still affected.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Figure of Aestras" level="10" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Lifetime</duration>
<boost>+10 Range near</boost>
<boost>+20 Unnatural shapes possible</boost>
<boost>+40 All plants in range can be affected</boost>
<description>
Cause a single plant to grow in a chosen configuration. The magic lasts for 
the lifetime of the plant, gradually shaping it into its desired form. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Balm of Gresan" level="10" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+10 Gives +6 bonus</boost>
<boost>+20 Gives +9 bonus</boost>
<boost>+40 Allows a second first aid roll</boost>
<description>
When cast on an injured target, gives +3 to the first aid roll. Does not 
grant a second first aid roll for the target if one has previously been made. 
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Hand of Iliam" level="30" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Heals already infected wounds</boost>
<boost>+30 Automatically heals a body level</boost>
<description>
Prevents a touched wound from becoming infected. It stops bleeding and any 
potential worsening of the wound. If the wound is already infected, then it 
has no effect. Can be considered similar to a first aid attempt on the wound, 
though there is no chance of healing a body level. Note that the magic only 
seals and cleans the wound and does not have any long term effect beyond 
this. If the wound is reopened it may possibly be infected, though it is 
unlikely.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Takara's Curse" level="30" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Stamina 20</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Resist of 25</boost>
<boost>+30 Resist of 30</boost>
<boost>+60 Resist of 35</boost>
<description>
Causes a single open wound to become infected. If the spell is not resisted, 
then the target must make a stamina roll each day at difficulty 20, modified 
by normal wound penalty. Failure means the wound worsens by one level. The 
wound remains infected until the target dies, or the wound is purged of the 
infection.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Favrin's Bar" level="60" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Gives 30% base increase</boost>
<boost>+30 Size 24</boost>
<boost>+60 Can affect a complex structure</boost>
<description>
An enchantment which causes a single item of wood to expand, primarily across 
the grain. The effect is most dramatic with green or living wood. Seasoned 
wood expands by 15%, green wood by 30% and living wood by 60%. The wood is 
generally weakened by the change. A target up to size 12 can be affected. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Nurture of Isla" level="60" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+15 Bonus is +15</boost>
<boost>+30 Bonus is +20</boost>
<description>
A spell to increase the healing rate of a wound suffered by a living 
creature. They get a +12 bonus for their next natural healing roll. Only one 
casting of this spell will work on a target at any one time.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Power of Sharadorn" level="60" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range reach</boost>
<boost>+30 Increase two attributes</boost>
<boost>+60 Affect everyone in reach</boost>
<description>
A spell to temporarily increase one of the caster's physical attributes 
(strength, stamina, agility or dexterity) by one point. It cannot be combined 
with any other attribute enhancing spell (including itself, even if different 
spells are affecting different attributes).
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Dream of Galega" level="90" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Special</duration>
<description>
Causes a single living creature to fall into a deep slumber. Each night they 
sleep, they get one natural healing roll (instead of getting one at the end 
of each week). The creature will naturally awaken the morning after they 
become fully healed. This spell can be combined with spells such as Nurture 
of Isla.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Mankor's Curse" level="90" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Penalty is -20</boost>
<boost>+30 Range is medium</boost>
<boost>+60 Affects all designated creatures in near of target</boost>
<description>
A spell to induce a unique wasting disease in a single creature. The victim 
suffers -10 to all healing (including first aid) and fatigue recovery rolls 
(including sleep). If cast multiple times on a target, then only the worst 
effect applies.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Eye of Perfection" level="30" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Know two worst injuries</boost>
<boost>+30 Know all things about the target</boost>
<description>
Analyses the health of a single living creature, informing the caster 
of the nature of the worst injury the target is suffering from.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Syncope of Shalor" level="30" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Size 12</boost>
<boost>+30 Range short</boost>
<boost>+60 Up to size 25 targets</boost>
<description>
Causes a single target up to size 6 to fall asleep if they fail their 
stamina resistance roll. Higher castings of this spell may affect 
multiple targets up to the total size that may be affected.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Balm of Herl" level="60" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+30 Size 9</boost>
<boost>+60 Range is short</boost>
<description>
Transfers a disease, infection or other natural ailment (not a wound) 
from one living creature to another living creature. Both make stamina 
rolls to resist, and the spell fails unless they are both failed. 
Neither creature can be greater than size 6.
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Arbad's Wounding" level="60" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Causes 2 wounds</boost>
<boost>+30 Causes 3 wounds</boost>
<boost>+60 Range is short</boost>
<description>
This spell causes the skin and flesh on a living target to rupture, 
causing one body level of damage if the target fails to resist. 
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Regenesis" level="90" convocation="fyvria">
<time>1 hour</time>
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range becomes touch</boost>
<boost>+30 Can regenerate limbs</boost>
<boost>+60 Can regenerate dead organic matter</boost>
<description>
Regenesis greatly accelerates the healing of living things. While 
the spell is being maintained, the target creature will get a 
natural healing roll every eight hours. The Shek-Pvar must keep the 
spell up over at least an eight hour period while her target 
rests or sleeps. The process is fatiguing however, five fatigue 
levels are gained by the target during the period, reduced by 
one per point of stamina. Versions of this spell which regenerate 
limbs do so very slowly. Even a lost hand will take about 15 days. 
Dead matter, even if it can be regenerated, can never be restored 
to life.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Vine of Alguinas" level="90" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Centre of affect can be up to range near</boost>
<boost>+30 Can be cast on thorny/non-succulent plants</boost>
<description>
This spells causes very rapid growth in succulent vines. All plants 
within range begin growing to form a clump of tough, tangled vines, 
branches and roots. After three rounds, the plants have reached 
about ten times normal size, they will die. The plants will have 
rotted back within about half an hour. Though the Shek-Pvar is at 
the centre of the area when it begins to grow, he generally does 
have time to get clear if he so wishes. 
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Animus of Nithri" level="120" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+20 If the zombie has muscles, it can be commanded to move, 
though control is literal and very difficult</boost>
<boost>+40 Zombie can be given simple directions</boost>
<boost>+80 Zombie can be given tasks, such as to fight or follow</boost>
<description>
Animus of Nithri restores a small portion of a dead creature's animus, 
effectively creating a zombie. It cannot be used on a creature who 
has had buriel rites performed on it, since it requires a portion of 
the dead creature's soul to be present in the corpse. The basic spell 
is enough to activate the memories and (if they are still functional) 
vocal cords of the dead creature. Memories decay with time. 
Intelligence and will both drop by a point after a day, a week, and 
then each month after that, down to a minimum of one. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Regrowth of Evala" level="120" convocation="fyvria">
<time>1 day</time>
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+20 Only 25% of the original is required</boost>
<boost>+40 Only 10% of the original is required</boost>
<boost>+80 Only 5% of the original is required</boost>
<description>
This spell regrows a complete organism from a part of it. For the
basic spell, 50% of the organism must be present in order to regrow
the whole. It can be used to regrow lost body parts, restore corpses
or recover a plant. Dead organisms are not restored to life.
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Silme's Ward" level="120" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch/Medium</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+20 Caster is alerted as to general nature of intruder</boost>
<boost>+40 Specific information about intruders are known, limited 
by sense of the target</boost>
<boost>+80 Caster may limit what type of intruders raise an alarm</boost>
<description>
When cast upon a living plant or creature, the Shek-Pvar will be 
alerted if the target perceives another living creature. It is 
generally used as a alarm. The Shek'Pvar must be within medium 
range of the target if she is to hear the alarm. The perceptive 
range of most plants is about three metres. The warning is via 
a mind link to the Shek-Pvar. 
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Succor of Blezil" level="120" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+20 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+40 Up to 12 body levels</boost>
<boost>+80 Half fatigue is gained</boost>
<description>
This spell will heal either disease or injury in a living creature. 
If used to heal a disease, then the disease is completely healed, and 
the creature gains from one to five points of long term fatigue, 
depending on the severity of the disease. If used to heal injuries, 
then up to six body levels are immediately healed, and converted to 
long term fatigue. If the target cannot gain more fatigue, then there 
is no effect. It cannot be used to regenerate lost body parts. 
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Passage of Chabar" level="160" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+40 Organic clothing and equipment is affected</boost>
<boost>+80 Range is touch</boost>
<description>
This spell enables the caster to melt through earth, stone or wood, 
though not other substances. The caster can move through earth at 
one quarter walking speed, through wood at a fifth speed, and through 
stone at one tenth speed. If the caster is inside a solid object 
when the spell stops, then she is instantly killed. Clothes and 
equipment are unaffected, so only her naked body can travel this way. 
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Vessel of Galanda" level="160" convocation="fyvria">
<time>Special</time>
<range>Special</time>
<resist>None</resist>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+20 Takes 42 days to grow</boost>
<boost>+40 Takes 35 days to grow</boost>
<boost>+80 Takes 28 days to grow</boost>
<description>
This spell grows an adult body from a dead embryo or foetus, though 
it only works on mammals. The foetus must have been dead at least 
six hours, and no more than 24 hours when the spell is begun. It 
takes about ten hours of casting initially to start the spell, and 
the foetus must be kept in clean water and finely sifted earth. Each 
day, the growing body consumes about 200 litres of water and 100kg 
of earth, and the caster must spend about 4 hours with the body. 
After 56 days, the body is a fully grown adult, and is ready to 
receive a spirit. It will die within a few hours if a spirit does 
not inhabit it. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Essence of Sinad" level="200" convocation="fyvria">
<time>8 hours</time>
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+25 Aging is halted for 2 years</boost>
<boost>+50 Aging is halted for 3 years</boost>
<boost>+100 Aging is halted for 5 years</boost>
<description>
This spell halts all biological aging in the Shek-Pvar. It requires 
a transfusion of one litre of blood from a Sindarin or other 
immortal species. The caster will stop aging for 1 year. However, 
one point of stamina and strength is lost permanently. 
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Touch of Ptaris" level="200" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</range>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+25 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+50 Final form can be wood or earth. Earth tends to 
crumble, so is usually fatal</boost>
<description>
This spell turns an organic target up to size 12 to stone. The 
target is still capable of thought, though at greatly reduced 
rate. 
</description>
</spell>


</grimoire>
