<grimoire convocation="Fyvria">
<preface>
Fyvria
Fyvrianism is the magic of the earth, of green and growing, of pale and dying 
things, of the cycles of growth and decay that underlie the natural world. The 
base of Fyvria is fertile earth, where life swarms in its endless struggle to 
survive and prosper.

Change

Guidelines
5: Change the speed of growth of a plant (x100)
5: Prevent a wound from going bad.
5: Infect a wound.
10: Cause a wound. Half effect gives damage to be soaked.
10: Accelerate plant growth by x1,000. Most plants will starve.
15: Change the speed of growth of an animal by x10
15: Expand or shrink the size of a plant.
20: Accelerate plant growth by x10,000. This will starve a plant very quickly.
30: Change the speed of growth of an animal by x100
</preface>


<spell name="Balm of Gresan" level="25" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="I">10 + 5T (wounds)+ 5E (bonus)</level>
<target>3 wounds or less</target>
<effect>0 bonus</effect>
<range>-1 bonus / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 1m</resist>
<description>
When cast on an injured target, provides the effects of a first aid roll. It 
cannot be cast on the same wounds more than once a day, but can be cast on 
wounds which have been tended to with a mundane healing attempt. Only works on 
wounds of three levels or less in severity.
</description>
<notes>
Each 5 levels placed into target affects up to one wound level. Each five 
levels placed into the effect give a bonus of +1 to the healing roll, though 
the basic version of the spell has no such bonus. A concentration version of 
the spell would allow a different person to be healed each round.
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Figure of Aestras" level="25" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="I">10 + 3T (size)</level>
<target>Size 5</target>
<range>-1 size / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 1m</resist>
<description>
Cause a single plant to grow in a chosen configuration. The spell 
is cast, and the new desired shape is immediately imprinted on the plant, 
which will continue to grow into that shape at normal speed, unless something 
happens in the future to change things.
</description>
<notes>
The results can only be what the plant could possibly achieve through 
natural growth. Each three levels of target affects a plant up to a size of 
one.
</notes>
</spell>



<spell name="Putrid Hand" level="20" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="I">5 + 5 (conc) + 5T (size) + 5E (speed)</level>
<concentration/>
<target>Size 2</target>
<effect>10 x decay speed</effect>
<range>-1 size / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 1m</resist>
<description>
Causes rotting organic matter up to size 2 to start rotting at a 
much accelerated pace, up to 10 times faster. Undead corpses get a stamina 
roll 
to resist the spell, but are otherwise still affected.
</description>
<notes>
Every 5 levels of target will affect one size point of matter. 
Every 5 levels of effect will increase the rate of decay by a factor of 10, so 
5 levels 
is 10 times faster, 10 levels if 100 times faster.
</notes>
</spell>



<spell name="Verdant Hand" level="30" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="I">5 + 5 (conc) + 2T (size) + 10E (speed)</level>
<concentration/>
<target>Siz 10</target>
<effect>10 x growth speed</effect>
<range>-1 size / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 1m</resist>
<description>
Greatly accelerates the normal growth of a living thing, by a factor of 10. 
The target requires an equal increase in sustenance as it did previously, 
else it will die. Mental capacity is not affected. The target may die of age 
as a result of this spell. If the size of the target exceeds the maximum size 
which can be affected by the spell, then the spell ends.
</description>
<notes>
Every two levels of target affects one point of size of plant or creature. 
Every ten points of effect increases the rate of growth by a factor of 10, so 
10 levels multiplies growth by x10, and 20 levels multiplies by x100.
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Eye of Perfection" level="45" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="II">20 + T5 (size)+ 5E (information)</level>
<target>Size 50</target>
<effect>3 levels of knowledge</effect>
<range>-1 knowledge / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Analyses the health of a single living creature, providing the caster with 
knowledge up to level three (one a scale of 1 (basic) to 5 (complete 
knowledge)). 
Any plant or animal up to size 10 can be examined with this spell.
</description>
<notes>
Each level of target affects up to 5 size points of creature or plant. Every 
five levels 
of effect, will grant one level of knowledge about the target, up to a maximum 
of five.
</notes>
</spell>



<spell name="Hand of Iliam" level="40" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="II">10 + 5T (wounds)</level>
<target>Wounds up to level 6</target>
<range>-1 body level / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 1m</resist>
<description>
Prevents a wound of up to six body levels from becoming infected. It 
prevents bleeding and worsening of the wound, though does not heal it. The 
wound is considered to be stabalised however. If the wounds are greater than 
six body levels in severity, then the spell has no effect.
</description>
<notes>
Each 5 levels of effect will help one level of wound. A concentration 
version of the spell would allow one target to be enchanted each round.
</notes>
</spell>



<spell name="Syncope of Shalor" level="45" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="II">15 + 5E (fatigue)</level>
<effect>6 fatigue levels</effect>
<range>-1 fatigue / 10m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Causes a single target to gain 6 fatigue levels if they fail 
their stamina resistance roll. Fatigue levels gained is reduced by 
range.
</description>
<notes>
Every 5 levels of effect gives one fatigue level to the target. A 
concentration version of the spell would keep on adding fatigue each 
round, though would have no effect beyond unconsciousness.
</notes>
</spell>




<spell name="Takara's Curse" level="50" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="II">25 + 2T (size) + 5E (disease)</level>
<target>Size 5</target>
<effect>Level 3 infection</effect>
<range>-1 infection / 5m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Causes a single open wound to become infected with a level 3 infection 
(equivalent to a serious wound infection, which could be fatal if not 
stopped in time).
</description>
<notes>
Each two points of target effects a creature of size 1, and each five 
levels of effect cause one level of infection (maximum five).
</notes>
</spell>




<spell name="Balm of Herl" level="80" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="III">35 + 3T (size) + 10E (infection)</level>
<target>Size 5</target>
<effect>Transfer level 3 infection</effect>
<range>-1 level / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 1m</resist>
<description>
Transfers a disease, infection or other natural ailment (not a 
wound) up to severity 3 from one living creature to another living creature. 
Both make stamina 
rolls to resist, and the spell fails unless they are both failed. Neither 
creature can be larger than size 5. The spell range is the total distance 
between the caster and the first target, and the caster and the second target. 
If the infection is worse than level 3, then the spell fails.
</description>
<notes>
Every 3 levels of target affect one size of creature. Every 10 levels of 
effect 
can transfer one level of infection.
</notes>
</spell>




<spell name="Favrin's Bar" level="65" convocation="fyvria">
<frequency>Common</frequency>
<level complex="III">25 + 3T (size) + 25E (growth)</level>
<target>Size 15</target>
<effect>25% growth</effect>
<range>-1% / 5m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
An enchantment which causes wood to expand, primarily across the grain. The 
effect is most dramatic with green or living wood. Seasoned wood expands by 
25%, green wood by twice this and living wood by four times the base. The wood 
is generally weakened by the change, which occurs over the course of about 
five seconds. The wood will return to roughly it's original size over the 
course of the next day. If the spell is cast on already expanded wood, the 
growth will be calculated from its natural size.
</description>
<notes>
Each level of effect gives 1% volume increase for seasoned wood, twice this 
for green wood, and four times this for living wood. Every 3 levels of target 
will affect something of base size of one.
</notes>
</spell>



<spell name="Nurture of Isla" level="65" convocation="fyvria">
<level complex="III">40 + 5E (bonus)</level>
<effect>+5 to healing roll</effect>
<range>-1 / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
A spell to increase the healing rate of a wound suffered by a 
living creature. They get a +5 bonus for their next natural healing roll. Only 
one casting of this spell will work on a target at any one time.
</description>
<notes>
Each 5 levels of effect give a +1 bonus to the next natural healing 
roll only (at the end of the week).
</notes>
<frequency>Common</frequency>
</spell>



<spell name="Power of Sharadorn" level="80" convocation="fyvria">
<level complex="III">25 + 5 conc + 50E (bonus)</level>
<effect>+1 to attribute</effect>
<range>-1 bonus / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
A spell to temporarily increase one of the target's physical attributes 
(strength, stamina, agility or dexterity) by one point. It cannot 
be combined with any other attribute enhancing spell (including itself, even 
if different spells are affecting different attributes).
</description>
<notes>
Each fifty points of effect give a bonus of +1. A spell to reverse the effect 
would be a similar level, though would be a permanent effect (so no  
concentration component would be needed). A version of the spell which gives 
multiple bonuses can be split across more than one attribute.
</notes>
<frequency>Common</frequency>
</spell>




<spell name="Dream of Galega" level="110" convocation="fyvria">
<level complex="IV">50 + 5T (size) + 10E (bonus)</level>
<target>Up to size 6</target>
<effect>+3 bonus</effect>
<range>-1 bonus / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Causes a single living creature up to size 6 to fall into a deep slumber, 
which lasts until they are either wakened, or they die of dehydration. Each 
night they sleep, they get a natural healing roll at a +3 bonus.
</description>
<notes>
Each five levels of target affects a size one creature. Every ten points of 
effect gives a +1 bonus to the healing rolls.
</notes>
<frequency>Common</frequency>
</spell>




<spell name="Mankor's Curse" level="120" convocation="fyvria">
<level complex="IV">50 + 25 effect</level>
<range>-1 / 5m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>A spell to induce a unique wasting disease in a single creature. 
The victim suffers -10 to all healing (including first aid) and fatigue 
recovery rolls. If cast multiple times on a target, then only the worst effect 
applies.</description>
<notes>Each five points of effect reduce healing rolls by two.</notes>
<frequency>Common</frequency>
</spell>


</grimoire>



