<grimoire convocation="Fyvria">
<preface>
Fyvrianism is the magic of the earth, of green and growing, of pale and dying
things, of the cycles of growth and decay that underlie the natural world.
The base of Fyvria is fertile earth, where life swarms in its endless
struggle to survive and prosper.
</preface>

<spell name="Verdant Hand" level="10" convocation="fyvria">
<level complex="I">5 + 10 effect</level>
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Day</duration>
<boost>+10 Years worth of growth</boost>
<boost>+20 All plants in near</boost>
<boost>+40 All plants in short</boost>
<description>
Greatly accelerates the normal growth of a living plant, causing it to
undergo a month of growth over the course of the day. Food and water
requirement for the plant are increased by a similar amount.
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Putrid Hand" level="10" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Affects up to size 10</boost>
<boost>+20 Range near</boost>
<boost>+40 1000 x decay speed</boost>
<description>
Causes dead organic matter up to size five to begin rotting at a greatly
accelerated rate. While the spell is in effect, the material will decay at
100 times normal speed. Undead corpses get a will roll to resist the spell,
but are otherwise still affected.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Figure of Aestras" level="10" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Lifetime</duration>
<boost>+10 Range near</boost>
<boost>+20 Unnatural shapes possible</boost>
<boost>+40 All plants in range can be affected</boost>
<description>
Cause a single plant to grow in a chosen configuration. The magic lasts for
the lifetime of the plant, gradually shaping it into its desired form.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Balm of Gresan" level="10" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+10 Gives +6 bonus</boost>
<boost>+20 Gives +9 bonus</boost>
<boost>+40 Allows a second first aid roll</boost>
<description>
When cast on an injured target, gives +3 to the first aid roll. Does not
grant a second first aid roll for the target if one has previously been made.
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Hand of Iliam" level="30" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Heals already infected wounds</boost>
<boost>+30 Automatically heals a body level</boost>
<description>
Prevents a touched wound from becoming infected. It stops bleeding and any
potential worsening of the wound. If the wound is already infected, then it
has no effect. Can be considered similar to a first aid attempt on the wound,
though there is no chance of healing a body level. Note that the magic only
seals and cleans the wound and does not have any long term effect beyond
this. If the wound is reopened it may possibly be infected, though it is
unlikely.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Takara's Curse" level="30" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Stamina 20</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Resist of 25</boost>
<boost>+30 Resist of 30</boost>
<boost>+60 Resist of 35</boost>
<description>
Causes a single open wound to become infected. If the spell is not resisted,
then the target must make a stamina roll each day at difficulty 20, modified
by normal wound penalty. Failure means the wound worsens by one level. The
wound remains infected until the target dies, or the wound is purged of the
infection.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Favrin's Bar" level="60" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+20 Gives 30% base increase</boost>
<boost>+40 Size 24</boost>
<boost>+80 Can affect a complex structure</boost>
<description>
An enchantment which causes a single item of wood to expand, primarily across
the grain. The effect is most dramatic with green or living wood. Seasoned
wood expands by 15%, green wood by 30% and living wood by 60%. The wood is
generally weakened by the change. A target up to size 12 can be affected.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Nurture of Isla" level="60" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+20 Bonus is +15</boost>
<boost>+40 Bonus is +20</boost>
<description>
A spell to increase the healing rate of a wound suffered by a living
creature. They get a +12 bonus for their next natural healing roll. Only one
casting of this spell will work on a target at any one time.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Power of Sharadorn" level="60" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+20 Range reach</boost>
<boost>+40 Increase two attributes</boost>
<boost>+80 Affect everyone in reach</boost>
<description>
A spell to temporarily increase one of the caster's physical attributes
(strength, stamina, agility or dexterity) by one point. It cannot be combined
with any other attribute enhancing spell (including itself, even if different
spells are affecting different attributes).
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Dream of Galega" level="100" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<description>
Causes a single living creature to fall into a deep slumber. Each night they
sleep, they get one natural healing roll (instead of getting one at the end
of each week). The creature will naturally awaken the morning after they
become fully healed. This spell can be combined with spells such as Nurture
of Isla.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Mankor's Curse" level="100" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+25 Penalty is -20</boost>
<boost>+50 Range is medium</boost>
<boost>+100 Affects all designated creatures in near of target</boost>
<description>
A spell to induce a unique wasting disease in a single creature. The victim
suffers -10 to all healing (including first aid) and fatigue recovery rolls
(including sleep). If cast multiple times on a target, then only the worst
effect applies.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Eye of Perfection" level="30" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Know two worst injuries</boost>
<boost>+30 Know all things about the target</boost>
<description>
Analyses the health of a single living creature, informing the caster of the
nature of the worst injury the target is suffering from.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Syncope of Shalor" level="30"  convocation="fyvria">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Size 12</boost>
<boost>+30 Range short</boost>
<boost>+60 Up to size 25 targets</boost>
<description>
Causes a single target up to size 6 to fall asleep if they fail their stamina
resistance roll. Higher castings of this spell may affect multiple targets up
to the total size that may be affected.
 </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Balm of Herl" level="60" convocation="fyvria">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+20 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+40 Size 9</boost>
<boost>+80 Range is short</boost>
<description>
Transfers a disease, infection or other natural ailment (not a wound) from
one living creature to another living creature. Both make stamina rolls to
resist, and the spell fails unless they are both failed. Neither creature can
be greater than size 6.
</description>
</spell>
</grimoire>
