<?xml version="1.0"?>

<grimoire convocation="Jmorvi">
    <preface>
        <para>
            Jmorvi Shek-Pvar, standing between fire and earth, have an affinity for
            all minerals, but especially metals. Their element is the solid heart of
            the world, steel and black iron.
        </para>

        <para>
            Most Jmorvi are artificers; their magic tends to run in a slower vein
            than that of other Shek-Pvar. The element and its manipulators are powerful
            and unyielding, but sometimes brittle, insensitive, brutal and shallow.
            Jmorvi distrust the spiritual believing the soul of humanity to be
            unpredictable and unreliable. They prefer the sureness and solidity of
            cold, hard steel.
        </para>

        <para>
            Several Jmorvi spells can be used to enhance the toughness of
            materials. Enhancing fully metallic items is easier than
            enhancing partially metallic or other items. If it is used to
            enchant armour, then the basic bonus given to the soak of the
            item is the soak to use if the armour itself is harmed. The
            soak bonus gained by the wearer of the armour depends on the
            type of armour being enhanced.
        </para>

        <targetlist>
            <targetLabel>Soak</targetLabel>
            <valueLabel>Type of armour</valueLabel>

            <entry target="1/20" value="Helm, greaves or vambraces"/>
            <entry target="1/10" value="Breastplate, vest"/>
            <entry target="1/5" value="Habergeon, jacket, leggings"/>
            <entry target="2/5" value="Hauberk"/>
        </targetlist>

        <para>
            For example, a +30 bonus to a chain hauberk would only give a
            +12 bonus to the wearer's soak. The same bonus to a metal helm
            would only give +1.
        </para>

    </preface>

    <spell name="Sight of Eneldir" level="10" convocation="jmorvi">
        <time>15 minutes</time>
        <range>Far</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+10 Range 500m</boost>
        <boost>+20 Range 1km</boost>
        <boost>+40 Range 2km</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                A spell to detect and identify metallic minerals. The
                caster declares a specific metallic mineral and learns
                the direction to the nearest (single) 'good source'.
                A small amount of refined metal in close proximity is
                more noticeable than a large deposit of ore a hundred
                metres away. Although the spell ignores any Focus
                through which it is cast, it may detect a companion's
                sword.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Ward of Sirik" level="10" convocation="jmorvi">
        <range>Touch</range>
        <duration>Ward</duration>
        <boost>+10 Can affect mostly metallic objects</boost>
        <boost>+20 Target can be size 5</boost>
        <boost>+40 Target can be size 10</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                This ward protects a wholly metallic object of up to size 3
                from harm. It grants a +15 to soak the next time significant
                damage (i.e. a soak roll is required) is suffered. The ward
                then terminates. If it is placed on armour, it only grants
                one third the protection to the wearer. This ward cannot be
                stacked with other wards.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>


    <spell name="Greater Ward of Sirik" level="30" convocation="jmorvi">
        <range>Touch</range>
        <duration>Ward</duration>
        <boost>+15 Can affect mostly metallic objects</boost>
        <boost>+30 Target can be size 10</boost>
        <boost>+60 Soak increased by 30</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                This ward will protect a wholly metallic object up to size 5
                from harm. The next time the object is harmed, its soak is
                raised by +30. If the ward is placed on armour, then one third
                of this bonus is granted to the wearer. This ward cannot be
                stacked with any other ward.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Aspect of Tarus" level="30" convocation="jmorvi">
        <range>Touch</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+15 Maximum weight 500kg</boost>
        <boost>+30 Surface is more durable</boost>
        <boost>+60 Can change to denser metal</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                An enchantment which transforms the surface of a wholly metallic
                object into another metal. The enchantment is fragile, and, because
                it only places an extremely thin veneer, transformed objects will
                not pass more than a cursory inspection. Scratching the object,
                even with a fingernail, removes some of the plating. The
                transformation must be to a lower density metal. The maximum weight
                of the object is 100kg.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Tempering of Pytama" level="30" convocation="jmorvi">
        <time>8 hours</time>
        <range>Touch</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Momentary</duration>
        <boost>+15 Can affect mostly metallic weapon</boost>
        <boost>+30 Raise two qualities</boost>
        <boost>+60 Raise three qualities</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                An enchantment to increase the weapon quality of a wholly metallic
                weapon. With success, one statistic (initiative, attack, defence
                or damage) is increased by 1.  This is not cumulative with any
                other weapon enhancing magic, including rune magic.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Sirik's Cant" level="60" convocation="jmorvi">
        <range>Near</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+15 Can be laid on mostly metallic object</boost>
        <boost>+30 Object can be made to shatter</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                An enchantment which causes a wholly metallic object to resonate
                and grow warmer. This makes the object difficult to use and
                justifies an immediate penalty of at least 10. The object cannot
                weight more than 15kg.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Anvil of Pytama" level="60" convocation="jmorvi">
        <time>8 hours</time>
        <range>Touch</range>
        <duration>Momentary</duration>
        <boost>+15 Can affect a mostly metallic object</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                A minor artifact power installed in a wholly metallic weapon
                to increase its damage. It cannot be combined with any other
                enchantment. The weapon does +2 damage.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Sirik's Protection" level="60" convocation="jmorvi">
        <range>Touch</range>
        <duration>Ward</duration>
        <boost>+15 Can affect mostly Jmorvin objects</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                This spell affects any metallic, stone or crystalline objects
                of up to size 5. It is a ward which grants a +30 bonus to
                soak next time the object is harmed. If the object is being
                used as armour, the wearer gains a +10 bonus to their soak.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>



    <spell name="Fist of Kuhan" level="90" convocation="jmorvi">
        <range>Self</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+15 Range touch</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                An enchantment which infuses the caster's hands with Jmorvi
                essence, allowing them to strike for real damage. The limbs
                stiffen only when actually hitting or parrying, so there is
                no loss of flexibility.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell  name="Forge of Obras" level="90" convocation="jmorvi">
        <time>8 hours</time>
        <range>Touch</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+15 Affects 50kg of metal</boost>
        <boost>+30 Can change into a denser metal</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                An enchantment to change up to 10kg of metal into a different
                metal which is less dense.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Skin of the Rock" level="90" convocation="jmorvi">
        <range>Self</range>
        <duration>Ward</duration>
        <boost>+15 Range is touch</boost>
        <boost>+30 Bonus is +20</boost>
        <boost>+60 Bonus is +25</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                This spell harden's the skin of the caster, giving her a +15
                bonus to soak. The ward comes into affect the next time the
                caster is injured, and then terminates. It cannot be combined
                with other wards on the same target.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>


    <spell name="Myrthil's Shield" level="90" convocation="jmorvi">
        <range>Self</range>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+15 Range is touch</boost>
        <boost>+30 Skin colour is unaffected</boost>
        <boost>+60 Agility and dexterity penalty negated</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                Grants the caster a +4 to their soak while the spell is being
                maintained. This spell can be stacked with itself. The skin
                will take on a slightly darker hue while the spell is in
                effect, and the toughness of the skin means a -4 penalty
                to all dexterity and agility rolls.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>


    <spell name="Tharasin's Ward" level="120" convocation="jmorvi">
        <time>8 hours</time>
        <range>Touch</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Momentary</duration>
        <boost>+20 Can affect mostly metal armour</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                An enchantment to increase the soak of wholly metallic
                armour. The soak of such armour is increased by a base
                of +5, modified by the type of armour. This cannot be
                combined with another similar enchantment, including
                rune magic.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>


    <spell name="Barl's Cloak" level="160" convocation="jmorvi">
        <range>Self</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+20 Range is touch</boost>
        <boost>+40 Skin colour is unaffected</boost>
        <boost>+60 Penalties are negated</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                An enchantment which toughens the skin to protect like
                armour. The skin assumes a slight blue-black colour
                while the enchantment is in place. The caster's soak is
                increased by 6. This spell can be stacked with itself.
                The target of the spell suffers a -6 penalty to agility
                and dexterity rolls while the spell is in effect.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

</grimoire>
