<grimoire convocation="Lyahvi">
<preface>
Lyahvi is the magic of the air, of the insubstantial, the invisible, the 
ethereal, and the illusionary. Lyahvian mages are manipulators of light: 
reflection, refraction and confusion, with effects faster than the eye and 
difficult to describe. They are masters of air and other gases, of sound 
(which travels on the air), and they can summon Asiri and other ethereals to 
their benefit. The Lyahvi nemesis is earth, represented by the convocation of 
Fyvria. The essence of Lyahvi is bright, sterile and unliving.
Secondary: Peleahn, Savorya
Tertiary: Jmorvi, Odivshe
Diametric: Fyvria
</preface>

<spell name="Darin's Sprite" level="20" convocation="lyahvi">
<level>10 + 5 conc + 5 effect</level>
<range>-1 to control / 1m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Summons a sapient element of Lyahvi, which appears as a small mote of light, 
about as bright as a candle flame. The elemental has limited intelligence, but 
can follow simple instructions. It cannot pass through solid matter, but can 
travel as much as 25m away from the caster. If it is commanded to travel 
further than this, then control over it will be lost. It can see and hear, 
though cannot understand any speech other than its elemental language, and 
will have difficulty telling mundane creatures apart. All communication with 
the elemental is speech, in the tongue of the lyahvian element. Opposed Will 
rolls must be made when the sprite is summoned in order to control it. The 
sprite will have a will of one.
</description>
<notes>
Each level of effect gives 5m of range for the elemental. This is a type I 
elemental, more powerful types can be summoned by increasing the base level of 
the spell by 10 per type.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Ablarin's Field" level="15" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="I"> 5 + 5 conc + 5 effect</level>
<range>-1 bonus / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
The spell is placed upon an object, which may be the caster, another creature 
or an inanimate object. All sound near that point is muffled, and perception 
tasks are at +5 difficulty to hear sounds from the target. The spell effects 
anything within a metre radius of the target point.
</description>
<notes>
Base is 5 to manipulate noise, +5 for concentratioin duration. Each +1 then 
gives +1 bonus to stealth rolls. Effect is reduced by 5 per 1m distance.
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Aeric's Whisper" level="10" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="I">5 + 5 effect</level>
<range>+1/10m to awareness</range>
<resist>None</resist>
<description>
When cast, the caster's voice is carried to a designated spot within line of 
sight. The voice travels the intervening distance, though in a reasonably 
tight beam. The spell lasts for one round. Listeners at the other end must 
make an awareness roll to hear the caster's voice, at difficulty 5 + 1/10m.
</description>
<notes>
Base of 5 for shaping sound, +5 for the effect, which reduces awareness 
difficulty from a base of 10, to 5. Higher effects will make the voice clearer 
at longer range.
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Beacon of Isala" level="15" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="I">5 + 5 conc + 5 effect</level>
<range>-1 effect / 10m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Causes the air around the target point to glow softly, with as much light as a 
torch. If the target is an object, then the light will move with that object. 
Sentients get a will roll to resist the spell if they are made the target.
</description>
<notes>
Base of 5 for creating candle light, the effect of +5 makes it torchlight, 
then +5 for concentration. The spell causes a spot (about torch size) to light 
up, or the whole object if it is smaller.
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Crimson Rune" level="15" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="I">5 + 5 conc + 5 complex</level>
<range>-1 dexterity / 1 m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
The caster traces out shapes on a surface, leaving a glowing mark which can be 
simple shapes, or complex writing. The caster must make a dexterity roll of 
difficulty 10 for simple shapes, 15 for writing or 20 for fine writing. The 
runes can be written in the air, or on a solid object. If the target is a 
sentient, then they get a will roll to resist.
</description>
<notes>
Base is 5 for candlelight, +5 for concentration, then +5 for being a complex, 
changing effect. Adding an effect modifier would give a bonus to the dexterity 
roll (+1 / +1).
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Aeric's Silken Voice" level="25" method="shape" 
convocation="lyahvi">
<level>5 + 5 conc + 15 effect</level>
<range>-1 skill bonus / 1m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Modifies sound making it clearer and generally more pleasant. The upshot is 
that the target of the spell gets a +3 bonus to skill rolls involving sound, 
such as speaking, singing or playing a musical instrument.
</description>
<notes>
Base is 5 for shaping a sound, +5 to make it a concentration spell. Each +5 
effect gives +1 bonus to skill rolls.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Cloak of Kalaerin" level="20" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="II">5 + 5 conc + 10 effect</level>
<range>-1 bonus / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Hides an inanimate object, giving -5 penalty to spot it. Normally, thed 
ifficulty to spot an object in a room is 15 - 3 x size of the object.
</description>
<notes>
Normally, difficulty to spot an object in a room is 15 - 3 x size. This spell 
adds +1 to difficulty per 2 levels of spell. Base difficulty is 5, with no 
modifier for object size, since larger objects are going to need greater 
effects to hide them anyway. If object moves, then the spell is broken. +5 to 
make it last concentration.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Hlandor's Flash" level="25" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="II">15 + 10 effect</level>
<range>-1 / 5m</range>
<resist>Perception + 1 / m</resist>
<description>
Causes a bright flash of light, which can blind those looking at it. A 
perception roll is made at difficulty 20, and if failed, a -5 penalty is 
suffered to actions for the next minute. Creatures suffer a -5 to the 
resistance rolls in gloomy conditions, and -10 in dark conditions (due to loss 
of night vision).
</description>
<notes> Effectively just creates a bright light for a brief moment. Perception 
difficulty is 10 + the effect of the spell. It's not that much use in full 
daylight.
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Lens of Ikara" level="20" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level>5 + 10 effect + 5 conc</level>
<range>-1 size / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>Shapes the appearance of an object up to size 6 in minor ways. 
The colour, exact shape or size can be changed, though the basic structure of 
the object will still be the same. The object can be 50% bigger or smaller 
(though no larger than size 6). A glass could become a vase, a dog a cat etc. 
If the object moves, the spell is broken. The change is a visual illusion only 
- touch, smell or sound is not effected.
</description>
<notes>Each five levels of effect will change an object up to 3 points of 
size. Add 5 levels to the base spell to affect sound or smell, ten levels for 
both.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Globe of Setath" level="40" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="III">15 + 5 conc + 20 effect</level>
<range>-1 effect / 1m</range>
<resist>Perception +1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Creates a glowing ball of flashing light, which confuses people who look at 
it. Make perception rolls 20+ to resist confusion. Suffer penalty equal to 
half effect.
</description>
<notes>
Effect gives difficulty of 10 + 1/2 effect. 15 is base for confusion 
illusions, +5 to make it last concentration. Each 5 metres reduces difficulty 
by 1.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Prism of Gethan" level="30" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="III">15 + 5 conc +10 effect</level>
<range>-1 effect / 1m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Creates a still, purely optical, illusion. Difficulty 25 to spot it as an 
illusion.
</description>
<notes>
Base illusion difficulty is 3 per point of size, so this creates something of 
human size. Base perception roll to notice it as an illusion is 15, plus 
effect, plus 1 per 10 metres of distance of observer.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Sight of Castranel" level="30" method="know" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="III">10 + 5 conc + 15 effect</level>
<range>-1 perception / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Allows the target to see clearly through air as if they had a perception of 3. 
The spell ignores all effects such as mist, rain, fog and smoke. The target 
creatures new perception cannot be higher than its base (so a blind creature  
cannot be allowed to see with this spell). It does not grant the ability to 
see in darkness.
</description>
<notes>
Each five levels of effect give a perception score of 1 to the target. The 
targets new perception can never be raised higher than their natural 
perception. Versions of the spell to see clearly in low light are five levels 
higher. To see in total darkness, add ten levels to the spell base.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Beam of Nolar" level="45" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="IV">10 + 5 conc + 30 effect</level>
<range>-1 effect / 1m</range>
<resist>Perception + 1 / 5m; Soak + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>Creates a beam of light. Can blind if perception 25+ is failed. 
Also burns for damage equal to quarter effect. Damage and difficulty are  
reduced by 1 per five metres of distance.</description>
<notes>
Perception difficulty is 10 + half effect. Burn damage is minor, and probably 
won't do very much at all. It is difficult to harm directly with Lyahvi.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Entora's Mirror" level="40" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="IV">15 + 5 conc + 20 effect</level>
<range>-1 spot difficulty / 10m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Creates an image of an object being touched within range of the  spell. 
Difficulty to spot as an illusion is 25.
</description>
<notes>
As for normal image creation, but difficulty is 15 + effect for spotting, 
since the caster has something to work off. Add two range modifiers if the 
object is not to be touched. Add normal modifiers for animation etc if the 
object is changing - the base spell only shows a snapshot.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Light of Aestir" level="50" method="know" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="IV">25 + 5 conc + 20 effect</level>
<range>-1 / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Reveals any ethereal, illusionary or invisible objects or creatures. Illusions 
have their spot difficulty reduced by effect of the spell. Ethereal creatures 
are considered to have a spot of 30 for purposes of the spell (and considered 
invisible). Effect is reduced by 1 per 5 metres. Creatures get a will roll 
against the casters will to be effected.
</description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Wind of Sharis" level="55" method="change" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="IV">10 + 5 conc + 40 effect</level>
<range>-1000l / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Changes 40,000 litres of air into stale, difficult to breathe, air. 40K litres 
is about euivalent to a small room. The spell is normally centred on the 
caster - each 5m range reduces effect by one (volume by 1000l).
</description>
<notes>
Each point of effect changes a cubic metre (1000l). Halve this to change air 
to non-breathable. Fifth it to change it to poisonous. Similar effect level  
would make stale air fresh etc. Air must be in line of sight, so not already 
in someone's body.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Evardin's Tube" level="55" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="V">30 + 5 conc + 20 effect</level>
<range>-1000l / 1m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Make 10Kl of a substance ethereal, such that it can be passed through. Only 
inanimate objects can be so enchanted. Affecting elements other than those
normally affected by Lyahvi has a penalty to the casting roll equal to -5 for
secondary elements, -15 for tertiary elements and -30 for diametric elements.
Neutral elements (if any) are at -10.
</description>
<notes>Each level of effect affects 500l of substance.</notes>
</spell>

<spell names="Motes of Arden" level="60" method="shape" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="V">15 + 5 conc + 40 effect</level>
<range>-1 penalty / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
A swarm of dancing, brightly flashing motes are created which swarm around the 
target point, confusing anyone caught within the area. The area is up to 40m 
across, and anyone caught within it suffers a -20 penalty to actions.
</description>
<notes>
Each point of effect creates motes over a diameter in metres equal to the 
effect, and gives a penalty of half this.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Passage of Lyah" level="65" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="V">45 + 5 conc + 15 effect</level>
<range>-1 size / 1m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
The target of the spell is made translucent and semi-ethereal, though this 
only affects sentient creatures, so no clothing or equipment will be affected 
along with them. The target has difficulty movin. Normal air resists as if 
they were swimming in molasses, and maximum movement is agility metres per 
round. Solid objects, such as walls, can be moved through at about a tenth 
this speed. The target cannot be easily harmed - sword slashes etc will be 
fealt as a stinging pain, but actual damage will only be done on a natural 
roll of 20.
</description>
<notes>Every 5 points of effects will change a creature of size two. It is an 
extra 15 levels to change a complicated target, such as a creature wearing 
clothes.</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Visions of Sheridyn" level="60" method="shape" 
convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="V"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Maslor's Charm" level="60" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="VI"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Wind of Ardian" level="60" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="VI"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Figure of Aestir" level="80" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="VII"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Vapour of Hirin" level="80" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="VII"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>

</grimoire>

