<grimoire convocation="Lyahvi">
<preface>
Lyahvi is the magic of the air, of the insubstantial, the invisible,
the	ethereal, and the illusionary. Lyahvian mages are manipulators of
light:	reflection, refraction and confusion, with effects faster than the
eye and	difficult to describe. They are masters of air and other gases, of
sound	(which travels on the air), and they can summon Asiri and other
ethereals to	their benefit. The Lyahvi nemesis is earth, represented by the
convocation of	Fyvria. The essence of Lyahvi is bright, sterile and
unliving.	Secondary: Peleahn, Savorya	Tertiary: Jmorvi, Odivshe	Diametric:
Fyvria
</preface>

<spell name="Ablarin's Field" level="10" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Medium</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Effect is +10.</boost>
<boost>+20 Effect is +15.</boost>
<boost>+40 Effect is +20.</boost>
<description>
The spell is placed upon an object, which may be the caster, another
creature	or an inanimate object. All sound near that point is muffled, and
perception	tasks are at +5 difficulty to hear sounds from the target. The
spell effects	anything within a metre radius of the target point.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Darin's Sprite" level="10" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 range short</boost>
<boost>+20 range medium</boost>
<boost>+40 range far</boost>
<description>
Summons a sapient element of Lyahvi, which appears as a small mote of
light,	about as bright as a candle flame. The elemental has limited
intelligence, but	can follow simple instructions. It cannot pass through
solid matter, but can	travel as much as 25m away from the caster. If it is
commanded to travel	further than this, then control over it will be lost. It
can see and hear,	though cannot understand any speech other than its
elemental language, and	will have difficulty telling mundane creatures
apart. All communication with	the elemental is speech, in the tongue of the
lyahvian element. Opposed Will	rolls must be made when the sprite is
summoned in order to control it. The	sprite will have a will of one.
</description>
</spell>

 <spell name="Aeric's Whisper" level="10" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Medium</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Message need not be spoken aloud</boost>
<boost>+20 Range far</boost>
<description>
When cast, the caster's voice is carried to a designated spot within line
of	sight. The voice travels the intervening distance, though in a
reasonably	tight beam. The spell lasts for one round.
</description>
</spell>
 
<spell name="Beacon of Isala" level="10" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will + 1/5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Range near</boost>
<boost>+20 Range short, or campfire brightness</boost>
<boost>+40 Range medium, or bonfire brightness</boost>
<description>
Causes the air around the target point to glow softly, with as much light as
a torch. If the target is an object, then the light will move with that
object. Sentients get a will roll to resist the spell if they are made the
target. The more powerful incantations of this spell can increase the range
of the spell, or the brightness.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Crimson Rune" level="10" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Range is reach</boost>
<boost>+20 Duration is sun</boost>
<boost>+40 Duration is moon</boost>
<description>
The caster traces out shapes on a surface, leaving a glowing mark which can
be simple shapes, or complex writing. The runes can be written in the air, or
on a solid object.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Aeric's Silken Voice" level="30" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range is touch</boost>
<boost>+30 Effect is +10</boost>
<description>
Modifies sound making it clearer and generally more pleasant. The upshot is
that the target of the spell gets a +5 bonus to skill rolls involving sound,
such as speaking, singing or playing a musical instrument.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Cloak of Kalaerin" level="30" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Effect is 10</boost>
<boost>+30 Effect is 15</boost>
<boost>+60 Effect is 20</boost>
<description>
Hides an inanimate object, giving -5 penalty to spot it. Normally, the
difficulty to spot an object in a room is 15 - 3 x size of the object, higher
if viewer is distracted.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Hlandor's Flash" level="30" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Perception 20</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Resist is 25</boost>
<boost>+30 Resist is 30</boost>
<boost>+60 Resist is 35</boost>
<description>
Causes a bright flash of light, which can blind those looking at it. A
perception roll is made at difficulty 20, and if failed, a -5 penalty is
suffered to actions for the next minute. Creatures suffer a -5 to the
resistance rolls in gloomy conditions, and -10 in dark conditions (due to
loss of night vision).
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Lens of Ikara" level="30" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+30 Maximum size 9</boost>
<boost>+60 Maximum size 12</boost>
<description>
Shapes the appearance of an object up to size 6 in minor ways. The colour,
exact shape or size can be changed, though the basic structure of the object
will still be the same. The object can be 50% bigger or smaller (though no
larger than size 6). A glass could become a vase, a dog a cat etc. If the
object moves, the spell is broken. The change is a visual illusion only -
touch, smell or sound is not effected.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Globe of Setath" level="60" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Perception 25</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+20 Resist of 30</boost>
<boost>+40 Penalty of -20</boost>
<boost>+80 Range is short</boost>
<description>
Creates a glowing ball of flashing light above the head of the caster. Any
within range who looks towards the caster must make a perception roll of 25+
or suffer a penalty to all actions of -10.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Prism of Gethan" level="60" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+20 Illusion quality is 35</boost>
<boost>+40 Maximum size is 12</boost>
<boost>+80 Illusion can be animated</boost>
<description>
Creates a still, purely optical, illusion. In order to spot that it is an
illusion requires a perception x awareness roll of 25 + 1 / 10m of distance,
though the fact that it does not move tends to be a give away. The illusion
can be of any three dimensional object up to size 6. More powerful castings
of this spell may allow the illusion to be animated. The animation must be a
simple and repetitive (such as rippling cloak or hair).
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Sight of Castranel" level="60" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Medium</range>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+20 Range is far</boost>
<boost>+40 Can see in darkness</boost>
<boost>+80 Can grant ability to touched target</boost>
<description>
Allows the castert to see clearly through air ignoring all weather effects up
to the range of the spell. Does not grant ability to see in darkness.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Beam of Nolar" level="100" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Perception 25</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+25 Resist is 35</boost>
<boost>+50 Range short</boost>
<boost>+100 Range medium</boost>
<description>
A blinding, burning beam of light shoots forth from the caster's hand,
automatically hitting the specified target within range. If a perception roll
of 25+ is not made, the target is blinded for one hour per point failed by.
On a fumble, they are blinded permanently. The beam also burns, causing +10
damage.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Entora's Mirror" level="100" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Short</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+25 Range is Far</boost>
<boost>+50 Size is 25</boost>
<boost>+100 Object can be animate</boost>
<description>
Creates an image of an object being touched within range of the  spell.
Difficulty to spot as an illusion is 40. Can be cast on any inanimate object
up to size 12.
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Light of Aestir" level="100" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Medium</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+25 Range far</boost>
<description>
Reveals any ethereal, illusionary or invisible objects or creatures as they
really are. Sapient creatures get an opposed will roll to resist the effects
of this spell, all freestanding illusions are automatically seen through.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Wind of Sharis" level="100" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Near</range>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+25 Air can be made poisonous</boost>
<boost>+50 Effect 100Kl of air</boost>
<boost>+100 Effect 250Kl of air</boost>
<description>
Changes 40,000 litres of air into stale, difficult to breathe, air. 40K
litres is about equivalent to a small room. The spell is normally centred on
the caster. Higher incantations of this spell can make the air poisonous,
which requires a stamina roll of 30+ each round to avoid nausea or sickness,
and a -15 penalty.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Evardin's Tube" level="150" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<description>
Turns an amount of inanimate material etheral, allowing it to be passed
through. A tube 2m wide, 10m long can be created.
</description>
</spell>

<spell names="Motes of Arden" level="150" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="V">15 + 5 conc + 40 effect</level>
<range>Medium</range>
<resist>Perception 30</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+25 Caster and specified friends not affected</boost>
<boost>+50 Area is 100m across</boost>
<boost>+100 Penalty is -30</boost>
<description>
A swarm of dancing, brightly flashing motes are created which swarm around
the	target point, confusing anyone caught within the area. The area is up to
30m	across, and anyone caught within it suffers a -20 penalty to actions.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Passage of Lyah" level="150" convocation="lyahvi">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+25 Range is touch</boost>
<boost>+50 Effects non-Fyvria clothes and equipment</boost>
<boost>+100 Effects all equipment</boost>
<description>
The target of the spell is made translucent and semi-ethereal, though
this	only affects sentient creatures, so no clothing or equipment will be
affected along with them. The target has difficulty moving. Normal air
resists as if they were swimming in molasses, and maximum movement is agility
metres per round. Solid objects, such as walls, can be moved through at about
a tenth	this speed. The target cannot be easily harmed - sword slashes etc
will be	fealt as a stinging pain, but actual damage will only be done on a
natural roll of 20. Affected targets cannot be larger than the wizard.
</description>
</spell>

 <spell name="Visions of Sheridyn" level="150" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="V"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Maslor's Charm" level="200" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="VI"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Wind of Ardian" level="200" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="VI"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Figure of Aestir" level="250" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="VII"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Vapour of Hirin" level="250" convocation="lyahvi">
<level complex="VII"></level>
<range></range>
<resist></resist>
<description></description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>
</grimoire>
