<grimoire convocation="Neutral">
<preface>
<para>
The Neutral convocation affects energy and magic directly.
It rarely has any physical effect, though is good for
defending against other magics.
</para>

<para>
Neutral elementals are raw magic, random and wild. They
appear as a whirling cloud of bright motes. They cannot
pass through physical objects, but can slip through a gap
of almost any size.
</para>

<para>
The elemental's perception of the world is one based on
aura's. Objects without an aura cannot be truly perceived,
except as a featureless flatness. Living creatures, especially
sapiants, can be clearly seen, and recognised by their aura.
The aura sense of a magic elemental is equal to 5 x rank,
though they can always tell the elemental affinity of a
creature, including Shek-Pvar.
</para>

<para>
A magical elemental may strike at the lifeforce of a target,
causing fatigue and confusion.
</para>
</preface>

<spell name="Abort" level="0" convocation="neutral">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+25 Range is short</boost>
<boost>+50 Range is medium</boost>
<boost>+100 Range is far</boost>
<description>
Abort disrupts another spell while it is being cast. The target 
spell caster is touched, and if the spell being cast is of equal 
or lower rank than the Abort, then the spell may be aborted, 
assuming the target spellcaster fails an opposed will check. The 
abort must be cast before the target spell is finished. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Chain" level="0" convocation="neutral">
<range>Self</range>
<duration>Special</duration>
<description>
Chain links together multiple other spells, deferring fatigue 
until after all the spells have been cast. No spell in the 
chain can be higher rank than the Chain itself, and at most, 
1 spell per rank of Chain (not including Chain itself) can 
be chained together. All the spells to be cast are declared, 
together with their order, targets etc, and chain is cast. 
If successful, the other spells are each cast. Once the final 
spell is cast, fatigue for all spells (including the chain) is 
then gained. No spell in the chain can have a casting time 
longer than a round, and all must be cast within a round of 
each other. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Detect" level="0" convocation="neutral">
<range>Touch</range>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+25 Range is near</boost>
<description>
Detects magic in items and enchantments. The caster will see the
item glow with a soft light in the colour of the enchantment's
convocation. If the detected magic is of equal or lower rank of
the detect, then the rank of the magic is known, otherwise it is
simply known that it is of higher rank.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Dispel" level="0" convocation="neutral">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+25 Range is short</boost>
<boost>+50 Range is medium</boost>
<boost>+100 Range is far</boost>
<description>
This spell dispels another spell of equal or lower rank. The 
spell to be removed must have been identified. Only spells of 
duration Concentration or Ward can be affected. If the spell 
is being concentrated on, then the owner of that spell must 
make a will check against the caster of Dispel. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Raldyn's Bubble" level="0" convocation="neutral">
<range>Self</range>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+25 Caster can expand/contract the bubble</boost>
<boost>+50 Caster can move, and the bubble will follow</boost>
<boost>+100 Bubble can be detached, fixing it at one point</boost>
<description>
When the spell is cast, a sphere is created around the caster 
the prevents any enchantments of lower rank from entering. 
Permanent enchantments are suspended by the spell. The caster 
cannot cast spells of lower rank herself while this spell is up. 
Also, she cannot move. If she moves, the bubble collapses. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Eye of Kemdal" level="10" convocation="neutral">
<range>1km</range>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Range is 2km</boost>
<boost>+20 Range is 5km</boost>
<boost>+40 Range is 10km</boost>
<description>
A spell permitting the caster to survey his environment for the nearest 
spatio-temporal discontinuity (such as a godstone, Barasai Point, 
interdimensional vortex or other interworld portal). If it is out of 
range, she will learn its direction. Otherwise, she'll learn its 
general nature and rough distance.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Ear of Pvara" level="10" convocation="neutral">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Can touch a person to allow them to understand the target instead</boost>
<boost>+20 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+40 Limited understanding of animals possible</boost>
<description>
An enchantment that enables the caster to understand a single, specified 
person in the absence of a common language. It does not allow the target to 
understand the caster. The level of skill granted with the language is 3. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Tongue of Pvara" level="10" convocation="neutral">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Can touch a person to allow them to speak</boost>
<boost>+20 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+40 Can speak with animals</boost>
<description>
A self enchantment that enables the caster to be understood by a single, 
specified person in the absence of a common language. It does not allow her 
to understand the target. The level of skill granted with the language 
is 3.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Veil of Nashal" level="10" convocation="neutral">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Ward</duration>
<boost>+40 Bonus is +10</boost>
<description>
A spell to protect the caster from enchantment by granting a +5 
bonus to resist the effects of a spell. This can be either a 
bonus to will, soak or any other applicable defence. Multiple 
veils can be stacked, but each only affects one spell. The veil 
hinders the caster's own spells. Each veil gives a cumulative -10 
penalty to all spell casting rolls. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Open" level="10" convocation="neutral">
<time>1 hour</time>
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Special</duration>
<description>
Opens a minor artifact ready for storing spells into it. The 
artifact must have had 'focus' cast on it previously. An opened 
artifact can have spells placed into it with the use of Store. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Store" level="0" convocation="neutral">
<range>Touch</range>
<duration>Special</duration>
<description>
Stores the next spell cast into a minor artifact which has been 
opened for enchantment. The spell to be stored must be cast on 
the following round, and must be of at most the rank of the Store. 
Only the basic spell is stored - any effects of options are ignored. 
The spell to be stored cannot have a casting time longer than a round. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Close" level="0" convocation="neutral">
<time>1 hour</time>
<range>Touch</range>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+25 Artifact can be activated with gestures</boost>
<boost>+50 Artifact can be actived with mental command. This 
requires the artifact to be attuned to</boost>
<description>
Closes an opened minor artifact. At this point the trigger event 
for the artifact is also declared. The basic spell allows command 
phrases to activate the artifact.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Disrupt" level="0" convocation="neutral">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+25 Range is short</boost>
<boost>+50 Range is medium</boost>
<boost>+100 Range is far</boost>
<description>
This spell disrupts all magic in the area. Spells which are currently 
up will fail if their rank is less than or equal to the disrupt, however 
the Shek-Pvar maintaining the spell gets a will check to resist. Major 
artifacts are unaffected, though if they are maintaining spell effects, 
then they need to make a will roll as well to keep them maintained. 
Minor artifacts can be destroyed with this spell. If the Close that was 
used is of a equal or lower rank, then all spells in the minor artifact 
are lost. If the Focus is of equal or lower rank, then the artifact is 
rendered non-magical (and hence any spells in it are lost, regardless 
of the Close). 
</description>
</spell>

</grimoire>

