<grimoire convocation="Odivshe">
<preface>
<para>
Odivshe is the magic of slow, cool darkness, of water and ice, the opposite 
of fire and action. Odivshe magi study and work their spells on water and 
shadow, ice and cold. They are sometimes called the wizards of gloom. 
</para>

<para>
As well as these mundane elements, the Odivshe sometimes manipulate ethereal 
water. This "substance" takes a variety of forms, generally similar to 
ordinary water, but thinner, sometimes invisible. Often it is described as an 
"icy pallor that robs away the breath and drowns the very spirit with its 
dark, clinging, gloom". It takes about twice as long to drown in ethereal 
water, although this may be small comfort to those who have the experience. 
In general, ethereal water is easier to walk/run through than mundane water 
(half air movement rates), and more difficult to swim in (double fatigue).
</para>

<para>
The Odivshe use it because it is easier to manipulate than mundane water. 
Ethereal water effects ethereal creatures as mundane water affects mundane 
creatures. It will also quench ethereal fire.
</para>

<para>
Secondary: Fyvrian or Savoryan; Tertiary: Jmorvi or Lyahvi; 
Diametric: Peleahn 
</para>
</preface>

<spell name="Azure Hand" level="10" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+10 Range near</boost>
<boost>+20 Ignore all wound penalties</boost>
<boost>+40 Doesn't cause a fatigue level</boost>
<description>
A spell to gently reduce the temperature of an object. It works best on 
objects containing high proportions of water, and can cause minor discomfort 
to organic creatures. It is a good treatment for sunstroke, and can deaden 
pain. It causes one level of fatigue, and reduces wound penalties from wounds 
by one level. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Bonal's Quenching" level="10" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+20 One third as much water</boost>
<description>
Changes the water in the target's body to make it more refreshing 
and capable of sustaining life longer. It allows the target to 
survive on half as much water. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Power of Ulmer" level="10" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Size 10</boost>
<boost>+20 Size 20</boost>
<description>
Increases the buoyancy of an object, by an amount equivalent 
to its water content. Something with the equivalence of a human 
body can be affected up to size five, making it twice as buoyant, 
capable of even sleeping when floating, and doubling swimming 
speeds. Only half the amount of wood can be affected, and metal 
or rock can not be affected at all. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Chill" level="10" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Touch</range>
	<resist>Stamina</resist>
	<duration>Momentary</duration>
	<boost>+10 Range is reach</boost>
	<boost>+20 Maximum size is one</boost>
	<boost>+40 Temperature drops to -1C, freezing the target</boost>
	<description>
		Cools an object down to four degrees celcius, of not larger than
		size zero. Object will begin to regain temperature again at normal
		rate. If the object is a living creature, then it gets to resist,
		though failure will probably result in its death.
	</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Daenin's Specter" level="10" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Self</range>
	<resist>Will; Stamina to resist fatigue</resist>
	<duration>Concentration</duration>
	<boost>+10 The shadow does +5 fatigue damage</boost>
	<boost>+20 The shadow does +10 fatigue damage</boost>
	<description>
		Causes the Shek-Pvar's shadow to become enchanted, channelling
		ethereal cold into whatever passes through it. Any who touch
		or pass over it must make a resistence roll or suffer a feeling
		of coldness and unease. At sunset, a person's shadow is about
		150% of their height.
	</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Glamour of Fanon" level="60" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Range near</boost>
<boost>+30 Size 12</boost>
<description>
Reduces the temperature of an inanimate object up to size 6, by 
100 degrees Celsius. The object will return to room temperature 
normally.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Mouth of Lathal" level="60" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range touch</boost>
<boost>+30 Target can breathe air and water</boost>
<description>
Enables the target to breathe water, though does also remove the 
ability to breathe air as well. Creatures up to size six can be 
affected.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Tarl's Crystals" level="60" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Self</range>
<area>Far</area>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range far x2</boost>
<boost>+30 Hailstones 50x larger</boost>
<description>
An enchantment which enlarges snowflakes, raindrops, hailstones, 
or other precipitation over a wide area near the caster. Generally, 
the maximum effect is to combine 20 hailstones/raindrops into one. 
Effects of this are left to GM discretion. The spell does not cause 
hail or rain in the first place. The effects are centred on the caster. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Chalsa's Sponge" level="30" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<description>
An enchantment which causes the target to retain moisture. The 
effect can be unpredictable. In most cases sponge reduces and/or 
prevents thirst, and prevents or inhibits the loss of bodily 
fluids such as sweat, tears and urine. The spell eliminates the 
need for water, but does not affect thirst, so it can be used 
to traverse a desert, but not comfortably. After a few days, 
the target becomes bloated with retained moisture; they are 
generally immobilised after five to seven days, and die in ten. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Shadow of Yanar" level="30" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Self</range>
<area>Near</area>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range near</boost>
<boost>+30 Range short</boost>
<boost>+60 Area short</boost>
<description>
Forms a sphere of darkness emanating from the point indicated by 
the caster. The region within the sphere is pitch black. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Tarl's Alchema" level="30" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Stamina</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Affects 100l</boost>
<boost>+30 Affects 1Kl</boost>
<boost>+60 Affects 100Kl</boost>
<description>
A spell to separate discrete liquids from a mixture, causing 
them to form strata within the container. It cannot be used 
to break natural liquids into their components (e.g. water 
into hydrogen and oxygen, but ethanol could be purified from 
wine), nor to extract solids from liquids. It affects 15 
litres of liquid.
</description>
 </spell>

<spell name="Breath of Dhivu" level="30" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Soak</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<description>
Causes a cone of intensely cold air to emanate forward from the 
caster. The affected area is an equilateral sixty degree cone. 
Creatures within the cone take cold damage, which can be soaked 
with armour. The damage done is +30 (split) at point blank range, reduced 
by one point for each metre to the target. The effect is primarily 
achieved by means of a variety of ethereal ice.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Yavari's Spoon" level="10" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+20 Detects trace poisons</boost>
<description>
Find out whether water is safe to drink or not. Gives a basic 
yes or no. For purposes of short term drinking - trace poisons 
or other impurities will not be detected. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Eye of Ultramarine" level="30" convocation="odivshe">
<range>Far</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range far x 2</boost>
<boost>+30 Range far x 10</boost>
<boost>+60 Range far x 100</boost>
<description>
A spell to determine the location of the nearest body of water. 
It actually works by trying to summon a ethereal water, and 
noting where it comes from. The spell may attract the attention 
of water based elemental creatures.
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Sight of Teri" level="30" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Self</range>
	<area>Near</area>
	<duration>Concentration</duration>
	<boost>+15 Area is short (50m)</boost>
	<boost>+30 Area is medium (100m)</boost>
	<boost>+60 Area is far (200m)</boost>
	<description>
		Upon casting this spell, the Shek-Pvar is able to see through
		all natural darkness. She cannot see light, but perceives the
		world in shades of grey. The sight extends to the area of
		the spell.
	</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Curse of Balrin" level="90" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Near</range>
	<area>Near (15m radius)</area>
	<duration>Concentration</duration>
	<boost>+15 Range is short</boost>
	<boost>+30 Range is medium</boost>
	<boost>+60 Area is short (50m radius)</boost>
	<description>
		Summons ethereal water at the point specified, which covers
		an area determined by the limits of the spell, up to a height
		of three metres. The water remains in place while the Shek-Pvar
		concentrates on it. Once concentration is ceased, the water
		will collapse and flow as per normal water, though it evaporates
		with a half life of about a minute. Creatures caught in the
		ethereal water drown in about twice the time as normal.
	</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Evo's Sweat" level="90" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Near</range>
	<resist>Stamina</resist>
	<duration>Concentration</duration>
	<boost>+15 Range is short</boost>
	<boost>+30 Range is medium</boost>
	<description>
		Causes a target creature up to size six to begin loosing
		moisture, breaking out in a cold sweat. If affected, they
		must make a further stamina roll each minute, at a difficulty
		of 10 + 5/minute passed. Failure means one long term fatigue
		is gained. Once maximum fatigue is gained, they acrue wound
		levels until they die.
	</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Hewgon's Exodus" level="90" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Self</range>
	<duration>Concentration</duration>
	<boost>+60 The Shek-Pvar can cast spells from shadow form</boost>
	<description>
		The Shek-Pvar is able to move his spirit into his shadow, and
		detach his shadow from his body. The shadow can perceive the
		world, and move around at will, but cannot affect the real world.
		It can be affected by magic which affects Odivshe elementals.
		The Shek-Pvar knows where his body is, and on termination of
		the spell, will return to it. The shadow dies if the body dies.
		The shadow can only exist in darkness, or a shadowed area. It
		is always two dimensional, laid upon a surface.
	</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Figure of Aumos" level="120" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Self</range>
	<duration>Special (d20+10 days)</duration>
	<boost>+40 Clothing and equipment are affected</boost>
	<description>
		The caster changes into water, immediately behaving as normal
		water except that her 'body' will remain continguous. She is
		unconscious whilst in this form, and will reform when the
		spell's duration expires. The water will tend to float to the
		surface if it is in a large body of normal water, and remain
		near the shore. Clothing and equipment are not affected.
	</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Daenin's Eternal Font" level="160" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Short</range>
	<duration>Concentration</duration>
	<boost>+20 Range is Medium (100m)</boost>
	<boost>+40 Maximum flow is 50l a round</boost>
	<boost>+80 Water can be caused to 'rain' over 15m radius area</boost>
	<description>
		Creates pure, clean, cool, mundane water which flows from the
		caster's hands at a rate of ten litres a round all the time
		the spell is concentrated on. The rate of flow may be changed
		from a trickle up to maximum rate at any time.
	</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Aumos' Frozen Corpse" level="160" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Short</range>
	<duration>Momentary</duration>
	<resist>Stamina</resist>
	<boost>+20 Range is medium</boost>
	<boost>+40 Affect all targets within range</boost>
	<description>
		Chills a target up to size five to 4 degrees celcius if they
		fail their resistence roll. This will generally have the effect
		of killing a living creature.
	</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Orb of Aumos" level="200" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Medium</range>
	<area>Near</area>
	<duration>Momentary</duration>
	<resist>Soak</resist>
	<boost>+25 Range is far (200m)</boost>
	<boost>+50 Area is short (50m)</boost>
	<description>
		Creates a small orb of ethereal ice which can be thrown at a
		target, using the Shek-Pvar's through skill at +20. If it
		touches a target, it immediatly causes +50 cold damage, ignoring
		any metal armour. Any metal it touches becomes brittle, and
		will shatter if stressed. For each wound level caused, the
		target also suffers fatigue. Other creatures within 15m of the
		initial target suffer +30 damage for the orb's effects. Damage
		is also suffered each following round, though it is reduced by
		10 each round.
	</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Daenin's Icy Doom" level="250" convocation="odivshe">
	<range>Medium</range>
	<area>Near (15m radius)</area>
	<resist>Stamina</resist>
	<duration>Momentary</duration>
	<boost>+25 Range is far (200m)</boost>
	<boost>+50 Area is short</boost>
	<description>
		Connects the affected area to the essence of Odivshe for a short
		time, sucking all heat out of anything touched. Water will freeze
		solid, and living creatures will immediately die if they fail
		their stamina resistence roll. The ground and air will be
		extremely cold until it warms naturally, and all which remain
		in the area afterwards will suffer +30 damage each round, which
		ignores armour. A hot summers day will warm the area in an hour.
		During winter, it may take several hours.
	</description>
</spell>



</grimoire>
