<grimoire convocation="Odivshe">
<preface>
Odivshe
Odivshe is the magic of slow, cool darkness, of water and ice, the opposite of fire and action. Odivshe magi study and work their spells on water and shadow, ice and cold. They are sometimes called the wizards of gloom.
As well as these mundane elements, the Odivshe sometimes manipulate ethereal water. This "substance" takes a variety of forms, generally similar to ordinary water, but thinner, sometimes invisible. Often it is described as an "icy pallor that robs away the breath and drowns the very spirit with its dark, clinging, gloom". It takes about twice as long to drown in ethereal water, although this may be small comfort to those who have the experience. In general, etheral water is easier to walk/run through than mundane water (half air movement rates), and more difficult to swim in (double fatigue). The Odivshe use it because it is easier to manipulate than mundane water. Ethereal water effects ethereal creatures as mundane water affects mundane creatures. It will also quench etheral fire.

Secondary: Fyvrian or Savoryan
Tertiary: Jmorvi or Lyahvi
Diametric: Peleahn
Change

</preface>

<spell name="Azure Hand" level="10" method="change" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="I">5 + 5 effect </level>
<range>-1 effect / 5m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>A spell to gently reduce the temperature of an object. It works best on objects containing high proportions of water, and can cause minor discomfort to organic creatures. It is a good treatment for sunstroke, and can deaden pain. It causes one level of fatigue, and reduces wound penalties by one level. Target must make a soak roll of some amount as well, or maybe instead of fatigue loss.</description>
<notes>
Each level of effect causes one fatigue level per size of creature, so five levels are needed for each point of fatigue for a human sized (5) creature.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Bonal's Quenching" level="15" method="change" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="I"> 5 + 5 conc + 5 effect</level>
<range>-1 effect / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Changes the water in the target's body to make it more refreshing and capable of sustaining life longer. It gives a +5 bonus to resist dehydration while in effect.
</description>
<notes>
Each level of effect gives a +1 bonus.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Power of Ulmer" level="15" method="change" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="I">5 + 5 conc + 5 effect</level>
<range>-1 size / 5 m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Increases the buoyancy of an object, by an amount equivalent to its water content. Something with the equivalence of a human body can be affected up to size five, making it twice as buoyant, capable of even sleeping when floating, and doubling swimming speeds. Only half the amount of wood could be affected, and metal or rock could not be affected at all.
</description>
<notes>
Each point of effect affects one size point of target.
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Glamour of Fanon" level="30" method="change" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="III">5 + 20 effect + 5 effect</level>
<range>-1 / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Reduces the temperature of an inanimate object up to size 2, by 20 degrees celsius. The object will return to room temperature normally.
</description>
<notes>
Each level of spell effect reduces the temperature of an object. Each 5 point of extra effect will affect an object of size 2.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Mouth of Lathal" level="35" method="change" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="III">15 + 5 conc + 15 effect</level>
<range>-1 size / 5m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Enables the target to breathe water, though does also remove the ability to breathe air as well. Creatures up to size six can be affected.
</description>
<notes>
Each five levels of effect affect two size points of target creature. Add five levels to this spell to enable target to breathe both air and water.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Tarl's Crystals" level="35" method="shape" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="III">10 + 5 conc + 20 effect</level>
<range>-1 / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
An enchantment which enlarges snowflakes, raindrops, hailstones, or other precipitation over a wide area near the caster. Generally, the maximum effect is to combine 20 hailstones/raindrops into one. Every five metres from centre of the effect, one less drop is combined. Effects of this are left to GM discretion. The spell does not cause hail or rain in the first place.
</description>
<notes>
Each level of effect causes one raindrop to combine together.
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Chalsa's Sponge" level="25" method="shape" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="II">5 + 5 conc + 15 effect</level>
<range>-1 size / 5 m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
An enchantment which causes the target to retain moisture. The effect can be unpredictable. In most cases sponge reduces and/or prevents thirst, and prevents or inhibits the loss of bodily fluids such as sweat, tears and urine. The spell eliminates the need for water, but does not affect thirst, so it can be used to traverse a desert, but not comfortably. After a few days, the target becomes bloated with retained moisture; they are generally immobilised after five to seven days, and die in ten.
</description>
<notes></notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Shadow of Yanar" level="25" method="shape" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="II">10 + 5 conc + 10 effect</level>
<range>-1 / 1m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
Forms a sphere of darkness emanating from the point indicated by the caster. At its centre, the sphere gives -10 to all actions involving sight. The darkness is reduced towards the edges of the sphere, by one point per metre distance from the centre. If it is located on a living target, then they get a will roll to resist.
</description>
<notes>
Each point of spell effect increases the penalty by 1, though a creature cannot be at more than -10 penalty to actions - it just has the effect of increasing the size of the centre.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Tarl's Alchema" level="20" method="shape" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="II">5 + 15 effect</level>
<range>-1 litre / 1m</range>
<resist>Stamina + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>
A spell to separate discrete liquids from a mixture, causing them to form strata within the container. It cannot be used to break natural liquids into their components (e.g. water into hydrogen and oxygen, but ethanol could be purified from wine), nor to extract solids from liquids. It affects 15 litres of liquid.
</description>
<notes>
Each level of spell effect affects 1 litre of liquid.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Breath of Dhivu" level="30" method="shape" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="II">15 + 15 effect</level>
<range>-5 damage / 1m</range>
<resist>Soak + 1 / 1m</resist>
<description>
Causes a cone of intensely cold air to emanate forward from the caster. The affected area is an equilateral sixty degree cone. Creatures within the cone take cold damage, which can be soaked with armour. The damage done is +30 at point blank range, reduced by one point for each metre to the target. If the point of origin is not the caster, then damage done at point blank range is reduced by five per metre distant. The effect is primarily achieved by means of a variety of ethereal ice.
</description>
<notes>
Each point of effect does +2 damage.
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Yavari's Spoon" level="10" method="know" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="I">5 + 5 effect</level>
<range>-1 / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 10m</resist>
<description>
Find out whether water is safe to drink or not. Gives a basic yes or no, for purposes of short term drinking - trace poisons or other impurities will not be detected.
</description>
<notes>
Each 5 levels of effect find out a level of detail about the water - the first level is basic knowledge, the second level is more detailed (is the water safe to drink for months at a time), the third complete knowledge (is it a safe life time drinking source?).
</notes>
</spell>


<spell name="Eye of Ultramarine" level="25" method="summon" convocation="odivshe">
<level complex="II">15 + 10 effect</level>
<range>-1 / 1 km</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 100m</resist>
<description>
A spell to determine the location of the nearest body of water. It actually works by trying to summon a ethereal water, and noting where it comes from. The amount of water that can be detected is inversely proportional to the effect. An effect of 1 can detect 100t of water. Higher effects divide that amount by the effect level. The spell may attract the attention of water based elemental creatures.
</description>
<notes>
Just increase the level of effect to increase the range and sensitivity of the spell.
</notes>
</spell>
</grimoire>
