<grimoire>

<spell name="Zyrgin's Heat" level="15" method="shape" convocation="peleahn">
<level complex="I">5 + 5 conc + 5 effect</level>
<range>-1 effect / 5m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>When cast upon an existing fire, it increases its efficiency by 50%, adding this to the burning time. The spell will affect fires up to size 5.</description>
<notes>
Each level of effect will affect one size point of fire. Each doubling of the base spell level will increase efficiency by 50% (100% at 10, 150% at 20 etc).
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Sphere of Shanakar" level="15" method="summon" convocation="peleahn">
<level complex="I">5 + 5 conc + 5 effect</level>
<range>-1 effect / 1m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m; Soak</resist>
<description>
Summons a ball of etheral fire, which appears at the point specified. Placing it at a distance reduces the effect, and placing it on a sentient creature allows a will roll to resist the spell. Once summoned, the ethereal fire provides light and heat, though it only effects sentient creatures. If it is touched, it causes +5 fatigue damage.
</description>
<notes>
Each level of effect causes +1 damage.
</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Aidan's Hastening" level="25" method="shape" convocation="peleahn">
<level complex="II">10 + 5 conc + 10 effect</level>
<range>-1 size / 1m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>Hastens the actions of a creature, enabling them to move 50% quicker than normal. This grants a +12 bonus to initiative in combat, and +3 to attack, defence and damage rolls. However, fatigue rolls must be made every round of combat. The spell will affect a creature up to size 6.</description>
<notes>Every five levels of effect will affect 3 size points of a target. A base level of 20 would increase movement by 100%, initiative by +24 and other combat stats by +6. A base level of 40 would give a 150% bonus to movement, +36 to initiative and +9 to other combat stats.</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Skin of Lexesh" level="25" method="shape" convocation="peleahn">
<level complex="II">5 + 5 conc + 5 effect (size) + 10 effect (soak)</level>
<range>-1 soak / 3m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>Protects a target up to size 5 from the effects of mundane fire, granting it a +10 bonus to soak against heat.</description>
<notes>Each level of spell effect protects one size point of target. Each level of effect gives +1 soak bonus.</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Eyes of Niyar" level="30" method="know" convocation="peleahn">
<level complex="III">10 + 5 conc + 15 effect</level>
<range>-1 level / 1m</range>
<resist>Will + 1 / 5m</resist>
<description>An enchantment which causes the eyes of the target to perceive distinctions in heat instead of light. The subject perceives gradations in temperature as variations in colour. The enchanted eyes cannot see normally. The target gains a new perception (for purposes of vision) attribute of 3, though this cannot exceed the base perception of the target. This kind of infravision does not allow one to distinguish objects of similar temperature.</description>
<notes>Each five levels of effect grant an attribute score of one.</notes>
</spell>

<spell name="Orb of Zatara" level="30" method="summon" convocation="peleahn">
</spell>

</grimoire>