<grimoire convocation="Peleahn">

<spell name="Zyrgin's Heat" level="10" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Reach</range>
    <duration>Special</duration>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <boost>+10 Range near</boost>
    <boost>+20 Affect bonfire (size 12)</boost>
    <boost>+40 Affect housefire (size 20)</boost>
    <description>
        When cast upon an existing fire, it increases its efficiency
        by 50%, adding this to the burning time. The spell will affect
        fires up to size 5 (campfire).
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Sphere of Shanakar" level="10" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Touch</range>
    <resist>Will; Soak</resist>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <boost>+10 Range near</boost>
    <boost>+20 Does +10 damage</boost>
    <description>
        Summons a ball of ethereal fire, which appears at the point
        specified. Placing it on a sentient creature allows a will
        roll to resist the spell. Once summoned, the ethereal fire
        provides light and heat, though it only effects sentient
        creatures. If it is touched, it causes +5 fatigue damage.
        It has the brightness of a torch.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Caress of Pelena" level="10" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Touch</range>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <boost>+10 Range is reach</boost>
    <boost>+20 Range is near</boost>
    <description>
        Warms an item up to size 3 by a few degrees. Each round the
        spell is concentrated on, the object will approach human body
        temperature.
    </description>
</spell>


<spell name="Aidan's Hastening" level="30" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Touch</range>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Concentration></duration>
    <boost>+15 Range near</boost>
    <boost>+30 Size 12</boost>
    <boost>+60 Base +6 bonus, 100% faster</boost>
    <description>
        Hastens the actions of a creature, enabling them to move 50%
        quicker than normal. This also gives a base +3 bonus to attack,
        defence and damage, and four times this (+12) to initiative.
        However, fatigue rolls must be made every round of combat. The
        spell will affect a creature up to size 6.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Skin of Lexesh" level="30" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Self</range>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <boost>+15 Range touch</boost>
    <boost>+30 Affects size 12</boost>
    <boost>+60 Bonus is +15</boost>
    <description>
        Protects a target up to size 6 from the effects of fire,
        granting it a +10 bonus to soak against heat.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Awakening of Murazor" level="30" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Near</range>
    <resist>Stamina</resist>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+15 Range is short</boost>
    <boost>+60 Affects all targets in range</boost>
    <description>
        The target is forced to wakefulness as if from a bad dream.
        More powerful castings can affect all creatures in range.
        The target is awake, aware and flushed with energy, though
        this will only last a couple of rounds.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Eyes of Niyar" level="60" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Self</range>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <boost>+15 Range touch</boost>
    <boost>+30 Can tell apart objects of the same temperature</boost>
    <description>
        An enchantment which causes the eyes of the target to perceive
        distinctions in heat instead of light. The subject perceives
        gradations in temperature as variations in colour. The
        enchanted eyes cannot see normally. This kind of infravision
        does not allow one to distinguish objects of similar temperature.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Murazor's Bolt" level="60" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Near</range>
    <resist>Soak</resist>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <boost>+15 Range is short</boost>
    <boost>+30 Damage is +30</boost>
    <boost>+60 Range is medium</boost>
    <description>
        The spell causes a flame to appear in the caster's hand,
        which can then by thrown at a target as a bolt of fire.
        The flame can be held for as long as the spell is concentrated
        on, but ends when the bolt is thrown. If the bolt hits, then
        it does +20 damage to the target. The caster uses her throw
        skill, and the target may dodge. The flame is made of ethereal
        fire, and has an attack bonus of +6.
    </description>
</spell>


<spell name="Ariondh's Firedarts" level="60" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Near</range>
    <resist>Soak</resist>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+15 Range is short</boost>
    <boost>+30 6 darts</boost>
    <boost>+60 12 darts</boost>
    <description>
        Creates three darts of ethereal fire which shoot forth
        towards a single, or multiple, targets, hitting with the
        caster's throw skill at +6, doing +18 stun damage. Each
        target beyond the first gives a -3 penalty to all throw
        rolls. Against the same target, there is one dodge roll
        and one attack roll.
    </description>
</spell>


<spell name="Orb of Zatara" level="60" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Near</range>
    <resist>Soak</resist>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <boost>+15 Radius is 3m</boost>
    <boost>+30 Damage is +25</boost>
    <boost>+60 Range is short</boost>
    <description>
        Creates a small ball of fire in the caster's hand which may
        be thrown (using his throw skill at +6) at a target. On contact
        with a solid object, the ball explodes in a 1m radius ball
        of flames, causing +15 damage.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Fires of Nep" level="60" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Medium</range>
    <area>Short</area>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+15 Two dozen droplets</boost>
    <boost>+30 Range is far</boost>
    <boost>+60 Area is Medium</boost>
    <description>
        A ball of fire arcs away from the caster, exploding over the
        area designated. Flaming droplets rain down on the area
        beneath, igniting any combustable material they land on. The
        flare is as bright as daylight over the area, and there are
        about a dozen flaming droplets with land randomly over the
        area. If they hit someone, they will do +10 stun damage,
        but its unlikely unless the spell is cast over a large crowed.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Arc of Fiery Ribbons" level="90" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Near</range>
    <resist>Soak</resist>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+15 Range is short, attack is 50.</boost>
    <boost>+30 Damage is +40</boost>
    <description>
        Causes fiery tendrals to shoot from the caster's hands, over
        a sixty degree arc out to the range of the spell. Anyone caught
        by the flames suffers +30 damage. The flames hit with an attack
        of 40 (no roll), and can only be dodged. The defence gets a
        bonus equal to the range (e.g. +10 at 10m).
    </description>
</spell>


<spell name="Charadhi's Fever" level="90" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Reach</range>
    <resist>Stamina</resist>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+15 Range is near</boost>
    <boost>+30 Strength of fever is 45</boost>
    <boost>+60 Strength of fever is 50</boost>
    <description>
        The target of the spell becomes affected by a magical fever,
        which at first makes them restless and impatient. They will
        be forever pacing, running or otherwise being energetic. They
        will be unable to sleep properly. Each day, the target's body
        temperature will rise as if they suffer from a fever. The
        strength of the illness is 40, and has a time of Day/5. The
        effects of the illness are fever / fever / coma / coma / death.
        A creature up to size 9 can be affected.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Hornet Fire" level="90" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Short</range>
    <resist>Stamina 30</resist>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <boost>+15 12 hornets</boost>
    <boost>+30 Range is medium</boost>
    <boost>+60 24 hornets</boost>
    <description>
        Creates a swarm of burning motes which burn and sting those
        they are sent against. The number of hornets is initially 6,
        and can be sent against one target or split between many.
        Each round a stamina roll is made to ignore them. Failure
        means that the target suffers a penalty to all actions. The
        penalty is equal to 5 x number, to a maximum of -15.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Sea of Fire" level="90" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Medium</range>
    <area>Short</area>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+15 Area is medium</boost>
    <boost>+30 Can ignite a single material</boost>
    <boost>+60 Duration concentration, fire can be terminated</boost>
    <description>
        Ignites flammable material within range. A single area may
        be ignited, such as a field or wood. Anything easily flammable
        in the area will ignite. Clothing or equipment on sentients
        is protected by a will resist from the creature. Anyone caught
        in the blaze will tend to suffer from +10 to +20 stun damage
        each round (ignoring armour) from the flames, depending on the
        amount of flammable material.
    </description>
</spell>


<spell name="Pilum of Fire" level="120" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Short</range>
    <resist>Soak</resist>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+20 Range is medium</boost>
    <boost>+40 Bolt can be split into multiple bolts, splitting the damage as desired</boost>
    <boost>+80 Damage is +65</boost>
    <description>
        Causes a bolt of fire to form and strike at the target, using
        the caster's throw skill at +12. If it hits, the bolt does
        +50 fire damage to the target.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Passage of Ahnu" level="120" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Self</range>
    <duration>Special</duration>
    <boost>+20 Caster can choose to double or halve duration, decided before the duration is rolled</boost>
    <boost>+40 Caster can choose to double or halve duration, decided after it is rolled</boost>
    <boost>+80 Caster can choose duration, between 1 round and 60 hours</boost>
    <description>
        The spell causes the caster's body to immolate in ethereal
        fire within a round of caster the spell, leaving nothing but
        a thick black smoke. ONly the caster's body is affected. The
        smoke will drift on the wind until the spell terminates, at
        which point the caster will reform. She is unconscious for the
        during of the spell, and has no control over her movement.
        The spell lasts d20 + 10 hours.
    </description>
</spell>


<spell name="Fiend of Hazatai" level="160" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Short</range>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <resist>Soak</resist>
    <boost>+20 Range is medium</boost>
    <boost>+40 Damage is +60</boost>
    <boost>+80 Range is far</boost>
    <description>
        This spell creates a burning tower of ethereal fire, vaguely
        humanoid in shape. It can be moved around within range of the
        spell, being used to burn targets as desired. The fiend attacks
        with the caster's throw skill at +16, and does +50 damage,
        halving worn armour because of its tendency to totally envelop
        the target. It effectively has +20 soak and 5 body levels
        against water based attacks. It can be moved at 100m/round.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Doom of Zhatran" level="200" convocation="peleahn">
    <range>Medium</range>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <resist>Soak</resist>
    <boost>+25 Range is far</boost>
    <boost>+50 Fireball can explode at any point on its path</boost>
    <boost>
        +100 Fireball can explode at any point, and continues moving
        until it reaches the range of the spell, causing damage to
        all targets it passes over
    </boost>
    <description>
        Creates a small ball of fire which appears in the caster's
        hand, and which can then be thrown out to the range of the
        spell, using the caster's throw skill at +20. On hitting a
        solid target, it explodes over a 15m radius area, doing +70
        damage.
    </description>
</spell>

</grimoire>






