<grimoire convocation="Savorya">
<prelude>
Savorya is the magic of mind and spirit, perhaps the most esoteric of the
convocations of the Shek-Pvar.
Savoryans deal with aura and knowledge, with principles which, they at least
believe, stand above the other elements, and of the Shek-Pvar. A Savoryan's
is, probably, the greatest knowledge of psionics, and perhaps of Kelestia
itself.
It is not possible to read a person's deep thoughts with Savorya.
The aura of a person can be read. As can their emotions.
The aura of a person consists of (in increasing levels of detail):
	10+	Elemental nature.
	20+	Elemental affiliation (if magic using), or religion if priest.
	30+	Physical/mental wellbeing.
	40+	Law/Chaos.
	50+	Dark/Light.
	60+	Religion (even if not priest).

A person's emotions can be read in the following detail levels:
	10+	Single current active emotion (if any).
	20+	Single current active or passive emotion.
	30+	Target of emotion.
	40+	Conflicting emotions related to main emotion.
	50+	Other emotions currently in force.
	60+ Visual impressions.
</prelude>

<spell name="Alvid's Mote" level="10" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Range reach</boost>
<boost>+20 Range near</boost>
<description>
An enchantment that causes a bout of confusion in the target. The effect of
the confusion is to lower all skill rolls by -5 for the duration of the spell.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Perfection of Sif" level="10" convocation="savorya">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</durations>
<boost>+10 Range touch</boost>
<boost>+20 Bonus is +6</boost>
<boost>+40 Effects all three senses</boost>
<description>
An enchantment which increases the perception of the target, giving a +3
bonus to either eyesight, hearing or taste related skill rolls (combat skills
are unaffected though). After the spell is ended, the target suffers a
penalty equal to the bonus for a period equal to twice the time they were
under the effect of the spell.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Violet Eye" level="10" convocation="savorya">
<range>Self</range>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+20 One word answers possible</boost>
<boost>+40 Provides answer to a specific keyword</boost>
<description>
This spell allows the caster to ask a simple yes/no question. The question
must be on a subject close to the caster - it cannot involve knowledge that
cannot be found nearby. The caster can only use this spell, or one similar to
it, once a week. It takes d20*5 minutes before an answer is returned. Higher
castings of this spell provides an answer to a specific keyword or subject.
This gives less control over the answer, but can help if the caster does not
know what question to ask.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Aron's Thought" level="30" convocation="savorya">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Range near</boost>
<boost>+30 Range short</boost>
<boost>+60 Range medium</boost>
<description>
Places a thought into the target's mind, not exceeding five words in length.
The target is aware that the thought is external in origin.
</description>
</spell>.

<spell name="Galra's Enchantment" level="30" convocation="savorya">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range touch</boost>
<description>
A spell which increases the will power of the target, giving them a +1 to
their will. Once the spell ends, the target suffers a penalty equal to the
bonus for a duration equal to twice the time they were under the effect of
the spell.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Talesien's Eye" level="30" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Range reach</boost>
<boost>+30 Roll die + 20</boost>
<boost>+60 Roll die + 30</boost>
<description>
A spell by which the caster can determine the aural nature of a target. Roll
10 + a die to determine how much detail is learnt. See the aura detail chart
for information on what difficulties will give what information.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Usela's Perception" level="30" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Range reach</boost>
<boost>+30 Roll die + 20</boost>
<boost>+60 Roll die + 30</boost>
<description>
A spell which allows the caster to read the emotions of the target creature.
Roll 10 + d20 to determine how much detail is learnt. See the emotion detail
chart for information on what difficulties will give what information.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Ordeal of Frida" level="60" convocation="savorya">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+20 Range short</boost>
<description>
An enchantment which stimulates an existing phobia, mania or any psyche
complex in a victim. If successful, the victim's most acute psyche attribute
is stimulated; a victim with arachniphobia, for example, will see spiders
where none exist, or many spiders where only a few exist, and so on.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Wisdom of Usela" level="60" convocation="savorya">
<range>None</range>
<resist>None</resist>
<description>
This is a higher level version of Violet Eye, which allows single word
answers to questions. Otherwise it is the same.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Faroh's Touch" level="100" convocation="savorya">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Sleep</duration>
<boost>+50 Range short</boost>
<boost>+100 Shift passion by 10 points</boost>
<description>
This spell creates or weakens an emotion in the target, changing it by as
much as four points in either direction. No emotion can be taken beyond +/-
5. The change lasts until the target next sleeps.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Korbin's Exchange" level="100" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<boost>+25 Range near</boost>
<boost>+50 Affects 2 senses</boost>
<boost>+100 Affects all senses</boost>
<description>
An enchantment that permits the caster to experience the sensations of the
target. The caster declares a specific sense (eyesight, hearing, olfactory or
touch), and thereafter the caster experiences the target's sensations for
that sense. As long as the spell is maintained, the distance between target
and caster is irrelevant.
</description>
</spell>
</grimoire>
