<grimoire convocation="Savorya">

<preface>
<para>
Savorya is the magic of mind and spirit, perhaps the most esoteric of the
convocations of the Shek-Pvar.
</para>

<para>
Savoryans deal with aura and knowledge, with principles which, they at least
believe, stand above the other elements, and of the Shek-Pvar. A Savoryan's
is, probably, the greatest knowledge of psionics, and perhaps of Kelestia
itself.
</para>

<para>
It is not possible to read a person's deep thoughts with Savorya.
The aura of a person - which gives religious, moral and elemental
connections - may be read, as can emotions. The latter can give
clues to a person's surface thoughts, but spells to delve deeper
than this are unknown.
</para>

<para>
When a person's aura is read, a roll is made (determined by the spell)
and the following chart should be used to find what information was
revealed.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <title>Reading an aura</title>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="7.5cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Target</entry>
            <entry>Detail sensed</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>10</entry>
            <entry>
            The bloodline or basic nature of the target is known.
            Whether someone is Human, Sindarin, Faerie or an
            elemental or demonoic spirit is known.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>20</entry>
            <entry>
            Elemental and divine affinities, if any. Shek-Pvar who
            are attuned to an element will have an aura tainted by
            that element. Priests of a god are also bound to their
            god, and this affects their aura.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>30</entry>
            <entry>
            The physical and mental well being of the target is
            known. Roughly how exhausted, injured and hungry the
            target is can be determined, as well as their primary
            emotions.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>40</entry>
            <entry>
            Knowledge of a person's morals, in regard to whether
            they are good or evil is obtained.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>50</entry>
            <entry>
            If the target has any leanings towards Law or Chaos,
            then this can be determined.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>60</entry>
            <entry>
            The religion of the target, even if they are not a
            priest. Also given, is a general guide to how
            strongly they follow the ideals of their faith.
            </entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>
</table>
</para>


<para>
A person's emotions can be read in the following detail levels. In all
cases, all lower details are known as well as the highest attained.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <title>Reading emotions in a target</title>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="7.5cm"/>

    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Target</entry>
            <entry>Detail sensed</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>

    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>10</entry>
            <entry>
                The single strongest, most active, emotion of the
                target is known. Note that only active emotions are
                detected, so a religious fanatic who is relaxing and
                playing cards, will probably show an emotion about
                the game.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>20</entry>
            <entry>
                The strongest passion of the target is known,
                regardless of whether it is active or not. The
                target of the passion is not known (e.g. which
                religion a fanatic follows, only that the person is
                fanatical).
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>30</entry>
            <entry>
                The target of detected emotions and passions are
                known. So the religion of a fanatic could be
                determined.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>40</entry>
            <entry>
                Conflicting emotions related to main emotion are
                known.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>50</entry>
            <entry>
                All other emotions currently active are known.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>60</entry>
            <entry>
                Visual impressions.
            </entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>
</table>
</para>

<para>
Savorya elementals are spirits, generally appearing as a white,
faintly glowing mist. They have minimal affect on the physical
world, feeling like a soft breeze at most. They are unable to
pass through physical objects.
</para>

<para>
They may engage in a sort of
mental assualt, causing fatigue in the target. In this case,
they cause damage with their will, against the will of the
target, causing fatigue levels in the same way that a physical
attack causes wound or stun levels.
</para>

<para>
Savorya elmentals can perceive the physical world, regardless
of the level of illumination. They see emotions in the same
ense that magic (Neutral) elementals see auras. Their emotion
sense is d20 + rank * 5. They can also tell, to some extent,
the strength of a creature's mind.
</para>

</preface>

<spell name="Perception of the Mind" level="0" convocation="savorya">
    <range>Touch</range>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+25 Range is reach</boost>
    <boost>+50 Range is near</boost>
    <description>
        Detects the current emotions of the target, according
        to the emotion chart. Roll a d20 + 10 * (rank-1) to find the
        detail of emotions detected.
    </description>
</spell>


<spell name="Alvid's Mote" level="10" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Range reach</boost>
<boost>+20 Range near</boost>
<description>
An enchantment that causes a bout of confusion in the target. The effect of
the confusion is to lower all skill rolls by -5 for the duration of the spell.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Perfection of Sif" level="10" convocation="savorya">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Range touch</boost>
<boost>+20 Bonus is +6</boost>
<boost>+40 Effects all three senses</boost>
<description>
An enchantment which increases the perception of the target, giving a +3
bonus to either eyesight, hearing or taste related skill rolls (combat skills
are unaffected though). After the spell is ended, the target suffers a
penalty equal to the bonus for a period equal to twice the time they were
under the effect of the spell.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Violet Eye" level="10" convocation="savorya">
<range>Self</range>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+20 One word answers possible</boost>
<boost>+40 Provides answer to a specific keyword</boost>
<description>
This spell allows the caster to ask a simple yes/no question. The question
must be on a subject close to the caster - it cannot involve knowledge that
cannot be found nearby. The caster can only use this spell, or one similar to
it, once a week. It takes d20*5 minutes before an answer is returned. Higher
castings of this spell provides an answer to a specific keyword or subject.
This gives less control over the answer, but can help if the caster does not
know what question to ask.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Roanda's Glamour" level="10" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+10 Caster is immune to the glamour</boost>
<boost>+20 Can obscure whole sentences/ideas</boost>
<boost>+40 Can add one new idea to the work</boost>
<description>
An enchantment which can be placed on a written work, or other
information-bearing object, to apparently change its meaning. The
spell does not affect the object, but it adjusts the reader's
understanding. The caster is not immune to the effect.
Whenever someone tries to read the work, they get a will roll
opposed to the caster's own will. The caster does not have to
stay near the work once the spell is cast, but she does have to
concentrate on the spell. Glamour can rarely adjust more than
ten percent of the intrinsic meaning.
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Amil's Panic" level="10" convocation="savorya">
    <range>Touch</range>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+20 Range is reach</boost>
    <boost>+40 Range is near</boost>
    <description>
        Causes the target creature to suffer a sudden fear of the
        caster. They must make a bravery check against the caster's
        will, or flee in panic from the caster. The duration of the
        effects will generally be until the situation has calmed
        down. There must be a visible reason for the target to
        panic, though generally a loud voice is often enough.
    </description>
</spell>


<spell name="Rising Ire" level="10" convocation="savorya">
    <range>Touch</range>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Momentary</duration>
    <boost>+20 Range is reach</boost>
    <boost>+40 Range is near</boost>
    <description>
        A spell which causes the target to become furious at
        someone or something. A will check is needed, modified
        by suitable personality traits. There needs to be a reason
        for the fury - a spilt drink, an imagined insult, or not
        giving the target what they want.
    </description>
</spell>


<spell name="Truthsense" level="10" convocation="savorya">
    <range>Touch</range>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <boost>+20 Range is near</boost>
    <boost>+40 Bonus is +10</boost>
    <description>
        Allows the caster to have a better sense of whether the
        target is telling lies. A +5 bonus is gained to all
        perception guile checks the caster makes against the
        target.
    </description>
</spell>



<spell name="Aron's Thought" level="30" convocation="savorya">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Range near</boost>
<boost>+30 Range short</boost>
<boost>+60 Range medium</boost>
<description>
Places a thought into the target's mind, not exceeding five words in length.
The target is aware that the thought is external in origin.
</description>
</spell>.

<spell name="Galra's Enchantment" level="30" convocation="savorya">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range touch</boost>
<description>
A spell which increases the will power of the target, giving them a +1 to
their will. Once the spell ends, the target suffers a penalty equal to the
bonus for a duration equal to twice the time they were under the effect of
the spell.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Talesien's Eye" level="30" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Range reach</boost>
<boost>+30 Roll die + 20</boost>
<boost>+60 Roll die + 30</boost>
<description>
A spell by which the caster can determine the aural nature of a target. Roll
10 + a die to determine how much detail is learned. See the aura detail chart
for information on what difficulties will give what information.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Usela's Perception" level="30" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Range reach</boost>
<boost>+30 Roll die + 20</boost>
<boost>+60 Roll die + 30</boost>
<description>
A spell which allows the caster to read the emotions of the target creature.
Roll 10 + d20 to determine how much detail is learned. See the emotion detail
chart for information on what difficulties will give what information.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Pains of Worry" level="30" convocation="savorya">
    <range>Touch</range>
    <resist>Will</resist>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <boost>+15 Range is reach</boost>
    <boost>+30 Range is near</boost>
    <boost>+60 Passion gained is at +3</boost>
    <description>
        Places a painful emotion into the target, which nags and
        taunts at them while the spell is maintained. It is a fear
        of something unknown, a fear which cannot be named. The
        target gains a personality trait of 'fear of everything'
        at +2. Will checks at difficulty 20 are required in order
        for the target to initiate new endeavours.
    </description>
</spell>

<spell name="Amil's Agreement" level="60" convocation="savorya">
<range>Eye</range>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<resist>Will</resist>
<boost>+15 Bind target to a grudging agreement</boost>
<boost>+30 Bind target to an unwilling agreement</boost>
<boost>+60 Force agreement</boost>
<description>
Plants a suggestion in a person's mind to carry out some task.
The task must be simple in nature (e.g. deliver a message,
kill a person, guard me), and must be verbally described to
the target. For the base spell, the target must agree to the
task willingly - this spell is useful only for ensuring that
they don't go back on their word. A grudging agreement is
where the target would normally refuse, though out of belief
that they are being undepaid, rather than due to moral
or practical objections. Unwilling agreements are ones the
target would never agree to, but which don't go against the
target's core principles, or involve serious danger. A forced
agreement is one which is dangerous (though not suicidal), or
forces the target to, say, betray a close friend.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Loth's Key" level="60" convocation="savorya">
<time>8 hours</time>
<range>Touch</range>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+15 Caster can speak/write a translation</boost>
<boost>+30 Neither language nor script needs to be known</boost>
<description>
A spell which allows the caster to read documents written in a
language or script unknown to her. With the basic spell, the
caster must know either the language or the script.
The spell creates a special relationship between the caster
and a single page of the written work; and cannot be extended
to include other texts or readers. The caster is perceiving
the imprinted thoughts of the author, and this gets harder
with the age of the document. She must make a perception roll
of 15+ if the document is less than a month old, 20+ for up
to a year, and at a further +5 for each tenfold increase in
age of the work. If it was written by someone who didn't
understand what they were writing, translation may be impossible.
The caster cannot speak or write while performing the spell,
so any translations will have to be from memory.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Ordeal of Frida" level="60" convocation="savorya">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range short</boost>
<description>
An enchantment which stimulates an existing phobia, mania or any psyche
complex in a victim. If successful, the victim's most acute psyche attribute
is stimulated; a victim with arachniphobia, for example, will see spiders
where none exist, or many spiders where only a few exist, and so on.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Scroll of Pasalt" level="60" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+30 Duration becomes momentary</boost>
<description>
A spell which causes writing to appear magically on a scroll
or other written work held by the caster. The spell cannot
work on enchanted objects. The words exist for as long as the
caster concentrates.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Wisdom of Usela" level="60" convocation="savorya">
<range>None</range>
<resist>None</resist>
<description>
This is a higher level version of Violet Eye, which allows single word
answers to questions. Otherwise it is the same.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Enesin's Quill" level="90" convocation="savorya">
<time>1 hour</time>
<range>Touch</range>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<description>
An enchantment which improves the condition of a written work, 
raising its quality by one. Pen and ink are required. Each 
casting can affect one page of a work. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Faroh's Touch" level="90" convocation="savorya">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Sleep</duration>
<boost>+15 Range short</boost>
<boost>+60 Shift passion by 10 points</boost>
<description>
This spell creates or weakens an emotion in the target, changing it by as 
much as four points in either direction. No emotion can be taken beyond 
+/-5. The change lasts until the target next sleeps. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Korbin's Exchange" level="90" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<boost>+15 Range near</boost>
<boost>+30 Affects 2 senses</boost>
<boost>+60 Affects all senses</boost>
<description>
An enchantment that permits the caster to experience the sensations of the 
target. The caster declares a specific sense (eyesight, hearing, olfactory or 
touch), and thereafter the caster experiences the target's sensations for 
that sense. As long as the spell is maintained, the distance between target 
and caster is irrelevant. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Spirit Block" level="90" convocation="savorya">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+30 Caster can erase knowledge of his presence</boost>
<boost>+60 Caster may attempt to erase victim's memory in other regards</boost>
<description>
A spell to suppress the will of a victim touched by the caster, 
so that she will follow the caster's orders; it is normally used 
on animals or people. 
Spirit Block creates a bond between caster and his victim. He can 
read surface thoughts and emotions, direct her actions and ask 
questions. The victim will not volunteer information, so questions 
must be very direct and specific. Because of the bond, any harm 
which befalls either the caster or the victim is experienced by 
the other. So if one is cut, so is the other. If one dies, so 
does the other. The victim is aware of the spell, and what was 
asked of her. 
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Bolt of Mintora" level="120" convocation="savorya">
<range>Touch</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+15 Range is near</boost>
<boost>+30 Everyone within near can be affected</boost>
<boost>+60 Caster can choose who it affects, within near</boost>
<description>
This spell causes shock and confusion in the mind of the target. 
If the target fails to resist, then they cannot act for the rest 
of the round. From then on, they are at -10 penalty to physical 
actions, and at -50 to spell casting. At the end of each following 
round, they get a will roll at difficulty 20 to recover.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Jerila's Zone" level="120" convocation="savorya">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+15 The caster can move within the zone.</boost>
<boost>+30 Caster can release targets by touching them.</boost>
<boost>+60 The sphere can be moved, at a metre per round.</boost>
<description>
This spell creates confusion in the affected area. All creatures 
must make a will roll or suffer the effects of the spell. Those 
affected will tend to act randomly, if at all. The zone is centred 
on the caster, and if she moves, the spell is broken. If new targets 
come within the zone, they must make a will roll to avoid being 
affected. Once a creature as resisted, they do not need to roll again, 
even if they leave and re-enter the zone.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Arrow of Utern" level="160" convocation="savorya">
<range>Near</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+20 Range is short.</boost>
<boost>+40 Affects all within range.</boost>
<boost>+80 Caster can choose who within range is affected.</boost>
<description>
The target of this spell suffers powerful mental shock if they fail 
their will roll. The victim suffers +40 fatigue damage.
</description>
</spell>


<spell name="Veil of Iros" level="160" convocation="savorya">
<range>Short</range>
<resist>Perception</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+40 Spell may be placed on another target.</boost>
<boost>+80 Affected person may interact with others.</boost>
<description>
This spell is laid upon the caster, causing him to be ignored by 
those within range who fail their resistance roll. As long as the 
caster keeps a low profile, he will be ignored. If he does something 
which attracts attention, observers get another roll. Note that those 
outside the range of the spell are unaffected, so can possibly act 
to warn those nearby. More powerful castings of this spell may 
allow the caster to interact with others, causing them to treat the 
caster as another guard for instance.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Knife of Kasrith" level="200" convocation="savorya">
<range>Reach</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Momentary</duration>
<boost>+25 Range is near.</boost>
<boost>+50 Caster can choose which body functions are disabled.</boost>
<boost>+100 Duration is concentration, and caster can activate and 
deactivate body functions at will.</boost>
<description>
When cast on a target, Knife of Kasrith will sever the spirit and 
mind of the target. The target is not killed, but they no longer have 
conscious control over their body. Any automatic body functions will 
continue to function, such as breathing, and they can taste, see and 
hear normally. However, they cannot move, speak or cast spells.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Tongue of Bywan-Koh" level="200" convocation="savorya">
<range>Self</range>
<resist>Will</resist>
<duration>Concentration</duration>
<boost>+50 Caster can lay the spell on another.</boost>
<description>
This spell is cast upon the caster, and while it remains in effect, 
the caster can affect the mind of those he speaks to, forcing them 
to consider anything he says to be reasonable. When a conversation 
is first started with someone, then they get a will roll to resist. 
If the target's will is overcome, then guards will open doors for 
the caster, merchants will willingly hand over goods as gifts and 
so on. If suggestions are unreasonable (kill your lord, sign over 
all your property to my name), then further will checks, at a possible 
bonus, will be allowed.
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Mikaad's Ward" level="0" convocation="savorya">
<range>Special</range>
<duration>Special</duration>
<description>
This spell (which is not, actually, a ward) is used to protect 
a secret from being discovered through magical means. It can not 
prevent discovery using mundane methods. The rank of the spell is 
modified by how many people know the secret. If the number of people 
who know changes after the spell is cast, then the rank of the spell 
is changed to reflect this.

<table>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="0.75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="0.75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="0.75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="0.75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Persons:</entry>
            <entry>1</entry>
            <entry>2+</entry>
            <entry>4+</entry>
            <entry>8+</entry>
            <entry>16+</entry>
            <entry>32+</entry>
            <entry>64+</entry>
            <entry>128+</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>Rank:</entry>
            <entry>+1</entry>
            <entry>+0</entry>
            <entry>-1</entry>
            <entry>-2</entry>
            <entry>-3</entry>
            <entry>-4</entry>
            <entry>-5</entry>
            <entry>-</entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>
</table>

If 128 or more people know of the secret, then the spell is broken, 
and the caster is made aware of this fact. Likewise, if the effective 
rank of the ward drops to zero or less, then the spell is broken. The 
secret cannot be discovered by arcane means until the spell is removed, 
either with Survan's Key, or a Dispel at least two ranks higher. The 
latter must be cast on someone who knows the secret, and specifically 
against this spell.  
</description>
</spell>

<spell name="Survan's Key" level="0" convocation="savorya">
<range>Special</range>
<duration>Special</duration>
<boost>+50 The caster can leave the Mikaad's Ward in place. They 
are free to divine the hidden knowledge however. This does increase 
the number of people who know the secret.</boost>
<description>
This spell allows the caster to remove Mikaad's Ward on a named 
secret. If Survan's Key is higher rank than Mikaad's Ward, then 
the Ward is broken, and the caster can then divine the secret. The 
caster of the original Mikaad's Ward will know that their spell 
has been broken.
</description>
</spell>

</grimoire>
