<?xml version="1.0"?>


<article>
    <header>
        <title>Bestiary</title>
        <tagline>Yags 0.7</tagline>
    </header>
    
    
    <body>
        <sect1>
            <title>Bestiary</title>
        </sect1>
        
        
        <sect1>
            <title>What does it all mean?</title>
            
            <para>
                Meanings for some of the attributes.
            </para>
            
            <sect2>
                <title>Size</title>
                
                <para>
                    The size rating of a creature gives a rough indication
                    of how big it is. An average adult human is considered
                    to be size five - and very few adult humans will
                    differ from this norm.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    The smallest possible size is zero - about the size
                    of a robin or similar bird - something that fits
                    easily into one hand. Creatures any smaller are also
                    size zero, but are very rarely worth bothering about.
                    There is no upper limit on size, and scaling is non
                    linear.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    In game terms, a creature's size directly affects how
                    many body levels it has, and also affects some combat
                    statistics.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    Size ranges are classified according to the following
                    chart. The descriptive names simply give an indication
                    of the rough size of the beast.
                </para>
                
                <targetlist targetFirst="true" bold="true">
                    <targetLabel>Size</targetLabel>
                    <valueLabel>Description</valueLabel>
                    
                    <entry target="0" value="Diminutive">
                        About 10cm long or tall, diminutive creatures are
                        the smallest that can be comfortably handled in
                        Yags. Any creature smaller than Tiny is Diminutive,
                        so technically it covers mice and insects.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="1" value="Tiny">
                        A small cat or dog - about 30cm long or tall.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="2-3" value="Small">
                        Small creatures range from 60cm (sized 2) to 90cm
                        (size 3) in length or height. A large dog would be
                        size 3.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="4-6" value="Medium">
                        Medium creatures cover the range of adult humans,
                        from about 130cm tall (size 4) to 210cm tall
                        (size 6). A size 5 creature is about 170cm long
                        or tall. Bulk also affects this as much as height
                        or length.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="7-10" value="Large">
                        Large creatures are about as big as most things get,
                        with elephants, whales and dinosaurs being bigger
                        than this in the real world. Dimensions can range
                        from about 250cm to 5m in length or height.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="11-15" value="Huge">
                        Huge creatures are extremely rare, at least in the
                        real world, ranging from about 6m to 10m in length.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="16-21" value="Enormous">
                        Dimensions range from 11m to 16m in length.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="22-28" value="Gigantic">
                        Up to about 23m in length. The largest dinosaurs and
                        whales fit into this category.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="29-36" value="Colossal">
                        Up to about 31m in length.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="37+" value="Titanic">
                        Anything about 31m or longer is considered to be
                        Titanic in proportions. This is the largest size
                        category normally available.
                    </entry>
                </targetlist>

            </sect2>
        </sect1>

        <sect1>
            <title>Combat</title>

            <para>
                Beasts tend to have a wide variety of ways in which to
                defend themselves.
            </para>
            
            <sect2>
                <title>Multiple Attacks</title>
                
                <para>
                    It is normal in Yags for creatures to be only able
                    to make a single attack in a round. In most cases
                    this holds true, and all attacks are collapsed into
                    a single attack and damage roll. A wolf may attack
                    with its teeth and claws, but these are counted as
                    a single attack, directed at a single target.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    Some creatures may have several options open to them.
                    An eagle could bite someone annoying it. It could
                    also swoop down and rake with its claws. However, it
                    cannot do both at the same time.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    For some things though, this breaks down, especially
                    where fantasy beasts are concerned. A large dragon
                    could bite someone in front of them, knock others
                    down with its tail, and maybe stun those around it
                    with its wings. Subsuming all of these into a single
                    attack wouldn't work, and yet all should be possible
                    each round.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    To this end, some creatures are capable of attack
                    multiple creatures simultaneously. There are two
                    methods this can be done - area attacks, and
                    independent attacks. Independent attacks simply allow
                    the beast to attack two or more times with different
                    types of attack (a bite and a tail bash for instance).
                    Area attacks are a single attack which threatens
                    everyone in an area - a single tail swipe may knock
                    over several people if the beast is huge.
                </para>
                
                <sect3>
                    <title>Area attacks</title>
                    
                    <para>
                        An area attack is directed at a single area, and
                        any targets within that area are affected. Tail
                        swipes, tramples and pounce attacks are all
                        examples of possible area attacks from a large
                        creature. Generally, only huge creatures
                        or bigger can make an area attack.
                    </para>
                </sect3>
            </sect2>
            
        </sect1>
    
    </body>
    
</article>#ÿ
