<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/usr/share/web/xsl/yagsbook/html/yagsbook.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<article>
    <header>
        <title>Bestiary</title>
        <tagline>Yags 0.7</tagline>
        <author>
            <fullname>Samuel Penn</fullname>
            <email>sam@bifrost.demon.co.uk</email>
        </author>

        <cvsinfo>
            <version>$Revision: 1.4 $</version>
            <date>$Date: 2002-09-09 21:16:08 $</date>
        </cvsinfo>

        <license>
            <year>2002</year>
            <holder>Samuel Penn</holder>
            <url>http://www.bifrost.demon.co.uk/comp/yagsbook/fdl.html</url>
            <text>
                Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or
                modify this document under the terms of the GNU
                Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any
                later version published by the Free Software
                Foundation; with no invariant sections, with no
                Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover Texts.
                A copy of the license is included in the section
                entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
            </text>
        </license>

        <style name="combat"/>
    </header>


    <body>
        <sect1>
            <title>Bestiary</title>
            
            <para>
                A bestiary is a book describing beasts.
            </para>
        </sect1>


        <sect1>
            <title>Creature Statistics</title>
            
            <para>
                Meanings for some of the attributes.
            </para>

            <sect2>
                <title>Creature Type</title>
                
                <para>
                    The creature type defines the broad class of creature,
                    which gives some indication to its form and properties.
                </para>
                
                <termlist>
                    <entry term="Humanoid">
                        A human, or human like creature. A natural, bipedal
                        creature with some degree of sapience.
                    </entry>
                    
                    <entry term="Monster">
                        A generic term for an unnatural, possibly magical,
                        creature which does not fit into the natural
                        ecology.
                    </entry>
                    
                    <entry term="Animal">
                        Animals are non-sapient natural creatures.
                    </entry>
                    
                    <entry term="Construct">
                        Constructs are unliving, artificially created. They
                        do not require sleep or food (at least not in the
                        way it is normally needed by living creatures). They
                        are often mindless, and have no vital organs.
                    </entry>
                    
                    <entry term="Demon">
                        A demon is an outerplaner creature, magical in nature.
                    </entry>
                    
                    <entry term="Elemental">
                        Elementals are magical constructs inhabited by a
                        spirit, clothed in material such as rock, earth,
                        water or air. They have no need of food or sleep,
                        and have no vital organs. They do however have
                        free will. They suffer fatigue, but have twice the
                        normal number of wound and stun levels.
                    </entry>
                    
                    <entry term="Vermin"> 
                        Vermin are natural creatures with a tendency to
                        swarm. They are small and numerous.
                    </entry>
                    
                    <entry term="Plant">
                        Plant based creatures may be natural or magical,
                        and may have unique properties.
                    </entry>
                    
                    <entry term="Undead">
                        Undead are the walking dead. They have no vital
                        organs, and have no need of food or sleep. They
                        ignore fatigue, and have double the normal number
                        of wound and stun levels for their size.
                    </entry>
                    
                    <entry term="Ethereal">
                        Ethereals have no physical body, and cannot be
                        harmed by physical weapons. Likewise, they cannot
                        affect the physical world, but may be able to
                        strike at the spirit or soul of living creatures.
                    </entry>
                </termlist>
            </sect2>

            <sect2>
                <title>Size</title>

                <para>
                    The size rating of a creature gives a rough indication
                    of how big it is. An average adult human is considered
                    to be size five - and very few adult humans will
                    differ from this norm.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The smallest possible size is zero - about the size
                    of a robin or similar bird - something that fits
                    easily into one hand. Creatures any smaller are also
                    size zero, but are very rarely worth bothering about.
                    There is no upper limit on size, and scaling is non
                    linear.
                </para>

                <para>
                    In game terms, a creature's size directly affects how
                    many body levels it has, and also affects some combat
                    statistics.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Size ranges are classified according to the following
                    chart. The descriptive names simply give an indication
                    of the rough size of the beast.
                </para>

                <targetlist targetFirst="true" bold="true">
                    <targetLabel>Size</targetLabel>
                    <valueLabel>Description</valueLabel>
                    
                    <entry target="0" value="Diminutive">
                        About 10cm long or tall, diminutive creatures are
                        the smallest that can be comfortably handled in
                        Yags. Any creature smaller than Tiny is Diminutive,
                        so technically it covers mice and insects.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="1" value="Tiny">
                        A small cat or dog - about 30cm long or tall.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="2-3" value="Small">
                        Small creatures range from 60cm (sized 2) to 90cm
                        (size 3) in length or height. A large dog would be
                        size 3.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="4-6" value="Medium">
                        Medium creatures cover the range of adult humans,
                        from about 130cm tall (size 4) to 210cm tall
                        (size 6). A size 5 creature is about 170cm long
                        or tall. Bulk also affects this as much as height
                        or length.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="7-10" value="Large">
                        Large creatures are about as big as most things get,
                        with elephants, whales and dinosaurs being bigger
                        than this in the real world. Dimensions can range
                        from about 250cm to 5m in length or height.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="11-15" value="Huge">
                        Huge creatures are extremely rare, at least in the
                        real world, ranging from about 6m to 10m in length.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="16-21" value="Enormous">
                        Dimensions range from 11m to 16m in length.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="22-28" value="Gigantic">
                        Up to about 23m in length. The largest dinosaurs and
                        whales fit into this category.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="29-36" value="Colossal">
                        Up to about 31m in length.
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="37+" value="Titanic">
                        Anything about 31m or longer is considered to be
                        Titanic in proportions. This is the largest size
                        category normally available.
                    </entry>
                </targetlist>

            </sect2>
        </sect1>

        <sect1>
            <title>Combat</title>

            <para>
                Beasts tend to have a wide variety of ways in which to
                defend themselves.
            </para>

            <sect2>
                <title>Combat Modifiers</title>

                <para>
                    Creatures of a certain size will tend to have similar
                    modifiers to their basic combat scores - things such
                    as initiative, attack and defence. Damage is never
                    modified by size, since it comes straight off strength,
                    which goes up with size anyway.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Large creatures get bonuses in combat simply because
                    their attacks have greater reach, are harder to parry,
                    and are dangerous enough to keep attackers at bay.
                </para>

                <table>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Size</entry>
                            <entry>Initiative</entry>
                            <entry>Attack</entry>
                            <entry>Defence</entry>
                            <entry>Damage</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Diminutive</entry>
                            <entry>-15</entry>
                            <entry>-9</entry>
                            <entry>-5</entry>
                            <entry>-10</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Tiny</entry>
                            <entry>-10</entry>
                            <entry>-6</entry>
                            <entry>-2</entry>
                            <entry>-5</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Small</entry>
                            <entry>-5</entry>
                            <entry>-3</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Medium</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Large</entry>
                            <entry>+2</entry>
                            <entry>+3</entry>
                            <entry>+2</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Huge</entry>
                            <entry>+5</entry>
                            <entry>+6</entry>
                            <entry>+4</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Enormous</entry>
                            <entry>+10</entry>
                            <entry>+9</entry>
                            <entry>+6</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Gigantic</entry>
                            <entry>+15</entry>
                            <entry>+12</entry>
                            <entry>+8</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Colossal</entry>
                            <entry>+20</entry>
                            <entry>+15</entry>
                            <entry>+10</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Titanic</entry>
                            <entry>+25</entry>
                            <entry>+18</entry>
                            <entry>+12</entry>
                            <entry>+0</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
		</table>
            </sect2>

            <sect2>
                <title>Base Soak</title>
                
                <para>
                    By default, all medium sized creatures have a
                    basic soak of 12. Larger or smaller creatures
                    can change this however. A huge creature may not
                    be totally immune to damage from normal sized
                    weapons, but they may be too small to do anything
                    other than superficial cuts, which aren't worth
                    even a single wound level.
                </para>
                
                <targetlist bold="true">
                    <targetLabel>Soak</targetLabel>
                    <valueLabel>Creature Size</valueLabel>

                    <entry target="3" value="Diminutive"/>
                    <entry target="6" value="Tiny"/>
                    <entry target="9" value="Small"/>
                    <entry target="12" value="Medium"/>
                    <entry target="15" value="Large"/>
                    <entry target="20" value="Huge"/>
                    <entry target="25" value="Enormous"/>
                    <entry target="30" value="Gigantic"/>
                    <entry target="40" value="Colossal"/>
                    <entry target="50" value="Titanic"/>
                </targetlist>
                
                <para>
                    Large creatures will tend to have strengths of
                    a suitable value in order to injure creatrures
                    of a similar size.
                </para>
            </sect2>

            <sect2>
                <title>Natural Armour</title>

                <para>
                    Some creatures, especially the larger ones,
                    will have natural armour which helps them soak
                    damage. Natural armour ranges in protection
                    from +0 up to +9, though a creature may have
                    more than one type of natural armour, all of
                    which will stack. For example, a bear has both
                    thick fur and a tough hide.
                </para>

                <targetlist targetFirst="true" bold="true">
                    <title>Examples of Hide Armour</title>

                    <targetLabel>Soak</targetLabel>
                    <valueLabel>Description</valueLabel>

                    <entry target="0-2" value="Thin">
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="3-5" value="Medium">
                    </entry>
                    <entry target="6-7" value="Thick">
                    </entry>
                    <entry target="8-9" value="Very thick">
                    </entry>
                </targetlist>

                <targetlist targetFirst="true" bold="true">
                    <title>Examples of Fur Armour</title>

                    <targetLabel>Soak</targetLabel>
                    <valueLabel>Description</valueLabel>

                    <entry target="0-2" value="Thin">
                    </entry>

                    <entry target="3-5" value="Medium">
                    </entry>
                    <entry target="6-7" value="Thick">
                    </entry>
                    <entry target="8-9" value="Very thick">
                    </entry>
                </targetlist>

            </sect2>
            
            <sect2>
                <title>Multiple Attacks</title>

                <para>
                    It is normal in Yags for creatures to be only able
                    to make a single attack in a round. In most cases
                    this holds true, and all attacks are collapsed into
                    a single attack and damage roll. A wolf may attack
                    with its teeth and claws, but these are counted as
                    a single attack, directed at a single target.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Some creatures may have several options open to them.
                    An eagle could bite someone annoying it. It could
                    also swoop down and rake with its claws. However, it
                    cannot do both at the same time.
                </para>

                <para>
                    For some things though, this breaks down, especially
                    where fantasy beasts are concerned. A large dragon
                    could bite someone in front of them, knock others
                    down with its tail, and maybe stun those around it
                    with its wings. Subsuming all of these into a single
                    attack wouldn't work, and yet all should be possible
                    each round.
                </para>
                
                <para>
                    To this end, some creatures are capable of attack
                    multiple creatures simultaneously. There are two
                    methods this can be done - area attacks, and
                    independent attacks. Independent attacks simply allow
                    the beast to attack two or more times with different
                    types of attack (a bite and a tail bash for instance).
                    Area attacks are a single attack which threatens
                    everyone in an area - a single tail swipe may knock
                    over several people if the beast is huge.
                </para>
                
                <sect3>
                    <title>Area attacks</title>

                    <para>
                        An area attack is directed at a single area, and
                        any targets within that area are affected. Tail
                        swipes, tramples and pounce attacks are all
                        examples of possible area attacks from a large
                        creature. Generally, only huge creatures
                        or bigger can make an area attack.
                    </para>
                    
                    <para>
                        When a beast makes an area attack, all people
                        in the area are potential targets. The beast
                        makes a single attack roll, which everyone gets
                        to defend against. Those that succeed fend off,
                        or dodge, the attack. Anyone who is hit takes
                        damage - in each case a seperate damage roll
                        is made.
                    </para>
                </sect3>
            </sect2>

        </sect1>

    </body>
</article>

