<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://www.bifrost.demon.co.uk/xsl/fo/docbook.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<article>
<artheader>
    <title>H&#x00e2;rn Characters</title>
    <author>
        <firstname>Samuel</firstname>
        <surname>Penn</surname>
    </author>

    <referenceinfo>
        <copyright>
            <year>2001</year>
            <holder>Samuel Penn</holder>
        </copyright>
        <releaseinfo role="meta">$Revision: 1.5 $</releaseinfo>
    </referenceinfo>
    <revhistory>
        <revision>
            <revnumber>0.7</revnumber>
            <date>14th Oct 2001</date>
            <revremark>Yagsbook format</revremark>
        </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <subjectset>
        <subject>Yags H&#x00e2;rn</subject>
    </subjectset>
    <colourscheme>
        <colour>green</colour>
        <darkcolour>#aaffaa</darkcolour>
        <lightcolour>#ddffdd</lightcolour>
    </colourscheme>
</artheader>

<sect1><title>Creating a Character</title>

<para>
The first task that a player has is to create a character. The
first stage in the process is to come up with a concept for the
character - who they are, what they do, and where they come from.
The GM may want to give some guidelines on this, such as character's
coming from a particular place, or having a certain profession.
</para>

<para>
Once the player has a concept firmly in mind, it is time to start
solidifying that concept into the framework of the game. To do
this, there are three basic steps:
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
		Determine attributes.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		Choose advantages and disadvantages.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		Purchase skills.
	</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
The order in which these are performed is not important, though
the above order will be followed in the steps below.
</para>

<sect2><title>Choosing a Race</title>

<para>
It is possible to play a non-human character - Sindarin (elves)
or Khuzdul (dwarves) are the most common.
</para>

<para>
If this is desired, then the advantage/disadvantage packages for
these races should be perused before making any other decisions.
They are given at the end of the advantages section, since they
will not make much sense unless the preceding information has
been read.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Attributes</title>

<para>
The eight attributes listed in the Introduction make up the core
definition of a character within the rules. All skills, and therefore
any action the character attempts, are based on one of the attributes.
</para>

<sect3><title>Determine Attribute Scores</title>
<para>
The player has 48 points to spend on attributes. The cost of buying
attributes is on a pyramid progression - see the chart on this
page. A score of one costs one point, whereas a score of three
costs six points. An average character, with three in each of
the eight attributes, costs 48 points.
</para>

<para>
It is possible to spend more (or less) points on attributes. If
necessary, up to a further twenty points can be purchased as advantages.
It is also possible to not spend points, in which case this is
counted towards the character's disadvantages.
</para>

<para>
Advantages and disadvantages are explained in the next section.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>


<sect2><title>Sunsign</title>

<para>
In Harn, the date of a character's birth can have a real affect
on their life. This should be rolled randomly, before the rest
of character generation proceeds.
</para>

<para>
Tuzyn Reckoning (TR) has a 12 month lunar year, and each month
has 30 days. Roll d12 to generate the month the character was
born, then a d6 followed by a d10 (d6, 1-2 = +0 to d10 roll, 3-4
= +10, 4-6 = +20) to generate the day of the month.
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>



<sect1><title>Advantages and Disadvantages</title>

<para>
Advantages are things that give a character an edge over others
in the world. Each type of advantage has a point cost, and a character
can take up to twenty points worth of advantages, though they
can take less if desired.
</para>

<para>
The majority of people within the world will have significantly
less than twenty points, maybe only three or four for typical
farmers in the field.
</para>

<para>
Disadvantages work against a character, and have a negative cost.
The total value of advantages and disadvantages taken must total
zero or less. You can buy more disadvantages than you have advantages,
but no benefit is gained from doing so (other than possibly making
for a more interesting character).
</para>

<para>
The different types of advantages and disadvantages are as follows.
</para>

<sect2><title>Attributes</title>

<para>
Spending more than the normal 48 points on attributes counts as
an advantage equal in value to the extra points.
</para>

<para>
Spending less than the normal 48 points is considered a
disadvantage equal to the shortfall.
</para>

<para>
Many characters will have about five points of advantages spent
on attributes. More than ten is unusual.
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Appearance</title>
<para>
A character's appearance ranges from -6 to +6, and costs 1 point
per level. Its level adds to rolls for social skills when dealing
with members of the opposite sex.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Edges and Flaws</title>
<para>
These modify one or more skills in a given situation. No more
than one edge or flaw can apply in a given situation (though a
single edge, and a single flaw, can combine). If more than one
are applicable, then take whichever has the biggest effect.
</para>

<para>
All edges and flaws are bought on a level from one to six.
</para>

<sect3><title>Edges</title>
<para>
Edges modify a skill under certain circumstances. For example,
the absolute direction edge will give a bonus to survival or area
lore rolls, but only when the character is trying to find their
way.
</para>

<para>
Edges range in level from one to six, and give a bonus to skill
rolls equal to their level. The cost of an edge is different from
its level. Costs are listed as +x/y levels, e.g. +1/2 levels.
</para>

<para>
Only one edge can ever apply to any given roll.
</para>

<para>
<import-advantages href="options/edges-and-flaws.xml" type="edge">
	<genre>Common</genre>
</import-advantages>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Flaws</title>
<para>
Flaws, similar to edges, give modifiers to skills under certain
situations. Unlike edges however, they are detrimental. Further,
if the die roll is equal to or less than the value of the flaw,
the attempt is an automatic failure (or at least, only a partial
success).
</para>

<para>
If more than one flaw applies to a given roll, then only the worst
one will have affect.
</para>

<para>
<import-advantages href="options/edges-and-flaws.xml" type="flaw">
	<genre>Common</genre>
</import-advantages>
</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>


<sect2><title>Generic Advantages</title>

<para>
These cover options which can be either advantages or disadvantages,
or which affect the starting state of the character.
</para>

<sect3><title>Background</title>

<sect4><title>Social Class</title>
<para>
A character is assumed to be a freeman (ceorl) unless this advantage
is taken. The main effect of social rank within the game is to
determine the  weregild of the character. A person's weregild
is a measure of how much their oath is worth in a court of law.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Wealth</title>
<para>
The starting wealth of a character is determined from their social
class. A person has an amount of money put aside equal to one
twentieth their weregild.
</para>

<para>
A character may start with more than the normal wealth. Each point
of advantage (up to a maximum of 5) doubles the starting money
of a character.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Exceptional Training</title>
<para>
The character had an exceptionally active life, and learnt far
more than their peers. For every point of advantage, they may
start the game with two extra points of skills (explained later).
Such points may be spent during the character's adulthood, and
do not add to the character's age.
</para>
</sect4>


<sect4><title>Reputation</title>
<para>
The reputation of a character can greatly affect how other people
react to them. Reputations can be good or bad, and are respectively
considered to be an advantage or a disadvantage.
</para>

<para>
The level of the reputation gives a bonus to people's intelligence
- area lore ability as if it were a passion, to see if they recognise
you. Other modifiers may be used, as decided by the GM. A reputation
must have been gained for some reason, so the player and GM should
decide how the character got his reputation.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Duty</title>
<para>
A duty is an obligation to a cause, organisation or person. It
can take up much of your time, and you may welcome it, or resent
it, but either way, when it calls, you must do your upmost to
fulfil it.
</para>

<para>
A duty is always a disadvantage. The base cost depends on how
regularly you will be called on to fulfil your obligations. Each
season, the GM will roll 2d10 against the chance given in the
duty table. If you are called up to serve a duty, then the amount
of time it takes is variable, probably of a few weeks, but could
be anything from a day, to a season.
</para>

<para>
The cost of the duty is multiplied by how much danger is generally
involved in carrying out the duty. If you have a duty to serve
as judge in a court of law occasionally, then the risk is minimal.
If you have a duty to protect a town, which is often raided by
giants and dragons, then it could be considered to be perilous.
A fyrd duty to a lord would be a common duty, with moderate risk,
for a cost of -6.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Allies and Enemies</title>
<para>
You can begin the game with a powerful NPC as either a friend
or enemy. An ally is considered to be an advantage, whereas an
enemy is a disadvantage.
</para>

<para>
The base cost depends on how frequently the enemy turns up. Each
adventure, the GM rolls two dice, and if the target number is
met, then the given enemy will be around to make your life more
interesting. Likewise, if you try to call on an ally for help,
then the chance of them helping is found in a similar way.
</para>

<para>
It should be noted that a powerful enemy is probably going to
send capable henchmen to deal with you pretty rapidly. If they
catch you, they'll probably kill you without too much difficulty,
so taking such an enemy will mean that you will be on the run
for a long time, until you are able to deal with the threat.
A very powerful enemy or ally who turns up most of the time will
not normally be possible, since the cost exceeds the 20 point
limit for characters.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Luck</title>
<para>
A character's luck is a measure of how lucky they are. Most people
have a luck of zero, which represents being neither particularly
lucky nor unlucky. Lucky characters possibly have the favour of
a god, or other power, who is looking out for them.
</para>

<para>
Luck can be gained by taking part in major religious ceremonies.
When checking for luck in a situation, roll 1d20, add the character's
current luck, and compare against the following difficulties.
</para>

<para>
    Target    Chance
    5    Very likely. Event is almost certain to occur.
    10    Likely. About 50% chance of event occurring to character's
benefit.
    15    Unlikely. Event probably won't occur, but there is a
chance, and it's not too improbable.
    20    Highly unlikely. It would be very rare for the event
to occur.
    25    Improbable. Character would have to be extremely lucky
for this to happen. The sort of event which is talked about for
ages.
    30    Highly improbable. So improbable, that if it does occur,
it smacks of divine intervention of some kind.
</para>

<para>
Luck (+1 / level): This can be taken up to five times, to give
the character a +5 luck. Each point of luck gives a +1 bonus on
luck rolls. At any time, a luck point can be spent to give a one
time immediate effect to get the character out of a sticky situation.
The effect is up to the GM, but examples would be that a fatal
blow leaves the character wounded and unconscious, a fumble is
turned into a simple failure, or a failure into success.
Luck is bestowed by the gods, so only characters who are part
of a religion can have luck points.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Other Advantages</title>

<para>
<import-advantages href="options/advantages.xml" type="advantage"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Other Disadvantages</title>

<para>
<import-advantages href="options/advantages.xml" type="disadvantage"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Passions</title>
<para>
Passions range in strength from +1 (a slight quirk) to +5 (controls
your life). Passions of level +1 or +2 cost nothing, and may be
taken freely to round out the character. Passions of +3 or higher
must be paid for as advantages or disadvantages.
</para>

<para>
Most passions are considered disadvantages, since they restrict
how a character behaves. There are three broad groups of passions
- minor, lesser and greater, which are based on how much effect
the passion will have on the character's actions. Greater passions
are worth a lot more than minor passions.
</para>

<sect3><title>Minor Passions (Disadvantages)</title>
<para>
Minor passions are worth one, two or four points, depending on
whether they are +3, +4 or +5 levels.
</para>

<para>
Cruel: Character delights in the suffering of others.
Curiosity: Character's curiosity often gets them into trouble.
Love: Character has a strong love for another person, and they
want to be with them, and make them happy.
Meddler: Character enjoys meddling in the affairs of others.
Personal hatred: Character has a strong hatred for a single person.
Rare phobia: Character has a fear of some relatively rare thing,
such as spiders, enclosed spaces or heights.
Sensitive: Character is overly sensitive about some subject, be
it suffering, abuse, foul language or whatever.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Lesser Passions (Advantages)</title>
<para>
Lesser passions are worth two, four or eight points, depending
on whether they are +3, +4 or +5.
</para>

<para>
Brave: Character is brave, possibly foolhardy.
Unfazable: Character never acts surprised, and takes everything
in her stride. It doesn't mean that she's brave, she just always
seem to do everything (even running away) with style.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Lesser Passions (Disadvantages)</title>
<para>
Coward: Favours personal safety over honour.
Egotist: Character is a self centred, selfish bastard.
Hatred: Has a strong dislike for a given group of people, and
will neither trust nor befriend them.
Impulsive: Character acts first, think later.
Intolerant: Looks down on those who behave or look differently
to the character.
Loyalty: Has sworn his loyalty to another person, or a cause.
It is a two way affair, so they may loose his loyalty if they
act wrongly.
Lustful: Character has a strong desire for sex, simply for the
physical pleasure it gives.
Manic: Character is full of boundless energy, cheerfulness and
enthusiasm. However controlling the enthusiasm usefully can be
a problem.
Overconfidence: Character is overconfident.
Paranoid: Trust no one.
Uncommon phobia: Character has an irrational fear of relatively
uncommon things, such as music, loud noises, death or blood.
Violent: Character is prone to resorting to physical violence
if they don't get their own way, are insulted or otherwise upset.
Weakness: Character has a weakness for something such as alcohol,
money or women. People may frown upon his activities, but only
for the amount of time they spend pursuing them, not for what
they are.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Greater Passions (Disadvantages)</title>
<para>
Greater passions are worth three, six or twelve points, depending
on whether they are +3, +4 or +5.
</para>

<para>
Common phobia: Character has a phobia of a common thing, such
as the opposite sex, the open air or darkness.
Death wish: Character no longer has a reason for living, and seeks
only to end his life in some suitably heroic way.
Depression: Character lacks energy and enthusiasm, and easily
gives up if the going gets tough.
Deviant: Character has a craving for something most people consider
unhealthy - illicit drugs, sadism or deviant sexual practises.
If anyone found out, at best she'd loose any reputation she might
of had.
Driving goal: Character has a mission in life which will not be
easy to accomplish.
Fanatic: Character is fanatically loyal to a person or a cause.
Unlike loyalty, his devotion cannot be shaken, whatever the focus
of his passion does.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Sindarin Advantages</title>
<para>
The following advantages are available only to Sindarin characters.
Mostly, these allow Sindarin to be good at the things they are
famed for cheaply.
</para>

<sect3><title>Standard Sindarin Advantages</title>
<para>
These advantages are common to all Sindarin, and are gained free
as part of the Sindarin package.
</para>

<para>
<advantage name="Immortal" type="advantage">
	<description>
	Sindarin are immortal. They can be killed, but will
	not die of old age. A Sindarin will appear to reach adulthood
	(late teens, in human terms) after about fifty years. After about
	two hundred years they will appear to be about 30, at which point
	they stop aging.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Immunity to disease" type="advantage">
	<description>
	Sindarin are immune to disease. No normal disease may affect them.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Hardy convalescence" type="advantage">
	<description>
	All Sindarin have this at +6.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Need no sleep" type="advantage">
	<description>
	Sindarin do not need to sleep, at least not in
	the human sense of the word.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Night vision" type="advantage">
	<description>
	All Sindarin have this at +6.
	</description>
</advantage>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Standard Sindarin Disadvantages</title>
<para>
Sindarin are often seen as 'superior' to humans, but there is
a reason humans have displaced the Sindarin as the dominant race
on Harn, and this comes down to their immortality.
</para>

<para>
Their long lives give Sindarin are very different outlook on time.
To humans, Sindarin appear lazy, distracted and indecisive. This
is because Sindarin have no reason to hurry about anything.
</para>

<para>
<advantage name="Lazy" type="passion">
	<description>
	All Sindarin have the lazy passion at +3.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Distracted" type="disadvantage">
	<description>
	Sindarin are very different in outlook to humans, a fact brought
	on by their immortal lifespan. They have a great interest in the
	contemplation of nature, of philosophy and meditation. They do not
	take well to the sort of intensive study and training that humans
	seem so keep on.
	<br/>
	If a Sindarin spends more than a week in study or training, then
	they suffer a -1 penalty to the quality of the source. There is
	a further cumulative -1 for each successive week of study. A
	Sindarin will be at -4 penalty for her fifth week of study.
	<br/>
	If a break is taken from study, the penalty is reduced by one for
	every two weeks that pass without study. The Sindarin finds her
	mind drifting onto other things, and must spend time fulfilling
	her inner desires before continuing with such intensive study.
	</description>
</advantage>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Required Advantages</title>
<para>
All Sindarin are required to take (and to pay for - these are
not obtained for free) each of the following.
</para>

<para>
<advantage name="Appearance" type="advantage">
	<description>
	Sindarin must take a positive appearance.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Beautiful voice" type="advantage">
	<description>
	Sindarin must take at least one level of this advantage.
	</description>
</advantage>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Optional Sindarin Advantages</title>
<para>
<advantage name="Lithe" type="advantage">
	<cost points="+2"/>
	<description>
	Sindarin have, on average, a higher agility than humans.
	This advantage gives them +1 to their agility, up to a maximum
	of five. Can only be taken once.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Perceptive" type="advantage">
	<cost points="+2"/>
	<description>
	Sindarin have, on average, better senses than humans. This
	advantage gives them a +1 to their perception. Can only be
	taken once.
	</description>
</advantage>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Khuzdul Advantages</title>
<para>
The following advantages are available only to Khuzdul characters.
</para>

<sect3><title>Standard Khuzdul Advantages</title>
<para>
These advantages and disadvantages are held by every Khuzdul,
and are gained free.
</para>

<para>
<advantage name="Possessive" type="passion">
	<cost>
		<passion degree="negminor"/>
	</cost>
	<description>
	Khuzdul tend to be very possessive. Though not exactly
	greedy, they are very frugal and acquisitive. They have the
	possessive passion at +3.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Loyalty (clan)" type="passion">
	<cost>
		<passion degree="neglesser"/>
	</cost>
	<description>
	Khuzdul are extremely loyal to their clan, and have a loyalty
	of +4 towards the clan as a whole.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Code of Honour (dwarven)" type="disadvantage">
	<description>
	A Khuzdul will never forget a friend, or foe. They will defend
	their freedom and possessions to the death. A dwarf can be killed,
	but never conquered. This does not make them stupid. They will
	surrender and retreat, but it is never permanent.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Hatred (Gargun)" type="passion">
	<cost>
		<passion degree="neglesser"/>
	</cost>
	<description>
	After the actions of Lothrim the Foulspawner, dwarves have a
	strong hatred for all orcs. They have this passion at +3.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Distrust (Sindarin)" type="passion">
	<cost>
		<passion degree="neglesser"/>
	</cost>
	<description>
	The Khuzdul do not trust the Sindarin, and are still upset with
	them over their betrayel during the battles with Lothrim. They
	have this at +2.
	</description>
</advantage>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Required Advantages</title>
<para>
<advantage name="Brave" type="passion">
	<description>
	Dwarves must take this at least at +3.
	</description>
</advantage>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Required Disadvantages</title>
<para>
<advantage name="Stubborn" type="passion">
    <description>
    Dwarves must take this at least at +3.
    </description>
</advantage>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Optional Khuzdul Advantages</title>
<para>
<advantage name="Enduring" type="advantage">
	<cost points="+2"/>
	<description>
	Khuzdul tend to have a higher stamina than humans. This advantage
	gives +1 to stamina, up to a maximum of five.
	</description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Strong willed" type="advantage">
	<cost points="+2"/>
	<description>
	Khuzdul are very strong willed, and this advantage gives +1 to
	will, up to a maximum of five.
	</description>
</advantage>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1><title>Skills</title>

<para>
Skills are those abilities which a character develops throughout
their life, and tend to change a lot more regularly than attributes
do.
</para>

<para>
How good a character is at a skill is rated as a value from zero
upwards. A skill of four is acceptable for someone wanting to
make a living with the skill. Higher skills are possible, though
skills above six will be rare.
</para>

<para>
Initial character development is divided into three broad categories
- general skills, professional skills and adulthood. These should
be worked through in the order given below.
</para>

<para>
If the player has decided to play a non-human, then starting skills
are somewhat different. This section should be read, in order
to understand the ideas involved, and then the sections at the
end on each of the non-human races should be used.
</para>

<sect2><title>General Skills</title>
<para>
A general set of skills are learnt throughout the character's
childhood and adolescence. For the most part, they are skills
which are common to everyone.
</para>

<sect3><title>Talents</title>
<para>
Talents are skills which the majority of people have at least
some skill at, and even people with only zero skill are capable
of trying to use such skills without further penalty.
</para>

<para>
The talents are Athletics, Awareness, Brawl, Charm, Guile,
Sleight, Stealth and Throw.
</para>

<para>
The player has twenty-four points to spend on these skills. No
skill can be given a score above 4, and all must have a score
of at least one. Skill cost is per the pyramid point cost system
as used for attributes.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Common Knowledges</title>
<para>
A character will start with a reasonable knowledge of the world
they live in - though their 'world' may well be limited to a single
village. This knowledge is represented by the following three
starting skills, which default to the following scores.
</para>

<para>
<table>
	<colspec colwidth="5cm"/>
	<colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
	<tbody>
		<row><entry>Speak own language</entry><entry>4</entry></row>
		<row><entry>Area lore</entry><entry>2</entry></row>
		<row><entry>Folk lore</entry><entry>2</entry></row>
	</tbody>
</table>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Languages</title>
<para>
Language skills are treated on a scale from one to four, and are
not normally 'rolled' like other skills. Instead, the level of
skill gives a guide to how much of a conversation a character
can understand.
</para>

<para>
<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Level one</term>
		<listitem>
			The character can recognise the language and knows
			a few words, but cannot put sentences together.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Level two</term>
		<listitem>
			The character can understand and form basic sentences.
			The character can probably get by in the market or in an inn.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Level three</term>
		<listitem>
			The character has a good grasp of the language and
			can hold a decent conversation. They will obviously still be a
			foreigner however, and many unusual words will be beyond their
			understanding.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Level four</term>
		<listitem>
			The character is fluent in the language. If they are
			a foreigner, then they may still have an accent, but they will
			not have any problems communicating.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Level five and above</term>
		<listitem>
			If the character is a non-native speaker,
			then they can speak without an accent. This level and
			beyond gives detailed knowledge of different dialects
			and really obscure words, but is not of use in everyday
			conversation.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>


<sect4><title>Harnic Languages</title>
<para>
<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Harnic</term>
		<listitem>
			The language, in one dialect or another, spoken by the
			majority of Harnians.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Ivinian</term>
		<listitem>
			Spoken by the Ivinians.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>Orbaalese</term>
		<listitem>
			The language spoken in Orbaal, a mixture of Ivinian,
			Harnic and Jarinese. Most Ivinians speak their own language to
			each other.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Jarinese</term>
		<listitem>
			An almost dead language, formerly used by the early Jarin
			settlers to Harn. Modern dialects of Jarinese are spoken
			by some tribes and by some stubborn Jarin.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Sindarin</term>
		<listitem>
			Spoken by the Sindarin of Harn.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Khuzdul</term>
		<listitem>
			Spoken by the Khuzdul.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Gargun</term>
		<listitem>
			The gargun have their own language, and each sub-race
			has its own variation. A skill with each sub-language is required,
			though other gargun languages can be spoken at the average of
			both skills (round down).
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Harnic Scripts</title>
<para>
The following scripts are used on Harn for written languages.
A read/write skill is with a script, not with a spoken language.
</para>

<para>
<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Lakise</term>
		<listitem>
			The script brought to Harn by human settlers from Lythia.
			Lakise is the principal form of writing on Harn today and
			remains almost identical to that still used in western Lythia.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Runic</term>
		<listitem>
			The angular, stone-carving script, originated by the Khuzdul
			and still used by them. The Ivinians also use Runic. This script
			is common in Orbaal, and is known to many who have contact with
			the Khuzdul.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Selenian</term>
		<listitem>
			The aesthetic, cursive script of the Sindarin.
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Professional Skills</title>
<para>
After the character's general skills have been decided upon, the
next step is to decide what the character did during apprenticeship,
which takes the character up to the age of 16.
</para>

<para>
Apprenticeship provides the character with thirty points of skills
to put where they want, though no skill can be raised above four
at this stage.
</para>

<para>
If desired, these points can be placed on talents, as long as
those skills are core to the character concept.
</para>

<para>
The pre-generated characters given later give skills generally
associated with given professions, and can be used as a guide
for choosing sensible skill combinations. A full list of skills,
together with their descriptions is given at the end of this section,
but for a brief list of commonly available skills and their difficulties,
see the character sheet.
</para>

<para>
Once these skills have been assigned, the character is considered
to be an adult, and ready to enter play. However, if a more experienced
character is desired then it is possible to age a character beyond
16, gaining experience each further year.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Adulthood</title>
<para>
At the age of 16, a character is assumed to be an adult, and can
enter play. Many players may well feel that their character isn't
quite suited to the big outdoors quite yet, and will want to develop
them further.
</para>

<para>
For every year of extra development a character has before they
enter play, another two points may be spent on skills.
</para>

<para>
Characters may begin at any age the player wants above 16, but
characters which start above 35 years of age will have to make
aging rolls before the game begins (so could possibly die).
</para>

<para>
It is suggested that characters are no more than 35 years old,
for simple reasons of play balance.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1><title>Skill Descriptions</title>

<sect2><title>Talents</title>

<para>
The following skills are all talents, and are purchased at the
initial part of character development. For most people, they will
all start at a level of 2.
</para>

<para>
<skilllist>
	<skill name="Athletics" type="talent">
		<description>
			Gymnastic and acrobatic feats are covered by this skill,
			including climbing, running, jumping and keeping balance.
		</description>
		<examples>
			<example target="10">Climbing a tree (each 5m)</example>
			<example target="15">Climbing a broken cliff (each 5m)</example>
			<example target="20">Climbing an average cliff (each 5m)</example>
			<example target="15">Jumping onto a table</example>
			<example target="20">Jumping over a table</example>
			<example target="30">Jumping from tree to tree</example>
		</examples>
	</skill>

	<skill name="Awareness" type="talent">
		<description>
			A measure of general aptitude at noticing things going
			on around you. Awareness checks are made to notice ambushes,
			hear noises, or notice unusual events. Generally used with
			perception.
		</description>
		<examples>
			<example target="perception x stealth">
				See a hidden person
			</example>
			<example target="agility x stealth">
				Hear a sneaking person
			</example>
			<example target="10">Hear people talking through a door</example>
			<example target="20">Hear people talking through a wall</example>
			<example target="10">Hear someone walking on gravel</example>
			<example target="15">Hear someone walking on leaves</example>
			<example target="20">Hear someone walking on grass</example>
			<example target="1/10m">See someone with casual glance</example>
			<example target="1/25m">See someone with careful look</example>
			<example target="x2 range">Vision during dusk</example>
			<example target="x4 range">Vision under moonlight</example>
			<example target="x10 range">Vision under starlight</example>
		</examples>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Brawl" type="talent">
		<description>
			A general purpose combat skill covering dodging, punching
			and wrestling. This is covered in more detail in the combat
			section.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Charm" type="talent">
		<description>
			Your ability to be nice to people, or at least make them
			think that you are. Calming people down, inciting them to riot,
			or simply trying to impress them would use this skill. Generally
			used with charisma, though can be used with will for organising
			others.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Guile" type="talent">
		<description>
			The ability to use deceit and deception in social situations,
			and also to be able to counter the same. With this skill, you
			can lie convincingly with both words and body language, see
			through other people's lies and have a good idea as to their
			emotions.
			<br/>
			It is used with charisma to fool others, possibly intelligence
			to think of a good excuse when fast talking, and perception when
			detecting subterfuge in others.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Sleight" type="talent">
		<description>
			Sleight of hand, from filching items on a market stall,
			to picking someone's pockets. Can also be used for anything
			which requires a great deal of fine dexterity.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Stealth" type="talent">
		<description>
			Moving quietly, hiding, and generally not being seen
			or heard. Based on agility for moving quietly, or perception
			for finding somewhere to hide.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Throw" type="talent">
		<description>
			Throwing things at distance with a reasonable degree of
			accuracy. Based on perception.
		</description>
	</skill>
</skilllist>
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title>Knowledges</title>

<para>
<skilllist>
	<skill name="Arcane lore" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge of esoteric subjects, such as how magic
			works, the capability of magical artifacts and the like.
			Used mostly by members of the Guild of Arcane Lore.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Area lore" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge of an area, including geographical and political
			knowledge. Area lore is used when checking to see if a
			character has heard of a person, place or organisation.
			The area covered will be based from a given place, so a
			character may have several area lore skills. It is based on
			intelligence.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Chirurgury" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Performing major operations on a wounded person. This
			requires some specialist tools (though rarely more complicated
			than sharp knives and tongs). It is generally only known by the
			Society of Physicians.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Earthmaster Lore" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge of the legends and facts about the ancient
			Earthmasters. Both the sites and artifacts of the
			Earthmasters is covered by this knowledge.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="First aid" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Care and treatment of wounds to the extent of stopping
			bleeding, and preventing infection.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Faerie lore" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge of the Other World, of faeries, spirits
			and beasts of supernatural nature. Based on intelligence.
		</description>
	</skill>

	<skill name="Folk lore" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge of stories, myths and legends of a people.
			Generally, everyone has basic folk lore knowledge of
			their own culture.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Geneaalogy" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge of the family history of a given line, normally
			a noble house. Based on intelligence.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Herb lore" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge of herbs and their properties. Can be used
			to recognise, collect and prepare herbs and plants for
			use in remedies, poisons and potions. Based on intelligence.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="History" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge of the past, especially the last few hundred
			years. Based on intelligence.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Law" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge and understanding of the law, and how to apply
			it in a given situation. Based on intelligence.
		</description>
	</skill>

	<skill name="Religion" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			Knowledge of a religion, including its gods, customs
			and rituals. Based on intelligence.
		</description>
	</skill>

	<skill name="Speak own" type="knowledge">
		<description>
			The ability to speak your own language. This defaults
			to four.
		</description>
	</skill>
</skilllist>
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Communication Skills</title>

<para>
Etiquette: Knowledge of manners and how to behave in polite company.
Normally based on charisma to behave correctly, or intelligence
for a specific knowledge.
</para>

<para>
<skilllist>
	<skill name="Gambling" type="social">
		<description>
			Knowledge of how to play games of chance. Guile is often
			also useful for bluffing and guessing what other people are up
			to. A guile roll can give a one-fifth bonus to the gambling skill
			roll. Normally based on intelligence.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Lip reading" type="social">
		<description>
			The skill of reading lips. Each 10 rolled gives an
			equivalent point of language skill. There may be penalties
			for distance, or partial visibility.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Orating" type="social">
		<description>
			The ability to give speeches to inspire passions in people.
			This skill is based on charisma.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Play (instrument)" type="social">
		<description>
			The skill needed to play a musical instrument.
			There is a separate skill for each type of instrument.
			Possible types of instrument include string, percussion and wind.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Poetry" type="social">
		<description>
			The knowledge of poems, and the ability to improvise new
			poems. Reciting a poem is charisma based, inventing a new
			poem is intelligence based.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Sing" type="social">
		<description>
			The ability to sing well and in a way to entertain people.
			Includes knowledge of songs, and the ability to choose and
			improvise songs to fit an occasion. It is charisma based to
			sing well, intelligence based to choose or improvise a song.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Teach" type="social">
		<description>
			The ability to teach another person, and train them in
			the use of a skill. See the Campaign section for details
			on training.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Trade" type="social">
		<description>
			Covers a multitude of skills involved with trading, including
			bartering, and having some clue as to the value of goods.
		</description>
	</skill>
</skilllist>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Cult Skills</title>
<para>
Cult skills are only available to members of a given religion.
In theory, they can be learnt by anyone, but it is generally forbidden
to teach them outside of the cult.
</para>

<para>
<skilllist>
	<skill name="Berserker" type="cult">
		<cult>Agrik</cult>
		<description>
			This skill is only known by the clerics and fighting
			orders of Agrik. It mimics the advantage of the same name. It
			is based on stamina, and each 10 points rolled gives an equivalence
			to one level of berserker advantage.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Dream lore" type="cult">
		<cult>Siem</cult>
		<description>
			It is believed that dreams give glimpses of the inner
			mind of a person, and also of their future. The ability to
			understand dreams, and to garner useful knowledge from them is
			difficult to master. At worst though, someone with this skill
			can give impressive interpretations of a dream, if not entirely
			accurate. Based on intelligence, and taught by the priests of Siem.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Erotic arts" type="cult">
		<cult>Halea</cult>
		<description>
			The skill of giving (and taking) pleasure to someone.
			It is unique to the priestesses of Halea, and a few favoured
			followers (mainly members of the guild of courtesans). Normally
			base on dexterity.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Riddle lore" type="cult">
		<cult>Save-K'nor</cult>
		<description>
			This is the skill of solving riddles and puzzles, of
			understanding the links connecting broken facts. It is taught
			by the priests of Save-K'nor.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Torture" type="cult">
		<cult>Agrik</cult>
		<description>
			A skill honed to perfection by the followers of Agrik.
			This gives knowledge of the 'ten thousand ways of pain'.
			It includes knowledge of anatomy, psychology and implements of
			torture. Normally based on intelligence.
		</description>
	</skill>
</skilllist>
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Wilderness Skills</title>
<para>
<skilllist>
	<skill name="Boating" type="wilderness">
		<description>
			Being able to use a small oared boat. Based on intelligence
			for judging travel conditions, strength for speed or dexterity
			for fine navigation.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Falconry" type="wilderness">
		<description>
			The skill of training, caring for and hunting with falcons
			and similar birds of prey.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Hunting" type="wilderness">
		<description>
			The skill of training, caring for and hunting with hounds.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Ride" type="wilderness">
		<description>
			The ability to ride, normally a horse. A different skill
			is needed for different types of animals (horses and ponies
			would be the same skill, a griffon another skill). As well as 
			enabling you to remain mounted, it grants a bonus to combat
			skills when mounted.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Survival" type="wilderness">
		<description>
			Knowledge of how to get by in the wilderness, from finding
			food, trapping animals, and moving at speed across country.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Swim" type="wilderness">
		<description>
			The ability to move in water without drowning or panicking.
			Basically, a waterborne version of the athletics skill.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Track" type="wilderness">
		<description>
			The ability to find, identify and follow tracks left by
			animals and people. To follow a single person across soft terrain
			is moderate difficulty. Muddy terrain, or a large number of people
			or creatures makes it easier. An opposed tracking roll can be
			used to hide tracks.
		</description>
	</skill>
</skilllist>
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Professional Skills</title>
<para>
Professional skills will not often be learnt by player characters,
however they will be the most common skills known by people in
the world.
</para>
<para>
Each professional skill covers those tasks performed by someone
who makes their living. As well as the actual obvious use of the
skill, the skill can be used to evaluate the quality of raw materials
and finished goods, estimate prices and set up and run a business
based around the profession.
</para>

<para>
<skilllist>
	<skill name="Armoury" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			Making armour such as chain mail or ring mail, but also
			includes leather armour as well.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Beekeeping" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The keeping of bees, and the harvesting of honey from
			them.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Blacksmithing" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			Metal working, including needles, horseshoes, tools
			and so on. It can be used to make knives and daggers, but
			anything larger requires the weaponsmithing skill.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Bowyer" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The making of bows and arrows.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Brewing" type="professional">
		<description>
			Brewing beer and ale. This skill is generally the domain
			of the ale wives in small villages.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Candlemaking" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The making of candles.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Carpentry" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			Crafting items out of wood, from chairs to houses.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Clothier" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			Working with cloth, generally in the making of clothes.
			Can be used for making leather or padded armour if necessary,
			though this is not normally the domain of clothiers.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Cooking" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The preparing, preserving and cooking of food. Includes
			some knowledge of herbs.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Copicing" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The care and management of woodland. All manors will
			have someone skilled in this, and it is not uncommon for such
			a person to be a carpenter as well.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Dairying" type="professional">
		<description>
			The making of cheese and other dairy products. Includes
			caring for and milking cows.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Farming" type="professional">
		<description>
			The planting, caring for and harvesting of crops, the
			care and feeding of animals such as cows, sheep and chickens.
			The majority of people in rural areas will of course be farmers.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Glassworking" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The making of glassware, though this is a rare,
			and highly sought after, skill.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Handicraft" type="professional">
		<description>
			The making of baskets, embroidery and other similar
			village hand crafts not covered by other professional skills.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Jewelcraft" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The crafting of jewellery and gems. Covers artistic
			skill, as well as knowledge of the values of such items.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Masonry" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The building of houses, bridges and other constructions
			out of stone.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Milling" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			Running a mill, from the grinding of #our to the baking
			of the bread.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Mining" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			Covers being able to locate new mines, and to construct
			and work them safely.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Ostling" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The care and training of horses.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Potter" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			Pottery.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Shipwright" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			Ship building.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Tanning" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			Tanning.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Thatching" type="professional">
		<description>
			Thatching.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Weaponsmithing" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			The making of weapons, including spears, daggers,
			swords and axes. The making of bows and arrows is a different
			profession, which is covered by bowyer.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Weaving" type="professional">
		<guilded/>
		<description>
			A profession which includes weaving and spindling.
		</description>
	</skill>
</skilllist>
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Combat Skills</title>
<para>
See the combat chapter for a complete description of how these
skills are used. Generally, a skill in a particular weapon is
not necessary, just a style of fighting.
</para>

<para><skilllist>
	<skill name="Battle" type="combat">
		<description>
			Knowledge of tactics and strategy for planning, and fighting,
			large scale battles (anything with a dozen or more people a side).
			Combined with charisma, it is also used for leadership in battle.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Bow" type="combat">
		<description>
			Using either a shortbow or longbow.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Great weapon" type="combat">
		<description>
			Using a large weapon such as a great sword.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Single Weapon" type="combat">
		<description>
			Fighting with a single melee weapon and no shield.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Two handed weapon" type="combat">
		<description>
			Fighting with a two handed weapon such as a great sword.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Two weapons" type="combat">
		<description>
			Fighting with a weapon in each hand, such as with
			two swords for example.
		</description>
	</skill>
	
	<skill name="Weapon and shield" type="combat">
		<description>
			Fighting with a weapon and shield.
		</description>
	</skill>
</skilllist></para>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Sindarin Starting Skills</title>
<para>
Sindarin begin the game much older than human characters, generally
in the region of 50 to 150 years. Older Sindarin are possible,
but it's difficult to rationalise a Sindarin of this age being
of 'beginning character' capability.
</para>

<para>
The Sindarin character's age should be chosen by the player, and
it has no effect on the number of skill points gained. Sindarin
are a fickle lot, and how much a Sindarin has learnt is as much
a factor of their mood for the last few decades, as it is of their
age.
</para>

<para>
Sindarin Common Knowledges
    Speak Own (Sindarin)    4
    Read/Write Sindarin    4
    Speak other language    4
    Area lore (Evael)        3
    Folk lore (Sindarin)    3
Sindarin Talents
    Athletics    2    Guile        2
    Awareness    4    Sleight    2
    Brawl    2    Stealth    4
    Charm    2    Throw    2
Sindarin Beginning Skills
    Bow                3
    Dance            2
    Herb lore            2
    Poetry            3
    Sing                2
    Single weapon        3
    Survival            2
</para>

<para>
Sindarin player characters have a further 10 experience points
to place on skills on their choice. If they wish to buy further
experience with advantages, this is possible, though at double
normal cost. Sindarin characters start with a lot of skills, though
not much flexibility.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Khuzdul Starting Skills</title>
<para>
Khuzdul player characters will start the game somewhere between
70 and 100 years of age. Khuzdul live well into their third century,
sometimes longer, so this is considered to be a young adult.
</para>

<para>
Khuzdul Common Knowledges
    Speak Own (Khuzdul)    4
    Read/Write Khuzdul    4
    Speak other language    4
    Read/Write other        2
    Area lore            2
    Folk lore (Khuzdul)    3
    History (Khuzdul)    2

Khuzdul Talents
    Athletics    3    Guile        1
    Awareness    2    Sleight    2
    Brawl    3    Sneak    1
    Charm    1    Throw    2

Khuzdul Beginning Skills
    Trade                3
    Weapon and Shield    3
    Armourer            3
    Blacksmith            3
    Glassworking        3
    Jewelcraft            3
    Mining            5
    Weaponsmith        3
</para>

<para>
Characters get a further 10 experience points to spend on other
skills. There is no modification of experience for age. Khuzdul
characters may buy extra experience with advantages, at the normal
rates.
</para>
</sect1>

</article>
