<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/fo/yagsbook.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<article>
<header>
    <title>H&#x00e2;rn Religion</title>
    <tagline>Yags H&#x00e2;rn</tagline>
    <uri>yags/harn/religion</uri>
    <format>System</format>
    <author>    
        <firstname>Samuel</firstname>
        <surname>Penn</surname>
        <email>sam@bifrost.demon.co.uk</email>
    </author>
    
    <referenceinfo>
        <cvsversion>$Revision: 1.15 $</cvsversion>
        <cvsdate>$Date: 2002-05-06 12:44:44 $</cvsdate>
        <copyright>
            <year>2001</year>
            <holder>Samuel Penn</holder>
            <licence>Copyright</licence>
        </copyright>
    </referenceinfo>
    
    <displayscheme name="religion">
        <colour>blue</colour>
        <darkcolour>#aaaaff</darkcolour>
        <lightcolour>#ddddff</lightcolour>
    </displayscheme>
</header>

<sect1><title>Religion</title>
<para>
The gods of Harn are real, and the powers they grant to their
priests are just as real. Described here are rules for playing
priests in Harn using Yags. For a complete description of the
gods and their beliefs, see the HarnMaster Religion supplement.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<sect3><title>Levels of Knowledge</title>
<para>
There are three levels of knowledge which define what cult
invocations are taught to a trainee priest. Invocations of
level I are taught to all initiates by their mentor. Village
priests will have most, if not all, level I cult invocations,
of some level. In game terms, a priest character can begin
with knowledge of any level I invocation up to the normal
limit of skill.
</para>

<para>
Level II invocations are those which are revealed only to those
who have proven themselves to those above them. Often, village
priests will have no knowledge of these, but wandering priests
may perform the services needed from time to time, occasionally
stopping to teach the secrets to those in great need who have
shown diligence in the faith.
</para>

<para>
Knowledge of the Level III invocations is restricted to the
highest levels of the priestly orders, and only those who have
risen in the ranks will be taught them.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Study of Invocations</title>
<para>
Invocations were gifted by the gods to their followers when the
principle religions were being founded. The original followers
were taught the ways to call on their god's power by the gods
themselves. Since that time, the gods have taken no further part
in the teaching of this knowledge, and it has been handed down
from priest to priest through the ages.
</para>

<para>
Knowledge of an invocation cannot be gained in any way other
than being taught by someone with higher skill. This generally
means finding a priest of senior ability and persuading them to
teach the student. This limitation allows the more senior members
of the order greater control over who advances in the church.
It is also a weakness, in that the premature death of senior
members of the church, who may be the only ones who know an
invocation up to a given level, will weaken the church permanently.
Most of the major religions have temples dedicated to the teaching
of the religions secrets to younger members, to try and minimise
the risk.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Using Cult Invocations</title>
<para>
Cult invocations may be taught to anyone, though only those
favoured by the god may find any use from that knowledge. A
cult invocation is a mixture of prayer, ceremony and sacrifice
as well as actual skill.
</para>

<para>
The invocation skill is always rolled against charisma. If the
invocation affects another person directly (e.g. It does not
take some physical form), then the target gets a will roll to
resist. Their will is opposed against the priest's will, with
the priest getting a bonus of one fifth of their invocation roll.
</para>

<sect3><title>Sacrifice</title>
<para>
One of the demands of the skill is that a suitable sacrifice is
made to the god during the prayer ceremony. The nature of the
sacrifice depends on the god, and the ritual that is being used.
It can range from a share of the crops, the loss of a valuable
item, or the sacrifice of an animal, or even a person.
</para>

<sect4><title>Material Cost</title>
<para>
The material cost the sacrifice is given with the invocation
description, and is rated from low, to very high. This is
relative to the earnings of the person who is benefitting from
the invocation.
</para>

<para>
If the cost is noted as immediate, then the sacrifice must be
paid before, or as, the invocation is made. Otherwise, it is
possible to delay the sacrifice until afterwards. How long
afterwards is up to the priest, though as soon as possible is
generally a good idea to avoid invoking the displeasure of
their deity.
</para>

<para>
As a general guide, the following costs of the material
sacrificed can be used. Cost is relative to the means of the
individual benefiting from the god's attention. For those
who don't have a stable income, then living expenses can be
substituted for income. For example, a 'high' cost would
equate to the amount normally spent on food and lodgings for
a period of a week. These costs are not hard and fast, though
should average out over time.
</para>

<para>
It is the responsibility of the benefactor of the invocation to
ensure that some recompense is paid to the god, not the
responsibility of the priest. Payment may be directly to the
god (in the form of a sacrifice), or payment to a temple. In
the latter case, wealth flows from the common folk, to the
local temples and then up to the more important temples.
Eventually, the wealth pays for a crusade, quest or new temple
in the name of the god.
</para>

<para>
    <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>Low</term>
    <listitem>
        A token amount, generally amounting to half a day's
        earnings. A serf or similar person who does not earn
        money, or have much material wealth to spare, may
        substitute half a day's labour done for the local temple.
        Often a son or daughter will be sent to help the
        priest for a day.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Moderate</term>
    <listitem>
        Two days earnings, or two day's labour. Similar possible
        payments might be the loan of tools or vehicles (such as
        a cart, or donkey) for the period to the local temple.
        If a travelling priest has performed an invocation for
        a family, then the family may be expected to provide food
        and lodgings for the priest for a couple of days.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>High</term>
    <listitem>
        A week's earnings. In a similar way to moderate sacrifices,
        payment in other forms is possible. Those who are capable
        may be requested to perform some task for the religion.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Very high</term>
    <listitem>
        A month's earnings. Such sacrifices are very rarely required
        by invocations. Only the most powerful invocations have
        such a cost, and the effects of these invocations are normally
        long lasting.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Spiritual Cost</title>
<para>
Some invocations have a spiritual cost as well. This cost is
in luck points, which must be paid immediately. This is shown
as /x after the material cost, where x is the number of luck
points.
</para>

<para>
This loss of luck is normally temporary, though if the invocation
was used in a way the god is not happy with, it will be permanent.
Generally, use of an invocation in a way that goes directly against
the god's wishes will be forbidden, whilst unnecessary use of their
power will result in luck being lost.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Effects of an Invocation</title>
<para>
Invocations are not subtle. If a god is going to be bothered
to interfere amongst mortals, then they want to advertise the
fact. An invocation must clearly name the deity. A successful
invocation will produce obvious special effects. A protected
person might glow, a healing invocation might produce glowing
lights around the person as they are healed. A curse will
strike a person down with flames, darkness or a ray of light,
depending on the preference of the deity.
</para>

<para>
The effects of Naveh tend to involve darkness, a shimmer
around the object affected or similar illusory effects.
</para>

<para>
Agrik and Larani tend to be bright, and very obvious. Sarajin's
invocations will tend to summon an icy wind, or a layer of frost.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Resisting Invocations</title>
<para>
It is possible to resist the effects of an invocation, though
only if the invocation affects a target directly. An invocation
that causes a pillar of fire to strike a target does not allow
resistance (other than soak). An invocation which causes disease
in a target does.
</para>

<para>
The resistance is the will of the target against the will of
the priest, with the priest getting a bonus equal to their
invocation skill. Both priest and target also each gain a bonus
equal to their current luck.
</para>

<para>
A resistance roll which fails by 10 or more causes the
invocation to be a critical success, which may have an
additional effect, depending on the invocation.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Cult Skills</title>
<para>
Cult skills are further secrets of a religion, though unlike
rituals they are totally mundane, but simply not well known.
Most are closely guarded secrets, though some are simply
restricted to a particular religion because no one else has
a need for them.
</para>

<para>
Learning cult skills is restricted, in that anyone with less
than level four in the skill can only improve by having
another teach them. Once level four has been reached,
improvement can be through self study and experience as for
other skills.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Aura</title>
<para>
All living things have an aura, which can sometimes be
determined through religious rituals. The aura of a person
or creature gives an insight into their nature, personality
and religious beliefs.
</para>

<para>
Any religious ritual which allows a priest to divine the
aura of a person uses the following guide for use of their
ritual skill.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="6.5cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Target</entry>
            <entry>Information gained from Aura</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>10</entry>
            <entry>
            The bloodline or basic nature of the target is known.
            Whether someone is Human, Sindarin, Faerie or an
            elemental or demonoic spirit is known.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>20</entry>
            <entry>
            Elemental and divine affinities, if any. Shek-Pvar who
            are attuned to an element will have an aura tainted by
            that element. Priests of a god are also bound to their
            god, and this affects their aura.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>30</entry>
            <entry>
            The physical and mental well being of the target is
            known. Roughly how exhausted, injured and hungry the
            target is can be determined, as well as their primary
            emotions.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>40</entry>
            <entry>
            Knowledge of a person's morals, in regard to whether
            they are good or evil is obtained.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>50</entry>
            <entry>
            If the target has any leanings towards Law or Chaos,
            then this can be determined.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>60</entry>
            <entry>
            The religion of the target, even if they are not a
            priest. Also given, is a general guide to how
            strongly they follow the ideals of their faith.
            </entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>
</table>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Divine Intervention</title>
<para>
Invocations are not the only way in which a god may aid one
of their followers. They are heavy on ritual and ceremony,
and can only be used by those who are part of the mainstream
church (since they will not be taught to anyone else).
</para>


<para>
Any follower of a god however may call for divine intervention.
Divine aid takes a round to be called for, though the character
may perform other actions whilst doing so. However, the call
for divine intervention must be made vocally, in a loud, clear
voice. The name of the god must be invoked, and the nature of
the request must be stated.
</para>

<para>
Assuming that the request does not go against the morals of the
god, then there is a chance that the god will intervene on
behalf of their follower. The character spends a number of points
of luck, and rolls for intervention as follows.

<skillequation>
    <attribute>luck spent</attribute>
    <constant>5</constant>
    <die/>
</skillequation>

The luck spent is always lost permanently, regardless of the
outcome. The target number that must be obtained depends on how
worthy the request is.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="6.5cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Target</entry>
            <entry>Worthiness of request</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>20</entry>
            <entry>
            Very worthy.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>30</entry>
            <entry>
            Worthy.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>40</entry>
            <entry>
            Neutral.
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>50</entry>
            <entry>
            Unworthy.
            </entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>
</table>
</para>



</sect2>

<sect2><title>Priest Characters</title>
<para>
The majority of priests attain priesthood after spending
many years training in a religious institution. There, they
are taught the tenants of their faith, as well as the basic
invocations and cult skills they are expected to learn.
</para>

<para>
Player character priests will normally be at least 21 years
old. Characters younger than this will rarely have had time
to learn all the necessary skills, and will be considered an
acolyte, rather than a full priest.
</para>

<para>
Priests of all religions will have the following common
invocations:
</para>

<para>
Blessing 2
</para>

<para>
They will also have the following skills:
    Religion (their own) 4
    Scribe (their own) 4
</para>

<para>
These do need to be paid for.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Common Invocations</title>
<para>
Common invocations are available to, and taught by, priests
of all religions. However, they are different in the details,
so the invocation skill for Blessing (Morgath) is very different
to that for Blessing (Larani).
</para>

<para>
Many of the common invocations are based off the same invocation
skill. There are three meta-invocations - Blessing, Channel and
Divination. All priests start with at least knowledge of
Blessing. This provides knowledge of the basic ceremonies the
priest has to be able to perform, in order to contact their god,
perform baptism's, marriage and funeral rites.
</para>

<para>
Invocations which make use of these meta-invocations will name
them in parenthesis after the invocation title.
</para>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/common.xml" religion="Common"/>
</para>

</sect1>



<sect1><title>Agrik</title>
<taglines>
	<line>Lord of the Four Horsemen</line>
</taglines>

<para>
The fiery, evil god of war, favoured by those who enjoy cruelty
and destruction. Agrik is worshiped by dozens of squabbling
clerical sects and fighting orders.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/agrik.xml" religion="Agrik"/>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Character Templates</title>

<sect3><title>Cult skills</title>

<sect4><title>Torture</title>
<para>
Knowledge of how to torture a person, without actually killing
them. This is rolled opposed against the victim's will to try
and break them.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Berserk</title>
<para>
This skill enables the priest to enter a berserk rage.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Eight Demons</title>
<para>
<import-character-template href="templates/agrik-clerics.xml"
                            name="Eight Demons Clerical Order"/>
</para>

<para>
</para>
</sect3>


<sect3><title>Fuming Gate</title>

<para>
<import-character-template href="templates/agrik-clerics.xml"
                            name="Fuming Gate Clerical Order"/>

</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1><title>Halea</title>
<taglines>
	<line>Enslaver of Hearts and Loins</line>
</taglines>

<para>
The goddess of wealth and pleasure. She demands unswerving
devotion and her adherents. Only women can enter her clergy.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/halea.xml" religion="Halea"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Cult skills</title>

<sect3><title>Erotic arts</title>
<para>
The skill of giving pleasure to someone. Also includes various
forms of exotic dancing and knowledge of how to dress and present
oneself in order to create desire in others, as well as simply
being very, very good in bed.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Character Templates</title>


<sect3><title>Silken Voice (Halea)</title>

<para>
<import-character-template href="templates/silkenvoice.xml"/>
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1><title>Ilvir</title>
<taglines>
	<line>Prince of the Fatherless Multitude</line>
</taglines>

<para>
The creator of the Ivashu. His followers are individualists,
creative, and mystical. Dozens of sects worship Ilvir, although
his adherents are few and mostly found in Orbaal.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>
<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/ilvir.xml" religion="Ilvir"/>
</para>
</sect2>


</sect1>


<sect1><title>Larani</title>
<taglines>
	<line>Lady of Paladins</line>
</taglines>

<para>
The Lady of Paladins is the goddess of chivalry and battle,
favoured by the feudal nobility. Those who follow her are
expected to display courage, compassion and honour.
</para>

<para>
Despite being a goddess of War, Larani despises violence, and
believes that it should only be used as a last resort. Her
followers vary greatly in how closely they follow this
particular ideal, the militant orders of her church can be
especially lax at times at avoiding violent confrontation.
</para>

<para>
There are two clerical orders - The Spear of Shattered Sorrow
and the Order of Hyvrik. Both have martial and non-martial
members, though all (in theory) prefer non-violent solutions
to disputes.
</para>

<para>
The sponsored fighting orders are not taught priestly
invocations, unless they have proven themselves worthy over
a long period of time.
</para>


<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>
<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/larani.xml" religion="Larani"/>
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Common skills</title>
<para>
Law; weapon and shield; ride; lance; guile; battle.
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Character Templates</title>


<sect3><title>Order of Hyvrik (Larani)</title>

<para>
<import-character-template href="templates/larani-clerics.xml" name="Order of Hyvrik"/>
<br/>
<import-character-template href="templates/larani-clerics.xml" name="Order of Hyvrik Warrior"/>
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1><title>Morgath</title>
<taglines>
	<line>Tormentor of the Unlamented Dead</line>
</taglines>

<para>
Morgath is the master of chaos, evil and the undead, who
despises all things fair and noble. His church is dour and
ruthless, and infamous for its human sacrifice.
</para>

<para>
The most feared aspect of priests of Morgath is their ability
to create, and control, undead. There are two types of undead
- the Amorvrin (willing) and the Gulmorvrin (unwilling). The
latter are far more common.
</para>

<sect2><title>Encounters with the Shadow</title>
<para>
Amorvrin may have a shadow extending beyond their bodies.
Entering this, or touching a morvrus, is generally not a good
idea. It is an extension of Bukrai # the power of Morgath.
</para>

<para>
Contact with the Shadow causes an immediate mental attack on
the living soul. The morvrus attacks with its will, as per a
damage roll which is soaked with the living soul's own will.
Damage is suffered in fatigue levels. Each round of contact
causes another will attack.
</para>

<para>
Note that for a gulmorvrin, touch is enough to initiate this
will attack, even if the attack does not get through armour.
</para>

<para>
If the living creature falls unconscious from fatigue, then
they are possessed by the Shadow. The soul is offered two
choices - accept it, and become an amorvrus, or refuse it and
become gulmorvrus.
</para>

<para>
In any event, the living creature immediately becomes undead.
Their body levels are effectively doubled, and if they are
gulmorvrin, they come under the control of the Shadow which
possessed them.
</para>

<para>
The Shadow extends out one metre for each point of will an
amorvrin has. If multiple Shadows are overlapping, only one
Shadow attack is made, but at increased strength. Use the
highest will # 4, plus 1 for each point of will overlapping.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>
<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/morgath.xml" religion="Morgath"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Naveh</title>
<taglines>
	<line>Lord of the Pitch Shadow</line>
</taglines>

<para>
A god of darkness, best known as the bringer of nightmares,
and worshiped by thieves and assassins. His fanatical clerics
will commit suicide to prove their faith.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/naveh.xml" religion="Naveh"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Peoni</title>
<taglines>
	<line>Bringer of Life Renewed</line>
</taglines>

<para>
The gentle goddess of agriculture and healing, worshiped by
most rural folk. Peoni's clergy are divided into celibate male
and female orders; both maintain hospitals. Temples are always
near poverty.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/peoni.xml" religion="Peoni"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Sarajin</title>
<taglines>
	<line>King of the Icy Wind</line>
</taglines>

<para>
The god of battlelust, who demands honour and bravery from his
adherents, mostly Ivinians. His sport is war and he sometimes
joins human battles.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/sarajin.xml" religion="Sarajin"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Save-K'nor</title>
<taglines>
	<line>Lord of Puzzles</line>
</taglines>

<para>
The god of knowledge and seeker of enlightenment, the Sage
of Heaven. His adherents believe that a stable and ordered
society precludes evil behaviour.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>
<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/saveknor.xml" religion="Save-K'nor"/>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Siem</title>
<taglines>
	<line>Master of the Lord of Dreams</line>
</taglines>

<para>
The benign god of mystery, magic and dreams. He is the special
deity of elves and dwarves. Siem's worshipers favour a personal
approach to the deity rather than one based on rigid church
doctrine. As such, there is little need for actual priests of
this god, and temples are few and far between. Shrines do exist,
though they are more likely to be a natural feature, such as
a pool or tree, as they are to be a stone monument.
</para>

<para>
Priests of Siem are more common amongst the Sindarin and Khuzdul
than they are amongst humans, mostly because he is the deity of
these races, but also partly because he appeals more to their
way of thinking. Few priests of the god are full time priests,
they are often merely people who have become close to him.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
The normaly method of progressing knowledge of invocations is
through study under a senior priest. The lack of any church
structure makes this infeasible for followers of Siem.
</para>

<para>
Unlike the other gods, Siem comes to those he considers worthy
himself, and shows them the paths they must follow to broaden
their understanding. When the time is right, a follower of Siem
is given a vision of a place to find, normally in the wilderness.
There, the knowledge of the god will be revealed to them.
</para>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/siem.xml" religion="Siem"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1><title>Barbarian Religions</title>

<para>
The various barbarian tribes of Harn have their own religions, generally
based around shamans. Like for the more mainstream religions, they have
their own beliefs, invocations and morals.
</para>

<sect2><title>Comman Shaman Invocations</title>

<para>
Shamans do not get access to the common invocations used by mainstream
priests, however they do have their own versions of these. The following
invocations can be learnt be taught by all shamans.
</para>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/barbarians.xml" religion="Barbarian"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Gozyda Invocations</title>
<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/barbarians.xml" religion="Gozyda"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>


</article>
