<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://www.bifrost.demon.co.uk/xsl/fo/docbook.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<article>
<artheader>
    <title>Harn Religion</title>
    <author>    
        <firstname>Samuel</firstname>
        <surname>Penn</surname>
    </author>
    
    <referenceinfo>
        <copyright>
            <year>2001</year>
            <holder>Samuel Penn</holder>
        </copyright>
        <releaseinfo role="meta">$Revision: 1.2 $</releaseinfo>
    </referenceinfo>
    <revhistory>
        <revision>
            <revnumber>0.7.1</revnumber>
            <date>14th Oct 2001</date>
            <revremark>Docbook format</revremark>
        </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <subjectset>
        <subject>Yags</subject>
        <subject>Harn</subject>
    </subjectset>
    <colourscheme>
        <colour>blue</colour>
        <darkcolour>#aaaaff</darkcolour>
        <lightcolour>#ddddff</lightcolour>
    </colourscheme>
</artheader>

<sect1><title>Religion</title>
<para>
The gods of Harn are real, and the powers they grant to their
priests are just as real. Described here are rules for playing
priests in Harn using Yags. For a complete description of the
gods and their beliefs, see the HarnMaster Religion supplement.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<sect3><title>Levels of Knowledge</title>
<para>
There are three levels of knowledge which define what cult 
nvocations are taught to a trainee priest. Invocations of
level I are taught to all initiates by their mentor. Village
priests will have most, if not all, level I cult invocations,
of some level. In game terms, a priest character can begin
with knowledge of any level I invocation up to the normal
limit of knowledge.
</para>

<para>
Level II invocations are those which are revealed only to those
who have proven themselves to those above them. Often, village
priests will have no knowledge of these, but wandering priests
may perform the services needed from time to time, occasionally
stopping to teach the secrets to those in great need who have
shown diligence in the faith.
</para>

<para>
Knowledge of the Level III invocations is restricted to the
highest levels of the priestly orders, and only those who have
risen in the ranks will be taught them.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Using Cult Invocations</title>
<para>
Cult invocations may be taught to anyone, though only those
favoured by the god may find any use from that knowledge. A 
ult invocation is a mixture of prayer, ceremony and sacrifice
as well as actual skill.
</para>

<para>
The invocation skill is always rolled against charisma. If the
invocation affects another person directly (e.g. It does not
take some physical form), then the target gets a will roll to
resist. Their will is opposed against the priest's will, with 
the priest getting a bonus of one fifth of their invocation roll.
</para>

<sect3><title>Sacrifice</title>
<para>
One of the demands of the skill is that a suitable sacrifice is
made to the god during the prayer ceremony. The nature of the
sacrifice depends on the god, and the ritual that is being used.
It can range from a share of the crops, the loss of a valuable
item, or the sacrifice of an animal, or even a person.
</para>

<para>
The material cost the sacrifice is given with the invocation 
escription, and is rated from low, to very high. This is
relative to the earnings of the person who is benefiting from 
he invocation.
</para>

<para>
If the cost is noted as immediate, then the sacrifice must be
payed before, or as, the invocation is made. Otherwise, it is
possible to delay the sacrifice until afterwards. How long 
afterwards is up to the priest, though as soon as possible is
generally a good idea to avoid invoking the displeasure of
their deity.
</para>

<para>
As a general guide, the following costs of the material
sacrificed can be used.
</para>

<para>
Low: A days earnings.
</para>

<para>
Moderate: A weeks earnings.
</para>

<para>
High: A months earnings.
</para>

<para>
Very high: A years earnings.
</para>

<para>
Some invocations have a spiritual cost as well. This cost is
in luck points, which must be paid immediately. This is shown
as /x after the material cost, where x is the number of luck
points.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Effects of an Invocation</title>
<para>
Invocations are not subtle. If a god is going to be bothered
to interfere amongst mortals, then they want to advertise the
fact. An invocation must clearly name the deity. A successful
invocation will produce obvious special effects. A protected
person might glow, a healing invocation might produce glowing
lights around the person as they are healed. A curse will
strike a person down with flames, darkness or a ray of light, 
epending on the preference of the deity.
</para>

<para>
The effects of Naveh tend to involve darkness, a shimmer
around the object affected or similar illusionary effects.
</para>

<para>
Agrik and Larani tend to be bright, and very obvious. Sarajin's
invocations will tend to summon an icy wind, or a layer of frost.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Resisting Invocations</title>
<para>
It is possible to resist the effects of an invocation, though
only if the invocation affects a target directly. An invocation
that causes a pillar of fire to strike a target does not allow 
esistance (other than soak). An invocation which causes disease
in a target does.
</para>

<para>
The resistance is the will of the target against the will of
the priest, with the priest getting a bonus equal to their
invocation skill. Both priest and target also each gain a bonus
equal to their current luck.
</para>

<para>
A resistance roll which fails by 10 or more causes the
invocation to be a critical success, which may have an
additional effect, depending on the invocation.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Cult Skills</title>
<para>
Cult skills are further secrets of a religion, though unlike
rituals they are totally mundane, but simply not well known.
Most are closely guarded secrets, though some are simply
restricted to a particular religion because no one else has
a need for them.
</para>

<para>
Learning cult skills is restricted, in that anyone with less
than level four in the skill can only improve by having
another teach them. Once level four has been reached,
improvement can be through self study and experience as for
other skills.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Aura</title>
<para>
All living things have an aura, which can sometimes be
determined through religious rituals. The aura of a person
or creature gives an insight into their nature, personality
and religious beliefs.
</para>

<para>
Any religious ritual which allows a priest to divine the
aura of a person uses the following guide for use of their
ritual skill.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Priest Characters</title>
<para>
The majority of priests attain priesthood after spending
many years training in a religious institution. There, they
are taught the tenants of their faith, as well as the basic
invocations and cult skills they are expected to learn.
</para>

<para>
Player character priests will normally be at least 21 years
old. Characters younger than this will rarely have had time
to learn all the necessary skills, and will be considered an
acolyte, rather than a full priest.
</para>

<para>
Priests of all religions will have the following common
invocations:
</para>

<para>
Blessing 2
</para>

<para>
They will also have the following skills:
    Religion (their own) 4
    Scribe (their own) 4
</para>

<para>
These do need to be paid for.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Common Invocations</title>
<para>
Common invocations are available to, and taught by, priests
of all religions. However, they are different in the details,
so the invocation skill for Blessing (Morgath) is very different
to that for Blessing (Larani).
</para>

<para>
Many of the common invocations are based off the same invocation
skill. There are three meta-invocations - Blessing, Channel and
Divination. All priests start with at least knowledge of
Blessing. This provides knowledge of the basic ceremonies the
priest has to be able to perform, in order to contact their god,
perform baptism's, marriage and funeral rites.
</para>

<para>
Invocations which make use of these meta-invocations will name
them in parenthesis after the invocation title.
</para>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/common.xml" religion="Common"/>
</para>

</sect1>



<sect1><title>Agrik</title>
<para>
Lord of the Four Horsemen
</para>

<para>
The fiery, evil god of war, favoured by those who enjoy cruelty
and destruction. Agrik is worshipped by dozens of squabbling
clerical sects and fighting orders.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/agrik.xml" religion="Agrik"/>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Character Templates</title>

<sect3><title>Cult skills</title>

<sect4><title>Torture</title>
<para>
Knowledge of how to torture a person, without actually killing
them. This is rolled opposed against the victim's will to try
and break them.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Berserk</title>
<para>
This skill enables the priest to enter a berserk rage.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Eight Demons</title>
<para>
A female only clerical order, infamous for sexual torture,
mutilation and the sacrifice of male captives. The sponsor
the fighting order Cohorts of Gashang.
</para>

<para>
<character-template name="Eight Demons Clerical Order">

	<description>
		A female only clerical order, infamous for sexual torture,
		mutilation and the sacrifice of male captives. The sponsor
		the fighting order Cohorts of Gashang.
	</description>

	<attributes points="48">
		<strength score="3"/>
		<stamina score="4"/>
		<agility score="2"/>
		<dexterity score="3"/>
		<perception score="2"/>
		<intelligence score="3"/>
		<charisma score="4"/>
		<will score="3"/>
	</attributes>

	<advantages points="10">
		<advantage name="attributes" cost="+2"/>
		<advantage name="literate" cost="+2"/>
		<advantage name="social status" cost="+2"/>
		<advantage name="experience" cost="+3"/>
		<advantage name="fanatic" score="+3"
					target="Agrik" cost="-3"/>
		<advantage name="deviant" score="+4"
					target="sexual torture" cost="-6"/>
	</advantages>

	<skills>
	
		<group name="Talents" type="talents">
			<skill name="Athletics" score="1"/>
			<skill name="Awareness" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Brawl" score="3"/>
			<skill name="Charm" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Guile" score="3"/>
			<skill name="Sleight" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Stealth" score="1"/>
			<skill name="Throw" score="1"/>
		</group>
		
		<group name="Common Knowledges" type="knowledges">
			<skill name="Area lore" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Folk lore" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Speak own" score="4"/>
			<skill name="Scribe own" score="4"/>
		</group>
		
		<group name="Skills at age 21" type="age21">
			<skill name="Religion (Agrik)" score="4"/>
			<skill name="Torture" score="5"/>
			<skill name="Single weapon" score="4"/>
			<skill name="First aid" score="1"/>
			<skill name="Blessing" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Ak-Syt's Peace" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Emyn's Cut" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Shield of Amanya" score="1"/>
		</group>
		
		<group name="Skills at age 25" type="age25">
			<skill name="Ak-Syt's Peace" score="3"/>
			<skill name="Emyn's Cut" score="3"/>
			<skill name="Shield of Amanya" score="2"/>
		</group>
		
		<group nmae="Skills at age 30" type="age30">
			<skill name="First aid" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Herb lore" score="1"/>
			<skill name="Ak-Syt's Peace" score="4"/>
			<skill name="Shield of Amanya" score="3"/>
		</group>
	</skills>

	<equipment>
		<item name="Dagger"/>
		<item name="Robes"/>
		<item name="Torture equipment"/>
	</equipment>
</character-template>
</para>
</sect3>


<sect3><title>Fuming Gate</title>

<para>
<character-template>
	<description>
		A clerical order based in Golotha. It sponsors the Copper Hook
		fighting order.
	</description>
	
	<attributes points="48">
		<strength score="3"/>
		<stamina score="3"/>
		<agility score="3"/>
		<dexterity score="3"/>
		<perception score="2"/>
		<intelligence score="3"/>
		<charisma score="4"/>
		<will score="3"/>
	</attributes>

	<advantages points="6">
		<advantage name="attributes" cost="+1"/>
		<advantage name="literate" cost="+2"/>
		<advantage name="social status" cost="+2"/>
		<advantage name="experience" cost="+1"/>
		<advantage name="fanatic" score="+3"
                target="Agrik" cost="-3"/>
        <advantage name="deviant" score="+3"
                target="sadistic torture" cost="-3"/>
    </advantages>


    <skills>
        <group name="Talents" type="talents">
            <skill name="Athletics" score="3"/>
            <skill name="Awareness" score="2"/>
            <skill name="Brawl" score="3"/>
            <skill name="Charm" score="2"/>
            <skill name="Guile" score="2"/>
            <skill name="Sleight" score="1"/>
            <skill name="Stealth" score="1"/>
            <skill name="Throw" score="1"/>
        </group>
        
        <group name="Common Knowledges" type="knowledges">
            <skill name="Area lore" score="2"/>
            <skill name="Folk lore" score="2"/>
			<skill name="Speak own" score="4"/>
			<skill name="Scribe own" score="4"/>
		</group>

        <group name="Skills for age 21" type="age21">
            <skill name="Religion (Agrik)" score="4"/>
            <skill name="Torture" score="4"/>
            <skill name="Single weapon" score="4"/>
            <skill name="Blessing" score="2"/>
            <skill name="Ak-Syt's Peace" score="2"/>
            <skill name="Shield of Amanya" score="2"/>
            <skill name="Emyn's Cut" score="2"/>
        </group>
    </skills>
    
    <equipment>
        <item name="Dagger"/>
        <item name="Robes"/>
        <item name="Torture equipment"/>
    </equipment>
</character-template>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1><title>Halea</title>
<para>
Enslaver of Hearts and Loins
</para>

<para>
The goddess of wealth and pleasure. She demands unswerving
devotion and her adherents. Only women can enter her clergy.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/halea.xml" religion="Halea"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Cult skills</title>

<sect3><title>Erotic arts</title>
<para>
The skill of giving pleasure to someone. Also includes various
forms of exotic dancing and knowledge of how to dress and present
oneself in order to create desire in others, as well as simply
being very, very good in bed.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Character Templates</title>


<sect3><title>Silken Voice (Halea)</title>

<para>
<import-character-template href="templates/silkenvoice.xml" name="Silken Voice"/>
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1><title>Ilvir</title>
<para>
Prince of the Fatherless Multitude
</para>

<para>
The creator of the Ivashu. His followers are individualists,
creative, and mystical. Dozens of sects worship Ilvir, although
his adherents are few and mostly found in Orbaal.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>
<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/ilvir.xml" religion="Ilvir"/>
</para>
</sect2>


</sect1>


<sect1><title>Larani</title>
<para>
Lady of Paladins
</para>

<para>
The Lady of Paladins is the goddess of chivalry and battle,
favoured by the feudal nobility. Those who follow her are
expected to display courage, compassion and honour.
</para>

<para>
Despite being a goddess of War, Larani despises violence, and
believes that it should only be used as a last resort. Her
followers vary greatly in how closely they follow this
particular ideal, the militant orders of her church can be
especially lax at times at avoiding violent confrontation.
</para>

<para>
There are two clerical orders - The Spear of Shattered Sorrow
and the Order of Hyvrik. Both have martial and non-martial
members, though all (in theory) prefer non-violent solutions
to disputes.
</para>

<para>
The sponsored fighting orders are not taught priestly
invocations, unless they have proven themselves worthy over
a long period of time.
</para>


<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>
<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/larani.xml" religion="Larani"/>
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Common skills</title>
<para>
Law; weapon and shield; ride; lance; guile; battle.
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Character Templates</title>


<sect3><title>Order of Hyvrik (Larani)</title>

The Larani clerical order which sponsors the fighting-order
Checkered Shield. The order is very wealthy, holding vast
estates throughout Kanday. This template describes a fighting
member of the order, trained to some extent to defend the weak
and helpless and oppression.

Non-Martial Member of Hyvrik
Attributes (48 points)
Strength    3    Perception    3
Stamina    3    Intelligence    3
Agility    2    Charisma    4
Dexterity    3    Will    4
Advantages and Disadvantages (14 points)
+5 attributes        +2 literate
+2 social status (clerical order)
+5 exceptional training (10 points)
-3 terrible liar (-3)
-6 duty (aiding the church)
-4 loyalty (Larani, +4)
-1 sensitive (+3, suffering of the weak)
Talents (24 points)
Athletics    2    Guile    3
Awareness    2    Sleight    1
Brawl    2    Stealth    1
Charm    3    Throw    1
Common Knowledges (fixed)
Area lore    2    Folk lore    2
Speak own    4    Scribe    4
Skills for age:        21    25    30
Religion (Larani)        4        5
Weapon and shield        2
Ride        3
Law        4        5    
First aid        3    4
Cult Invocations
Blessing        2
Banner of Mendiz        2
Larani's Shield        1    2
Light of Dolithor        1    2
Valamin's Insight        2
Fast of the Tirannon        1        
Passage to Tirithor        2        
Equipment
Priestly garb, riding horse.
Martial Member of Hyvrik
Attributes (48 points)
Strength    4    Perception    2
Stamina    3    Intelligence    3
Agility    2    Charisma    4
Dexterity    3    Will    4
Advantages and Disadvantages (15 points)
+6 attributes        +2 literate
+2 social status (clerical order)
+5 exceptional training (10 points)
-2 terrible liar (-2)
-6 duty (aiding the church)
-4 loyalty (Larani, +4)
-3 driving goal (wipe out Agrik, +3)
Talents (24 points)
Athletics    2    Guile    3
Awareness    2    Sleight    1
Brawl    2    Stealth    1
Charm    3    Throw    1
Common Knowledges (fixed)
Area lore    2    Folk lore    2
Speak own    4    Scribe    4
Skills for age:        21    25    30
Religion (Larani)        4    
Weapon and shield        5
Ride        4
Law        2            
Cult Invocations
Blessing        2
Banner of Mendiz        2    4    
Courage of Mendiz        2        3
Larani's Shield        2        4
Valamin's Insight            1    
Equipment
Half chain, broad sword, shield, helm, riding horse.
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1><title>Morgath</title>
<para>
Tormentor of the Unlamented Dead
</para>

<para>
Morgath is the master of chaos, evil and the undead, who
despises all things fair and noble. His church is dour and
ruthless, and infamous for its human sacrifice.
</para>

<para>
The most feared aspect of priests of Morgath is their ability
to create, and control, undead. There are two types of undead
- the Amorvrin (willing) and the Gulmorvrin (unwilling). The
latter are far more common.
</para>

<sect2><title>Encounters with the Shadow</title>
<para>
Amorvrin may have a shadow extending beyond their bodies.
Entering this, or touching a morvrus, is generally not a good
idea. It is an extension of Bukrai # the power of Morgath.
</para>

<para>
Contact with the Shadow causes an immediate mental attack on
the living soul. The morvrus attacks with its will, as per a
damage roll which is soaked with the living soul's own will.
Damage is suffered in fatigue levels. Each round of contact
causes another will attack.
</para>

<para>
Note that for a gulmorvrin, touch is enough to initiate this
will attack, even if the attack does not get through armour.
</para>

<para>
If the living creature falls unconscious from fatigue, then
they are possessed by the Shadow. The soul is offered two
choices - accept it, and become an amorvrus, or refuse it and
become gulmorvrus.
</para>

<para>
In any event, the living creature immediately becomes undead.
Their body levels are effectively doubled, and if they are
gulmorvrin, they come under the control of the Shadow which
possessed them.
</para>

<para>
The Shadow extends out one metre for each point of will an
amorvrin has. If multiple Shadows are overlapping, only one
Shadow attack is made, but at increased strength. Use the
highest will # 4, plus 1 for each point of will overlapping.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>
<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/morgath.xml" religion="Morgath"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Naveh</title>
<para>
Lord of the Pitch Shadow
</para>

<para>
A god of darkness, best known as the bringer of nightmares,
and worshipped by thieves and assassins. His fanatical clerics
will commit suicide to prove their faith.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/naveh.xml" religion="Naveh"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Peoni</title>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/peoni.xml" religion="Peoni"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Sarajin</title>
<para>
King of the Icy Wind
</para>

<para>
The god of battlelust, who demands honour and bravery from his
adherents, mostly Ivinians. His sport is war and he sometimes
joins human battles.
</para>

<sect2><title>Cult Invocations</title>

<para>
<import-invocations href="invocations/sarajin.xml" religion="Sarajin"/>
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

Prayer to Elkyri I
Time: 1 round        Range: Self
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low
A prayer to one specific Elkyri. Gives a bonus to one skill to perform one task of one fifth the invocation roll.
Unsarl's Hug I
Time: 1 minute        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Low/immediate
Increases subject's strength by one twentieth of the invocation roll. Lasts until sleep.
Jarlak's Lope I
Time: 1 minute        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Low/immediate
Increases subject's agility by one twentieth of the invocation roll. Lasts until sleep.
Character Templates
Cult skills
Berserk
Common skills
Weapon and shield; great weapon; battle; navigation; boating. 
Save-K'nor
Lord of Puzzles
The god of knowledge and seeker of enlightenment, the Sage of Heaven. His adherents believe that a stable and ordered society precludes evil behaviour.
Cult Invocations
Library of the Hyn-Aerlori I
Time: 1 round        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10
Protects one book, scroll or other object with recorded information from discovery. Grants a bonus to the Difficulty to find the item equal to one half the invocation roll.
Light of Uhla I
Time: 1 round        Range: Self
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low
Priest can see in the dark as if they had a perception of one tenth the invocation roll.
Wisdom of the Shea-Al-Aecor I
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Self
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Moderate
Gives the priest insight into the proper course of action in a moral quandary.
Althea's Lamp II
Time: 1 minute        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: High
Blesses a lamp with some of the attributes of Uhla. Those who are questioned in the light of Althea's Lamp must make a will check to avoid telling the truth. If they fail by 10 or more, they cannot remain silent.
Character Templates
Cult skills
None.
Common skills
None.


Siem
Master of the Lord of Dreams
The benign god of mystery, magic and dreams. He is the special deity of elves and dwarves. Siem's worshippers favour a personal approach to the deity.
Cult Invocations
Counsel of Sweldre I
Time: 1 minute        Range: Self
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/immediate
Gives the priest insight into the proper course of action in a moral quandary.
The Twilight Scribe's Question I
Time: 1 round        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/immediate/1
All plants, animals, and spirits have a unique true name and knowing it is very useful. Priest learns the true name of any entity touched.
Curse of Sloth I
Time: 1 round        Range: Near
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Low/2
Duration: Sleep
The priest can specify a number of people within range not exceeding their invocation skill. For each twenty points rolled on invocation, the target's agility is reduced by one. The reduction is automatic.
Ilsiri Dance I
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Horizon
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Moderate/immediate
Calls an Ilsiri within range. The animal may resist with a will check, unless its true name is used in the invocation. Ilsiri are sometimes mischievious, sometimes helpful.
Nature's Aid II
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Horizon
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Moderate/immediate
Calls a friendly animal within range. The animal may resist with a will check, unless their true name is used.
Sereniel's Stone II
Time: 1 minute        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/immediate
Priest learns the type of rock or mineral touched and its purity.
Siem's Blessing II
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Mod./immediate/1
Gives a bonus of +1 per 20 rolled on the invocation to either strength or perception until sleep. Multiple bonuses can be split between different attributes.
Water of the Azure Bowl II
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Low/immediate
Purifies up to 1 litre of water per point of invocation rolled. The water must be in a single container.
Yael's Calm II
Time: 1 round        Range: Near
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Low
Ends fighting within range. Combatants must make a will roll to continue fighting.
Truthsight II
Time: 1 minute        Range: Near
Difficulty: 20        Cost: Moderate/immediate
Allows the priest to see magically hidden objects, and to perceive the aura of a living being or ethereal within range.
Way from Taur-Im-Aina II
Time: 1 hour        Range: 1 km/10 rolled
Difficulty: 30        Cost: High/immediate
The priest can physically merge his body into that of a tree or large bush (larger than the priest), and emerge from another of te same species within range. The unique true names of both plants must be known. The priest may remain in one tree indefinitely, but is not immune to hunger or thirst.
On a failure, the priest is stuck in the original tree.
Elmithri's Shower III
Time: 15 minutes        Range:  1km/5 rolled
Difficulty: 10        Cost: Moderate/immediate
Creates a gentle shower over an radius equal to one fifth the invocation roll. If the radius is halved, the shower can become snow, hail or heavy rain.
Sweldre's Cloak III
Time: 15 minutes        Range: Touch
Difficulty: 30        Cost: High/immediate
The subject takes on the form of a chosen animal. They have the physical attributes of that animal, but the intelligence and will of the subject. It lasts until the subject or the priest wishes it to end.
    30    Subject is changed into an animal. No clothees or equipment survive the change. The animal must be land based, and no more than 50% smaller, or 100% larger than the subject.
    40    Subject can become a fish. Target shape can be as small as a cat.
    50    Clothes and equipment change, as long as the target form could physically carry them.
    60    Clothes and equipment change, regardless of size.

Character Templates
Cult skills
None
Common skills
None.

</article>
