<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/fo/yagsbook.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<article>

<header>
    <title>H&#x00e2;rn Shek-Pvar</title>
    <tagline>Yags H&#x00e2;rn</tagline>
    <uri>yags/harn/shekpvar</uri>
    <format>System</format>
    <author>
        <firstname>Samuel</firstname>
        <surname>Penn</surname>
        <email>sam@bifrost.demon.co.uk</email>
    </author>

    <referenceinfo>
        <cvsversion>$Revision: 1.8 $</cvsversion>
        <cvsdate>$Date: 2002-01-13 14:44:31 $</cvsdate>
        <copyright>
            <year>2001</year>
            <holder>Samuel Penn</holder>
            <licence>Copyright</licence>
        </copyright>
    </referenceinfo>
    
    <displayscheme name="magic">
        <colour>#00ddff</colour>
        <darkcolour>#bbddff</darkcolour>
        <lightcolour>#ccffff</lightcolour>
    </displayscheme>
</header>

<sect1><title>Shek-Pvar</title>

<para>
Harn is far from being Magic Weak. Although uncommon, accomplished
magi with awesome powers do exist. Characters with the interest
and natural ability to practice the hidden arts have the option
to enter an elite vocation that demands skill and dedication to
prosper.
</para>

<sect2><title>Origins of the Shek-Pvar</title>
<para>
The Guild of Arcane Lore is a loose association of alchemists,
astrologers, magi, rune masters etc. The Shek-Pvar is a sub-organisation
(actually, six separate organisations) within the guild.
Shek-Pvar subscribe to a doctrine called Pvarism. This doctrine
perceives and describes Kelestia (everything that exists) in terms
of six key elemental principles: Air, Fire, Metal, Earth, Water
and Spirit. Because manipulation of these elements imposed unique
demands upon the mind and body, six schools of arcane lore evolved,
each stressing one of the elements.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Convocations</title>
<para>
A Shek-Pvar first attunes to a Primary convocation and learns primary
spells. Adjacent to this are the secondary convocations and spells.
Those two removed are tertiary. The convocation opposite the primary
is the diametric. These relationships are symbolised by the Pvaric
Wheel.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="3.5cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Convocation</entry>
            <entry>Hue</entry>
            <entry>Element</entry>
            <entry>Essence</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>Lyahvi</entry><entry>Red</entry><entry>Air</entry>
            <entry>Light, illusion, ethereal</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Peleahn</entry><entry>Orange</entry><entry>Fire</entry>
            <entry>Heat, action, dryness</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Jmorvi</entry><entry>Yellow</entry><entry>Metal</entry>
            <entry>Metals, minerals, artifice</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Fyvria</entry><entry>Green</entry><entry>Earth</entry>
            <entry>Birth, growth, death, decay</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Odivshe</entry><entry>Blue</entry><entry>Water</entry>
            <entry>Cold, darkness, moisture</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Savorya</entry><entry>Violet</entry><entry>Spirit</entry>
            <entry>Knowledge, mind, meaning</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Neutral</entry><entry>Grey</entry><entry></entry>
            <entry>Counter magic, inter-world travel, energy storage</entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>

</table>
</para>

<para>
There is a seventh 'element', which is neutrality. Neutrality
is represented by the colour grey, and corresponds to counter
magic, inter world travel and energy storage.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Spells</title>
<para>
Knowledge of convocations is merely theoretical. In order to apply
that knowledge and actually cast a spell, the Shek-Pvar must have
knowledge of the spell in question.
</para>

<para>
It is not possible for a Shek-Pvar to cause a magical effect without
having learned a spell to perform that effect. Spontaneous magical
effects are not possible according to currently understood theories
of Pvarism.
</para>

<para>
A Shek-Pvar has a skill with each spell. Learning spells is actually
quite easy, and it is possible to rapidly achieve a useful skill
level with a spell.
</para>

<sect2><title>Casting Spells</title>
<para>
In order to cast a spell, the Shek-Pvar multiplies together their
convocation skill and their spell skill. In effect, the convocation
is treated as the attribute, and the spell is the skill. If this
total matches the level of spell, then the spell is successfully
cast.
</para>

<sect3><title>Fatigue</title>
<para>
Casting a spell can result in fatigue, the amount depending on
how well the spell was cast, and the relationship of the spell's
convocation to that of the Shek-Pvar.
</para>

<para>
A spell in a Shek-Pvar's primary convocation can be cast without
fatigue if the casting roll is five or more points above the level
of the spell. Any roll less than this causes one point of long
term fatigue, regardless of whether the spell was cast or not.
A diametric spell will always cause at least one level of fatigue.
Neutral spells are considered to be equal to secondary spells
for the purposes of fatigue.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Overcast</entry>
            <entry>Primary</entry>
            <entry>Secondary</entry>
            <entry>Tertiary</entry>
            <entry>Diametric</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>0 - 4</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>4</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>5 - 9</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>10 - 14</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>15 - 19</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>3</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>20 - 24</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>2</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>25 - 29</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>2</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>30+</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>1</entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>

</table>
</para>

<para>
See the table above for the full list of effects. Any failure
to cast a spell results in the maximum amount of fatigue for that
type of spell (so a failure to cast a tertiary or diametric spell
causes four levels of fatigue to be lost).
</para>

<para>
A spell casting which results in unconsciousness is still a success,
though if the spell requires concentration, then concentration
is immediately lost.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Spell Descriptions</title>

<para>
The spells are listed with three main game attributes - level,
range and resist. The level of the spell is a measure of how difficult
it is to cast. Higher level spells are more powerful however.
</para>

<sect4><title>Spell Level</title>
<para>
The level of a spell is a measure of how complicated it is to
cast. Spells have seven different complexity ranks, and each rank
has a different level associated with it. Many spells can also
be boosted beyond their basic level. If the spell is cast at this
level (and the level is chosen before the spell is attempted),
then extra effects come into play.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Rank</entry>
            <entry>Level</entry>
            <entry>B+1</entry>
            <entry>B+2</entry>
            <entry>B+3</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>I</entry>
            <entry>10</entry>
            <entry>+10</entry>
            <entry>+20</entry>
            <entry>+40</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>II</entry>
            <entry>30</entry>
            <entry>+15</entry>
            <entry>+30</entry>
            <entry>+60</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>III</entry>
            <entry>60</entry>
            <entry>+15</entry>
            <entry>+30</entry>
            <entry>+60</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>IV</entry>
            <entry>90</entry>
            <entry>+15</entry>
            <entry>+30</entry>
            <entry>+60</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>V</entry>
            <entry>120</entry>
            <entry>+20</entry>
            <entry>+40</entry>
            <entry>+80</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>VI</entry>
            <entry>160</entry>
            <entry>+20</entry>
            <entry>+40</entry>
            <entry>+80</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>VII</entry>
            <entry>200</entry>
            <entry>+25</entry>
            <entry>+50</entry>
            <entry>+100</entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>
</table>
</para>

<para>
A level 30 spell requires a difficulty 30 spell casting roll to
cast it. If it is boosted once, it becomes difficulty 30 + 15 =
45. Boosting it twice makes it level 60, and three times makes
it level 90.
</para>

<para>
Ranks above VII are possible, though they are extremely rare.
</para>

<sect5><title>Multi-level Spells</title>

<para>
Some spells are multi-level. Only one spell needs to be learned
in order to use it at all levels. The level it is cast at is determined
each time just before the spell is cast. A lot of neutral spells
are multi-level, as are spells to summon and control elementals.
</para>
</sect5>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Common Spells</title>
<para>
Some spells are common across all the Pvaric convocations. A spell
listed as being common exists once for each convocation. Effectively,
there are seven different spells, but since they differ only by
which convocation they affect, they are listed once under this
single heading.
</para>

<para>
Knowing a common spell of one convocation does not help with learning
the same spell for a different convocation.
</para>
</sect4>


<sect4><title>Casting Time</title>
<para>
Most spells can be cast in a single round. If a casting time is
not given for a spell, then assume it can be cast in one round.
Such spells occur during the normal initiative phase within combat.
The Shek-Pvar uses agility x spell skill, with a penalty of -5
per spell rank for their initiative total.
</para>

<para>
Spells which take more than a round to cast always go off at the
end of the round they are cast in. Normally such spells aren't
used in combat situations anyway, so it is rarely of much importance.
</para>

<sect5><title>Distractions during Spell Casting</title>
<para>
If the Shek-Pvar is distracted while casting a spell, then a will
roll may be needed in order to maintain concentration.
If damage is sustained, a will check of difficulty 10 + 5 x body
levels is required. If successful, spell casting may proceed at
-5 per wound.
</para>

<para>
If the Shek-Pvar is knocked from their feet, a difficulty 30 will
check is needed, which allows spell casting to continue at a -15
penalty.
</para>

<para>
If the spell takes a minute or more to cast, then distractions
are less of a problem. Exact penalties are left to the GM's discretion,
but basically, an 8 hour spell will not suffer from missing the
odd few minutes.
</para>
</sect5>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Range</title>
<para>
Spell range gives the maximum distance between caster and target.
Spell ranges are divided into a few categories, which are described
below. Unless otherwise stated in the spell description, there
must be a line of sight between the caster and her target.
</para>

<para>
<variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>Self</term>
    <listitem>
        The spell only affects the caster.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Touch</term>
    <listitem>
        The spell can affect a single touched target.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Reach</term>
    <listitem>
        The spell can affect a target very close to the
        caster, generally out to about three metres.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Eye</term>
    <listitem>
        Spells with a range of eye require substantial
        eye contact with the target. A range of up to
        about ten metres is normally the practical
        maximum. Such spells can also affect by touch.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Near</term>
    <listitem>
        A target out to a range of about fifteen metres
        can be affected by a near spell.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Short</term>
    <listitem>
        Any spell with a range of short can affect targets
        out to a range of about fifty metres.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Medium</term>
    <listitem>
        Medium range spells have a range of 100m.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Far</term>
    <listitem>
        This is the maximum range for most spells, and
        goes out to two hundred metres. Spells which have
        a longer range than this (generally detection type
        spells) have the specific range given.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Duration</title>
<para>
The duration of a spell is how long it lasts after it has been
cast. Most spells are either momentary, or concentration
</para>

<para>
<variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
    <term>Momentary</term>
    <listitem>
        Momentary spells end as soon as they are cast. They
        perform some action (create a flame, change a mind),
        then the magic ends. The results of the magic can
        live on though.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Concentration</term>
    <listitem>
        Any spell with this duration lasts as long as the
        caster continues to concentrate on it. Concentrating
        on a single spell does not preclude other actions -
        including casting other spells. It is even possible
        to concentrate on more than one spell at once, though
        it does get progressively harder.
        <br/>
        The first spell gives a -5 penalty to all actions
        (physical, perceptive and mental) while it is being
        concentrated on. The second spell gives a further -10
        penalty, the third a -15 penalty and so on. All
        penalties are cumulative. Concentrating on three
        spells gives a total -30 penalty.
        <br/>
        If the character suffers body levels of damage when
        concentrating on spells, a will check of difficulty
        5 per body level is needed (remember the penalty for
        concentrating on spells). Failure means that half
        (round up) the spells are dropped. The Shek-Pvar
        chooses which spells to drop.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term>Ward</term>
    <listitem>
        Spells with a duration of ward go dormant when they
        are cast. They can be detected and dispelled while
        dormant, though will rarely have a visible presence.
        When a trigger condition is met (this varies from
        spell to spell), the spell is activated, and its
        powers come into effect. The actual powers of the
        spell generally have a duration of momentary, so
        once the ward has been activated, it terminates.
        <br/>
        Only one ward can be placed on an object, location
        or person at any one time. If a second ward is
        placed, then it automatically fails. A second ward
        cannot be placed within an aura of a living creature.
        It is not possible for a person to carry two items
        which are both warded. One of the wards (choose
        randomly) fails if this happens.
        <br/>
        There are exceptions however. Some wards can be
        stacked with themselves. These are rare, and
        stacking always has other side effects.
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Learning Convocations</title>
<para>
When a Shek-Pvar is first trained, they are trained in a single
convocation. They are attuned to this convocation for the rest
of their life, and with the exception of becoming a Grey Mage,
they cannot change this.
</para>

<para>
Later, it may be possible to learn a different convocation. Secondary
convocations must be learned before a corresponding Tertiary convocation.
'Learned' in this case means up to a level of at least four. The
diametrically opposed convocation can only be learned if both tertiary
convocations are already known to a level of four.
</para>

<para>
It takes about a month to learn the basics of a new convocation,
and there are political matters than need attending to as well.
All this is described under the original Harn Magic rules.
A Satia-Mavari (journeyman) will know their primary convocation
and the neutral convocation when they enter play.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Learning Spells</title>
<para>
Spells can either be learned or invented. Learning can be from
a book, or from a tutor. Inventing spells is a long and difficult
process that can take many months, or even years, so most Shek-Pvar
prefer learning from the work of others, rather than re-inventing
the wheel.
</para>

<para>
For each week that is spent studying or inventing a spell, the
Shek-Pvar rolls on the Experience gained through training table
in Campaign:2. Spells however are quicker to develop than normal
knowledges, so get the following modifiers.
</para>

<para>
There is a bonus to the study total equal to the current convocation
score of the Shek-Pvar. There is a further +1 for every spell
in that convocation which is known at a higher level than the
spell being learned or invented.
</para>

<para>
If the study total is higher than the study difficulty, then 1
experience point is gained in the spell. For every five points
higher than the study difficulty, an extra point of experience
is gained that week.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Grimoires</title>
<para>
Initially written to help mavari in their studies, grimoires have
become quite common at all levels of skill. They are basically
a collection of tracts on a number of different spells. Study of
the grimoire will provide knowledge in each of the spells covered.
</para>

<para>
Like any other book, a grimoire has a level and a quality. When
a week is spent studying the grimoire, for each spell which the
reader has a lower score in than the level of the grimoire, they
get one study gain roll, at the quality of the grimoire. A study
roll is possible even if the student has no skill in the spell.
However, unless the student's skill in the convocation is at least
as high as the level of the grimoire, they will not be able to
understand it at all.
</para>

<sect3><title>Writing a Grimoire</title>
<para>
The author chooses the spells to write about. Any number of spells
can be chosen, however they must all be of the same rank, and the
same convocation.
</para>

<para>
The maximum level of the grimoire is equal to the minimum of
three times the rank of the spells, the lowest score the writer
has in any of the spells, and the writer's convocation score
minus two per spell beyond the first.
</para>

<para>
Multi-level spells count as any rank.
</para>

<para>
The quality of the grimoire is worked out as for other books. The
time taken is as for a standard book of the same level, multiplied
by the number of spells.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>The End of Apprenticeship</title>
<para>
Beginning Shek-Pvar PCs are assumed to have come to the end of
their apprenticeship. They have been released from the bond of
apprenticeship and sent into the world as one of the Satia-Mavari
(journeyman). They are expected to survive on their wits for at
least a year and a day. Any time after that, they may return with
a suitable gift for their chantry. Normally, this consists of
three items of value, and three 'original-arts', meaning spells
the former master does not know how to cast.
</para>

<para>
Most Satia-Mavari take three to five years to complete this part
of their training. After this they may become Shenava (Master)
or Viran (Grandmaster).
</para>

<para>
<import-character-template href="templates/mavari.xml" name="Shek-Pvar Mavari"/>
</para>

<para>
<import-character-template href="templates/mavari.xml" name="Sindarin Shek-Pvar"/>
</para>
</sect1>


<sect1><title>Pvaric Elementals</title>
<para>
Pvarism is restricted to only affected that which is in sight,
and even the more powerful magics are restricted in their effects
at long range. However, the Shek-Pvar do have a way of affecting
that which would otherwise be beyond their reach, and this is
through the use of elementals.
</para>

<para>
Each of the convocations has a type of elemental associated with
it. Elementals are sapient spirits formed from the element of
their convocation. A common use is to use them as scouts, to spy
on places a long way away, or to carry messages between Shek-Pvar.
Elementals range greatly in power, and the individual types will
be described in the section detailing the relevant convocation.
However, a brief guide to them is given here.
</para>

<sect2><title>Types of Elemental</title>
<para>
The strength and capability of an elemental is measured according
to its type. A type I elemental is barely sapient, and has little
physical strength. Type VIII elementals are amongst the most powerful
normally dealt with. They can be quite intelligent, strong willed,
and very powerful physically.
</para>

<para>
Each type of elemental corresponds to a complexity rank for spells.
Most spells to control elementals are multi-level, and also common.
This means a different spell is needed to summon an elemental
of Peleahn instead of a Lyahvi elemental.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="5.5cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Type</entry>
            <entry>Int</entry>
            <entry>Will</entry>
            <entry>Capabilities</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>I</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry>
            <entry>Simple commands only</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>II</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>2</entry>
            <entry>Conditional commands, can relay messages</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>III</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry>
            <entry>Can remember human speech, and act on own initiative</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>IV</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry>
            <entry>As per a human</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>V</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>5</entry>
            <entry>As per a human</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>VI</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>6</entry>
            <entry>As per a human</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>VII</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>7</entry>
            <entry>As per a human</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>VIII</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>8</entry>
            <entry>As per a human</entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>

</table>
</para>

<para>
Though elementals can only speak their own language, types III
and above can remember conversation in languages they do not understand,
and can relay that back to their summoner.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Elemental Statistics</title>
<para>
The following guidelines describe the different types of elementals.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <colspec colwidth="1.5cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth="1cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Elemental</entry>
            <entry>Size</entry>
            <entry>Str</entry>
            <entry>Sta</entry>
            <entry>Agi</entry>
            <entry>Dex</entry>
            <entry>Per</entry>
            <entry>Soak</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row><entry>Earth</entry>
            <entry>3xR</entry><entry>3xR</entry><entry>4</entry>
            <entry>3</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>2</entry>
            <entry>3xR</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Plant</entry>
            <entry>3xR</entry><entry>2xR</entry><entry>5</entry>
            <entry>4</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry>
            <entry>4xR</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Bone</entry>
            <entry>2xR</entry><entry>2xR</entry><entry>3</entry>
            <entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry>
            <entry>4xR</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Flesh</entry>
            <entry>2xR</entry><entry>2xR</entry><entry>3</entry>
            <entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry>
            <entry>2xR</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Stone</entry>
            <entry>3xR</entry><entry>4xR</entry><entry>5</entry>
            <entry>2</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry>
            <entry>6xR</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Iron</entry>
            <entry>2xR</entry><entry>4xR</entry><entry>6</entry>
            <entry>2</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>1</entry>
            <entry>8xR</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Magic</entry>
            <entry>1xR</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>2</entry>
            <entry>7</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>3</entry>
            <entry>0</entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>
</table>
</para>

<para>
Every variety of elemental has the same sort of skills, all of
which improve with the power of the elemental.
</para>

<para>
<table>
    <colspec colwidth="3.25cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth=".75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth=".75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth=".75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth=".75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth=".75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth=".75cm"/>
    <colspec colwidth=".75cm"/>
    <thead>
        <row>
            <entry>Attribute</entry>
            <entry>I</entry>
            <entry>II</entry>
            <entry>III</entry>
            <entry>IV</entry>
            <entry>V</entry>
            <entry>VI</entry>
            <entry>VII</entry>
            <entry>VIII</entry>
        </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <row><entry>Athletics</entry>
            <entry>2</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry>
            <entry>4</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>5</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Awareness</entry>
            <entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>2</entry>
            <entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>4</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Brawl</entry>
            <entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry>
            <entry>5</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>8</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Sleight</entry>
            <entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>2</entry>
            <entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>4</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Stealth</entry>
            <entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>2</entry>
            <entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>4</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Throw</entry>
            <entry>1</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>2</entry>
            <entry>3</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>4</entry>
        </row>
        <row><entry>Single Weapon</entry>
            <entry>0</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry>
            <entry>4</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>7</entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>
</table>
</para>

<sect3><title>Summoning an Elemental</title>

<para>
An elemental is summoned with the use of the Summon Elemental
spell. This is a common spell, and one version of it exists
for each convocation.
</para>

<para>
Summoning an elemental takes one minute. The elemental always
appears next to the summoner, and a will check must be made by
both the summoner and the elemental as soon as it arrives, in
order to see if the elemental is controlled. If control fails,
then the elemental will do as it pleases. Roll a d20, on a
1-19, it returns to where it came from. On a 20, it goes on a
random rampage, attacking anything in sight.
</para>

<para>
Assuming the elemental is controlled, then it can be given
commands. Very simple commands can be given with gestures,
however anything more complicated requires the caster to speak
and understand a Pvaric language. This can normally be done
with the Speak with Elemental spell.
</para>

<para>
The elemental must normally remain within range of the spell.
If the elemental ever leaves the spell range, then another
will check is required to maintain control of the elemental.
On failure, control is lost as when the elemental is first
summoned. Success, allows the elemental to be controlled, but
a further check is required each minute it remains beyond the
normal spell range. An out of range elemental will halt and
rest, awaiting further instruction.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1><title>Minor Artifacts</title>
<para>
Minor artifacts are the most common of the magical items constructed
by Shek-Pvar. They are easy and quick to make, though are temporary
in nature. They tend to be limited to being able to duplicate
effects of a single convocation.
</para>

<sect2><title>Creating a Minor Artifact</title>
<para>
Firstly, an item must be found which is suitable to contain the
powers of a minor artifact. The following suggestions should be
used as a guide when determining what material to use.
</para>

<sect3><title>Foci</title>

<sect4><title>Fyvria</title>
<para>
Wooden or bone staves and wands, or even bags of earth or dried
herbs are good. However, the magic does not convey any protection
to the focus, so weak materials have a down side.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Jmorvi</title>
<para>
Precious metals such as silver and gold, often in the form of
wands, amulets or weapons.
</para>
</sect4>


<sect4><title>Lyahvi</title>
<para>
Transparent, reflective or translucent materials are best used
for Lyahvi artifacts. Gems and glass is good, as are mirrors,
prisms and lenses. Red coloured items also help.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Neutral</title>
<para>
?
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Odivshe</title>
<para>
The colour of Odivshe is blue, so often blue containers of water
or ice are used as foci.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Peleahn</title>
<para>
?
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Savorya</title>
<para>
Representations of knowledge, such as a scroll or book are often
used as a focus. Quills are another favourite.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>


<sect3><title>Preparing the Item</title>
<para>
The item is prepared with the use of Focus, a multi-level common
spell. This purifies the item, giving it a magical aura. This process
takes a day.
</para>

<para>
The rank of the focus used determines the maximum number of charges
that can be placed into the item - one per rank of the spell.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Opening the Item</title>
<para>
The item can now, at any point after the item has been prepared,
be opened for enchantment. The rank I neutral spell Open is used
to do this.
</para>

<para>
While the item is open, Store (multi-level, neutral) can be used
to store spells in the item. Spells are placed into the item in
reverse order to what they are going to be cast in. The rank of
the spell must be no higher than the rank of the Store spell.
As many spells as the item may contain charges can be cast into
the item. Only spells with a casting time of one round can be
placed in the item, and all spells must be of the same convocation
as the original focus.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Closing the Enchantment</title>
<para>
Once all required spells have been stored, the item should be
closed, with Close (I, neutral). At this point the trigger action
for the item can be declared.
</para>

<para>
The minor artifact is now ready for use.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Using Minor Artifacts</title>
<para>
A minor artifact can be used by anyone if the trigger event is
physical (such as a word or action). If the trigger event is a
mental command, then the user must have attuned to the item first,
which more or less restricts the item to Shek-Pvar.
</para>

<para>
When the item is activated, the last spell stored in it is cast
at the target designated by the user.
</para>

<para>
The spell goes off on the initiative of the user. For physical
trigger events, this is agility x 4. For mental trigger events,
this is intelligence x 4.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Decay of Minor Artifacts</title>
<para>
Minor artifacts decay with time. Each month (on the new moon),
the top spell in any minor artifact decays and is lost. Once
all spells have been lost, the item is empty, but will not decay
further.
</para>

<para>
Any minor artifact can be reopened, and new spells stored within
it. If the item is left open for long periods, then one spell
is lost each day, rather than each month.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Major Artifacts</title>
<para>
Major artifacts are more powerful, more flexible and longer lasting
than minor artifacts. They are also more complicated to construct,
and take much longer to make. Whereas a minor artifact can be
constructed in a couple of days, a major artifact can take several
months to build.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Spell Grimoires</title>

<sect2><title>Common Spells</title>
<para>
<import-spells href="spells/common.xml" convocation="common"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Fyvria Spells</title>
<para>
<import-spells href="spells/fyvria.xml" convocation="fyvria"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Jmorvi Spells</title>
<para>
<import-spells href="spells/jmorvi.xml" convocation="jmorvi"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Lyahvi Spells</title>
<para>
<import-spells href="spells/lyahvi.xml" convocation="lyahvi"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Neutral Spells</title>
<para>
<import-spells href="spells/neutral.xml" convocation="neutral"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Odivshe Spells</title>
<para>
<import-spells href="spells/odivshe.xml" convocation="odivshe"/>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Peleahn Spells</title>
<para>
<import-spells href="spells/peleahn.xml" convocation="peleahn"/>
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Savorya Spells</title>
<para>
<import-spells href="spells/savorya.xml" convocation="savorya"/>
</para>
</sect2>


</sect1>

</article>
