<?xml version="1.0"?>

<grimoire convocation="Common">

    <spell name="Attune" level="0" convocation="common">
        <range>Touch</range>
        <duration>Special</duration>
        <time>1 hour</time>
        <description>
            <para>
                This spell is used to create a bond of affinity between
                the caster and an object or enchantment. Attunement is
                the first step towards controlling an enchantment or
                object, and is not actually an end in itself. It will
                only work on enchantments of equal or lower rank.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                Minor artifacts which have a mental trigger action must
                be attuned to before they can be used. Other minor
                artifacts do no require attuning (and hence can be used
                by non-Shek-Pvar). Major artifacts require attuning
                in order to control the artifact, though it may choose
                to use its powers without attunement.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                When an item is attuned to, the Shek-Pvar will know all
                powers in the artifact up to the rank of the <e>Attune</e>,
                as well as knowing the number and convocation of the
                others, and whether they are within two ranks of
                the <e>Attune</e>, or higher.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                Regardless of the rank of the <e>Attune</e>, the trigger
                words or actions for a minor artifact will be known.
                However, for mental triggers, the <e>Attune</e> must
                equal the rank of the spells. Since spells can only be
                cast in order, a single high rank spell in an artifact
                can block the casting of all the other spells.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Focus" level="0" convocation="common">
        <time>1 day</time>
        <range>Touch</range>
        <duration>Special</duration>
        <description>
            <para>
                This spell prepares an item for enchantment as a minor
                artifact. The item should be a suitable foci of the given
                convocation, and this spell enhances link the item has
                with its convocation. The number of spells which can be
                stored in the minor artifact is given by the suitability
                of the item (see table below), multiplied by the rank
                of the <e>Focus</e>.
            </para>
            
            <targetlist>
                <entry target="1" value="Opposed convocation"/>
                <entry target="2" value="Unsuitable"/>
                <entry target="3" value="Suitable"/>
                <entry target="4" value="Highly suitable"/>
                <entry target="+1" value="Marked with runes of convocation"/>
            </targetlist>
            
            <para>
                See the section on making minor artifacts for details
                on what materials and objects are considered suitable.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Summon Elemental" level="0" convocation="common">
        <time>1 minute</time>
        <range>Short (50m)</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+25 Range is medium (100m)</boost>
        <boost>+50 Range is far (200m)</boost>
        <boost>+100 Range is extreme (500m)</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                This spell summons a Pvaric elemental out of some mundane
                quantity of that element. Neutral and Savoryan elementals
                can be summoned anywhere. The size of the elemental varies
                according to the rank of the spell.
            </para>

            <para>
                The elemental must remain within the range of the spell at
                all times. If the Shek-Pvar forces the elemental out of
                range, or circumstances allow this to occur, then she
                looses control of the elemental. Regardless of the spell
                range, the elemental will initially appear within Near
                of the caster.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The caster must make an oppossed will roll to control the
                elemental when it is first summoned. The elemental can be
                communicated with using a suitable Pvaric language.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

    <spell name="Ward Against Elementals" level="0" convocation="common">
        <time>1 round</time>
        <range>Reach</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+25 Range is near</boost>
        <boost>+50 Range is short</boost>
        <boost>+100 Range is medium</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                Prevents elementals of the same convocation from entering
                the area protected. Elementals of equal to or lower rank
                than the rank of this spell are affected.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>


    <spell name="Speak with Elemental" level="10" convocation="common">
        <range>Touch</range>
        <resist>Will</resist>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <boost>+10 Range is near</boost>
        <boost>
            +20 All designated targets within range can speak with
            elementals.
        </boost>
        <boost>
            +40 Targets can speak with all elementals, regardless of the
            elemental's convocation.
        </boost>

        <description>
            <para>
                Enables the target to speak the language of elementals of the
                spell's convocation.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>


    <spell name="Block" level="0" convocation="common">
        <range>Self</range>
        <duration>Concentration</duration>
        <description>
            <para>
                This spell blocks spell of the same convocation from affecting
                the caster assuming that they are of equal or lower rank. The
                caster is also prevented from casting such spells himself,
                regardless of the target of such spells.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>
    
    <spell name="Elemental Bane" level="0" convocation="common">
        <range>Near</range>
        <duration>Momentary</duration>
        <resist>Ego</resist>
        <boost>+25 Range is Short</boost>
        <boost>+50 Up to three elementals affected</boost>
        <boost>+100 Up to 12 elementals affected</boost>
        <description>
            <para>
                When invoked against a particular Elemental, this spell
                causes pain and disruption in the target, destroying
                part of it. One wound level of damage is caused per rank
                of the spell.
            </para>
        </description>
    </spell>

</grimoire>
