<?xml version="1.0"?>

<advantages>

<advantage name="Berseker" type="advantage">
    <cost points="+3">
        <levels max="6"/>
    </cost>
    <description>
    The character is a berserker, making them a fearsome
    opponent in battle. The advantage is taken up to +6,
    with higher levels making the character more fearsome,
    but also less controlled. See the berserker rules under
    Combat for full details about this advantage.
    </description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Language talent" type="advantage">
    <cost points="+3"/>
    <cost points="+4"/>
    <description>
    The character is adept at picking up new languages
    quickly. Any experience placed on spoken language skills
    (excluding the starting score in speak own language) is
    doubled. The higher cost of this advantage includes
    written as well as spoken languages.
    </description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Literate" type="advantage">
    <cost points="+2"/>
    <description>
    The character can read and write any languages they can
    speak. The character starts with a scribe score equal to
    the score of each language skill they start with.
    Languages gained during play are not affected.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Need little sleep" type="advantage">
    <cost points="+2"/>
    <description>
    The character can go for longer without sleep than most
    people. Their stamina is effectively at +1 for purposes
    of sleep deprivation.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Second sight" type="advantage">
    <cost points="+2"/>
    <description>
    You are sensitive to that which is 'not quite right', or
    of a spiritual nature. You are often not aware that what
    you can sense, other's cannot - you cannot obviously tell
    what is natural and what isn't.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Tough" type="advantage">
    <cost points="+3"/>
    <cost points="+6"/>
    <cost points="+12"/>
    <description>
    The character gets a bonus to basic soak of +1, +2 or +3
    depending on the level of this advantage.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Albino" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <description>
    The character is an albino. Skin are hair are white,
    and eyes are pink. They will often suffer sun burn in
    bright sunlight, and suffer double range penalties.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Anosmia" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-1"/>
    <description>
    The character has no sense of taste nor smell.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Blind" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-10"/>
    <description>
    The character is completely blind. This disadvantage
    cannot be combined with any other that affects sight.
    </description>
    <forbiddon>Poor vision</forbiddon>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Branded criminal" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <cost points="-5"/>
    <description>
    You have been marked as a criminal. -2 point
    disadvantage for petty theft or something similar,
    -5 for something major (maybe dishonour in a society
    which highly values honour) which will cause major
    social problems.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Code of honour (Bodyguard's)" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-5"/>
    <description>
    Body guard's code of honour (-5): Guard your charge with
    your life - at the expense of it if necessary. Never shirk
    on your duties. You're only being paid to protect your
    charge, not anyone else. If bystanders get hurt, that's
    their problem. Life isn't fair, use whatever advantages
    you can in combat.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Code of honour (Gang member's)" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <description>
    Always avenge an insult, your friend's foe is your own,
    never attack a fellow gang member except in a fair duel.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Code of honour (Healer's)" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-5"/>
    <description>
    Always help anyone in need of aid, give generously to
    the poor. Put the needs of others before your own.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Code of honour (Mercenary's)" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <description>
    Don't change sides in a war, whatever you're offered
    to do so. Stay to the end, but not necessarily at the
    expense of your life. Accept the surrender of others,
    since one day you may want others to accept your
    surrender. Treat prisoners fairly.
    </description>
</advantage>

<advantage name="Code of honour (Warrior's)" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-5"/>
    <description>
    Never break your word, never ignore an insult to yourself
    or to your lord. Give hospitality where requested, and
    respect it when given. Avenge those of your family. Never
    take advantage of a worthy opponent, weapons and
    circumstances must be equal.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Code of honour (Chivalric)" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-10"/>
    <description>
    As for a warrior's, but also you must protect those
    weaker than yourself. You must accept any challenge
    to arms from those of equal or greater rank. Even in
    war, sides must be equal against noble and chivalric
    foes.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Colour blind" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <description>
    The character cannot distinguish certain colours,
    often red and green, though other combinations are
    possible.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Combat paralysis" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-4"/>
    <description>
    You are not good at reacting to combat or other
    dangerous situations. You spend the first round of any
    combat dithering about what to do.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Dark secret" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <cost points="-5"/>
    <description>
    You have a secret in your past which is best left
    hidden. If someone were to find it out, or to make it
    public, your life could become quite complicated. This
    is a -2 disadvantage if the secret would be annoying
    if let out, or -5 if it would be a serious risk to
    your health (you were a member of some particularly
    reviled cult for instance).
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Delusion" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-1"/>
    <cost points="-3"/>
    <cost points="-6"/>
    <cost points="-10"/>
    <description>
    The character suffers from a delusion of some kind,
    believing something to be true which very obviously
    isn't. A one point delusion is minor, and won't have
    that much affect. Something like believing that all
    squirrels are spying on everyone is only one point.
    The delusion that squirrels plan on enslaving everyone
    in their nut mines might be three points, if the
    character goes out of their way to avoid squirrels,
    and insists on warning people. Continuously hunting
    for the squirrel's secret nut mines, and hiring people
    to guard against evil squirrel armies would be six
    points. Likewise, belief that the character is a
    Shek-Pvar when they aren't might be six points.
    Belief that they are the king, and ordering everyone
    around would be ten points, since the character is
    likely to end up in trouble with the real king pretty
    quickly.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Epileptic" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-4"/>
    <description>
    The character suffers from epilepsy, or some similar
    disorder. When under stress, they are liable to have
    a seizure which will last several minutes. Under a
    moment of extreme stress, roll a d20. On an 18+, the
    character suffers a seizure.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Eunuch" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-1"/>
    <description>
    Available only to male characters. This may be due to
    an accident, or through choice on the part of someone.
    The character has no interest in sex. There may be a
    social stigma related to this if people find out.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Favours" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <description>
    You owe favours to a person, who will call them in at
    some point. Repaying the favours should not be a great
    hardship, but ignoring them will gain you a bad
    reputation (and possibly an enemy).
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Geas" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-1"/>
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <cost points="-5"/>
    <cost points="-8"/>
    <description>
    You have a geas which, if broken, will bring misfortune
    down on you. Types of geas are similar to vows (trivial,
    minor, major and legendary), but are somewhat worse.
    Breaking a geas will bring a lot of bad luck.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Honesty" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-4"/>
    <description>
    You don't like to break the law. You can lie, as long as
    it doesn't involve breaking the law.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Innumerate" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-4"/>
    <description>
    You are unable to count above ten, and even then you
    need to do lots of work on your fingers. Numbers above
    three are about all you can cope with easily.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Leprosy" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-15"/>
    <description>
    You have leprosy, and as such are a social outcast
    (you cannot take any social status). You probably smell
    of rotting flesh, and people will do their best to avoid
    (or destroy) you. Your appearance is automatically -5.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Look young" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-3"/>
    <description>
    This disadvantage can only be taken by characters
    between 16 and 19. They look very young - possibly
    12 or 13 - and people will treat them as being of
    such an age.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Loud voice" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-3"/>
    <description>
    Character has a very loud voice, and has difficulty
    keeping it down. If trying to speak quietly, they must
    make a will roll of difficulty 20 in order to succeed.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Missing hand" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-4"/>
    <description>
    The character is missing a hand. It is assumed that it
    is their off-hand.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Missing limb" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-8"/>
    <description>
    The character is missing either an arm or a leg. They
    possibly lost it due to injury, or they were born
    without it. If they are missing multiple limbs, then
    it is a further -4 disadvantage per limb beyond the
    first.
    </description>>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Nightmares" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-3"/>
    <description>
    The character's sleep is continuously disturbed by
    terrible dreams, from which they can awake screaming,
    soaked in sweat. The character may have difficulties
    getting a full nights sleep.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Noticeable mark" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-1"/>
    <cost points="-3"/>
    <description>
    The character has a strange and obvious mark on their
    body. This is a -1 disadvantage if it isn't normally
    visible, -3 otherwise.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Odious personal habit" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-1"/>
    <cost points="-3"/>
    <cost points="-6"/>
    <description>
    The character has a disgusting habit which others find
    repulsive. It could be continuous humming (one point),
    continuous swearing or nose picking (3 points) or
    habits which should never ever be done in public (six
    points). This disadvantage will give big penalties in
    social situations.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Orphan" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-1"/>
    <description>
    The character is an orphan, with no parents or immediate
    family to stand up for you.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Pawn of Darkness" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-4"/>
    <description>
    Either from birth, or because of some event in your
    youth, your life is plagued by the interventions of dark
    powers, be they demons, fey or gods. Alternatively, it
    may have been prophesied that such will come about later
    in your life.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Sexually tantalising" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <description>
    You seem to attract members of a compatible sex. For
    anyone else this would be a good thing, except that in
    your case it is always the people whom you don't want
    to attract which are attracted to you. You must have
    attractive to take this drawback.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Voracious appetite" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <description>
    You need to eat twice as much as everyone else. This
    is not the same as being greedy, since you really do
    need to eat this much to stay alive.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Vow" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-1"/>
    <cost points="-2"/>
    <cost points="-5"/>
    <cost points="-8"/>
    <description>
    You have sworn an oath, either to yourself or to a
    higher power (either mortal or godly). Warriors will
    often make oaths at the beginning of each year, vowing
    to complete some task. This type of vow can be taken,
    in which case a new one of the same value should be
    taken at the start of each year.
    <br/>
    A vow can be trivial (1 point), always wear red, never
    eat the meat of a dog; minor (2 points), chastity, vow
    of silence during the day, never ride a horse; major
    (5 points), never sleep indoors, own no more than you
    can carry, never strike someone who has not attacked
    you first, never let an insult go unchallenged;
    legendary (8 points), never refuse a request for aid,
    challenge every warrior you meet to combat, kill a man
    every month.
    </description>
</advantage>


<advantage name="Youth" type="disadvantage">
    <cost points="-3"/>
    <cost points="-6"/>
    <cost points="-9"/>
    <cost points="-12"/>
    <description>
    You start the game younger than the normal base of 16.
    For each year younger than this, it is a -3 disadvantage,
    and you start with 6 less experience. The youngest you may
    start is 12 years old, in which case you start with general
    skills and 6 points of professional skills.. As well as
    lacking skills, people will treat you as a young upstart,
    and not take you seriously.
    </description>
</advantage>

</advantages>
